<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="225">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01856335</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130127</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-N-0127</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01856335</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise Education for Adults With Seizure Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Increasing Self-Efficacy and Outcome Expectations For Exercise in Adults With Epilepsy: An Educational Motivation Intervention - E-MOVE</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Population

      -People with seizures benefit from regular exercise. Exercise may help decrease the number
      of seizures they have. It also improves overall health and quality of life. However, people
      with seizure disorders often have been prevented from doing sports or other regular physical
      activity. They may also feel that exercise or injury can increase their risk of seizures.
      Researchers want to try an exercise program for people who have seizures to see if they can
      increase motivation to exercise which will improve overall health and may decrease the
      frequency of seizures.

      Objectives:

      - To see how exercise education improves motivation to exercise in people who have a history
      of seizures.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have a history of seizures.

      Design:

        -  This study involves three outpatient visits and weekly telephone calls for about 12
           weeks. There will be followup calls at about 6 and 12 months after the outpatient
           visits.

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. They will
           answer questions about their current level of physical activity, mood, quality of life,
           and ideas about exercise.

        -  At the first visit, participants will learn how to keep a physical activity log and
           seizure calendar. They will also use an activity monitor and take their pulse
           regularly. They will complete questionnaires about their mood and thoughts about
           exercise and seizures.

        -  At the second visit, participants will set personal activity goals and learn about
           physical activity and seizures. They will review the physical activity log, seizure
           log, and activity monitor and pulse readings for the previous 4 weeks.

        -  After the second visit, participants will receive weekly telephone calls. Each call
           will last about 5 minutes. These calls will ask about physical activities for the week
           and participants' progress toward meeting their goals. These calls will also review the
           seizure log.

        -  At the third visit (12 weeks), the same tests from the first visit will be repeated.

        -  The followup phone calls will continue to monitor participants' activity levels.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      To see what keeps people with seizures from exercising and see how they can increase their
      belief that they can exercise and that exercise will help them.

      Study Population:

      50 adults with seizures

      Design:

      In this protocol, we will pilot the use of an educational intervention to provide people
      with seizure disorders an opportunity to learn about the benefits of exercise and learn
      specifically what types of exercise to incorporate into their daily lives.

      Outcome Measures:

      To assess the effectiveness of the educational intervention, we will use pre and post
      intervention measures including seizure specific measures of self-efficacy (belief that they
      can exercise) and outcome expectations (belief that exercise will help them) for exercise.
      To assess changes in physical activity, seizure frequency, and mood, we will monitor
      physical activity and seizure calendars, activity monitor recordings, and mood rating
      scales.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 0</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self-efficacy for exercise score following the E-MOVE intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Outocme Expectations for exercise score following the E-MOVE intervention.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Seizures</condition>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Education</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Able to use seizure calendars to record seizures throughout the study

        English speaking

        Able to provide informed consent

        Diagnosed with epilepsy by standard clinical criteria.

        Age 18 years and older

        Enrolled in evaluation and treatment of epilepsy protocol 01-N-0139

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Do not have health care provider clearance to participate in a physical activity program
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Irene H Dustin, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Irene H Dustin, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-9284</phone>
    <email>id30d@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-N-0127.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arida RM, Cavalheiro EA, da Silva AC, Scorza FA. Physical activity and epilepsy: proven and predicted benefits. Sports Med. 2008;38(7):607-15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18557661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arida RM, Scorza CA, Schmidt B, de Albuquerque M, Cavalheiro EA, Scorza FA. Physical activity in sudden unexpected death in epilepsy: much more than a simple sport. Neurosci Bull. 2008 Dec;24(6):374-80. doi: 10.1007/s12264-008-0805-z. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19037323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arida RM, Scorza FA, Cavalheiro EA. Favorable effects of physical activity for recovery in temporal lobe epilepsy. Epilepsia. 2010 Jul;51 Suppl 3:76-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1528-1167.2010.02615.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20618406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>April 3, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 10, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Seizures</keyword>
  <keyword>Epilepsy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Seizures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
