<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1220">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02308579</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDUS1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02308579</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Centralized Reading Assessment of Chronic CerebroSpinal Venous Insufficiency (CCSVI) in Patients With Multiple Sclerosis and Other Neurological Diseases</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prevalence of Chronic Cerebrospinal Venous Insufficiency in Patients With Multiple Sclerosis and Other Neurological Diseases. An Ultrasound, Blinded, Case-Controlled, Centralized Reading Assessment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University at Buffalo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pavia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University at Buffalo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This a retrospective, blinded trial in which collaborators in Italy will review the doppler
      findings from the Combined Transcranial and Extracranial Venous Doppler (CTEVD) trial in an
      attempt to measure reproducibility.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will retrospectively investigate doppler images from the second phase of the
      CTEVD trial.

        1. To determine the prevalence of CCSVI in patients with MS, compared with the prevalence
           observed in a control population consisting of Other Neurological Diseases (OND)
           patients and Healthy Controls (HC) by using blinded, controlled centralized ultrasound
           reading assessment of 5 Venous Haemodynamic (VH) CCSVI CCSVI Doppler UltraSound (CDUS)
           criteria.

        2. To investigate whether prevalence of CCSVI is different between centralized and local
           CDUS reading of 5 VH CCSVI CDUS criteria.

        3. To investigate the prevalence of CCSVI in patients with MS, compared with the
           prevalence observed in a control population consisting of OND patients and HC, when
           bidirectional flow in the intracranial veins and sinuses CDUS criterion is not
           considered as part of VH CCSVI CDUS criteria.

        4. To determine whether prevalence of CCSVI in patients with MS, compared with the
           prevalence observed in a control population consisting of OND patients and HC differs
           when using CDUS velocity and flow parameters in the Internal Jugular Veins (IJVs) and
           Vertebral Veins (VVs).

        5. To determine the reproducibility of VH criteria by using of centralized and local
           blinded, controlled CDUS reading assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case Control, Time Perspective: Retrospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of MS (or CIS) and HC (or OND) who have 5 VH CCSVI CDUS criteria on doppler ultrasound</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The prevalence (number) of MS/CIS vs. HC/OND who fulfill the 5 venous haemodynamic (VH) criteria on doppler ultrasound.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">499</enrollment>
  <condition>Clinically Isolated Syndrome (CIS)</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis (MS)</condition>
  <condition>Other Neurological Disorders (OND)</condition>
  <condition>Healthy (HC)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multiple Sclerosis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with Multiple Sclerosis (MS), identified in the CTEVD trial</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clinically Isolated Syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with Clinically Isolated Syndrome (CIS), identified in the CTEVD trial.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Other Neurological Disorders</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with Other Neurological Disorders (OND), identified in the CTEVD trial. ONDs fall into one of four categories: Neurodegenerative, Vascular, Autoimmune, and Neuromuscular; and the following disorders: Acute Disseminated Encephalomyelitis (ADEM); Antiphospholipid Antibody (syndrome; APLA); Atypical, short-lasting neurodegenerative disease; Autoimmune disease not otherwise specified (NOS); Cerebellum Syndrome; Charcot-Marie Tooth Disease; Chiari Malformation; Chronic Fatigue Syndrome; Central Nervous System Vasculitis; Demyelinating Disease; Epilepsy; Headaches; Idiopathic Chronic Neuropathy; Migraines; Mitochondrial Disease; Myelopathy; Neurofibromatosis; Neuropathy; Optic Neuritis; Parasthesia related to Transient Ischemic Attacks (TIA); Parkinson's Disease; Restless legs syndrome; Seizures; Spinal Cerebellum Disease; Spinal Disc Degeneration; Syringomyelia; and Vertigo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals who are healthy (i.e., free from neurological conditions; HC) , identified in the CTEVD trial.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants in this study will be those who had participated in the second phase of the
        Combined Transcranial/Extracranial Venous Deficiency (CTEVD) study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participation in the CTEVD Phase 2 study

          -  Available CDUS exam

          -  Diagnosed with CIS, MS, OND, or being a HC

          -  Fulfilling inclusion criteria from the CTEVD study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not having an available CDUS exam

          -  Diagnosed with Radiologically Isolated Syndrome (RIS) or Neuromyelitis Optic (NMO)

          -  Fulfilling exclusion criteria from the CTEVD study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Zivadinov, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University at Buffalo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>December 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>December 4, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 8, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University at Buffalo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert Zivadinov, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Venous Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
