<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1302">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02240394</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Shanghai6thPeoplesH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02240394</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TCD Detection of Ophthalmic Artery Blood Flow Velocity Prediction Feasibility Study of Intracranial Pressure</brief_title>
  <official_title>TCD Detection of Ophthalmic Artery Blood Flow Velocity Prediction Feasibility Study of Intracranial Pressure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai Jiao Tong University Affiliated Sixth People’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai Jiao Tong University Affiliated Sixth People’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>China: Science and Technology Commission of Shanghai Municipality</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Increased intracranial pressure is a cause of disease progression in patients with brain
      disease, a common cause of poor prognosis. Intracranial pressure monitoring is the
      observation of the disease, treatment, evaluation and important way to improve the
      prognosis. Non-invasive intracranial pressure monitoring can be used to stroke, intracranial
      hemorrhage, brain trauma, encephalitis and other patients. Ophthalmic artery originated from
      the internal carotid artery, the optic canal into the orbit, the entire process can be
      divided into intracranial optic tube segment and orbital segment. investigators' preliminary
      experiments show that when intracranial pressure, intracranial ophthalmic artery segment
      velocity increases with increasing velocity difference orbital segment. Accordingly, the
      investigators speculate, may be judged by the level of intracranial pressure intracranial
      and orbital velocity difference between the ophthalmic artery segment, and accordingly
      calculate the specific values of intracranial pressure. The investigators will collect brain
      trauma surgery, performed invasive intracranial pressure monitoring cases, the use of
      transcranial Doppler ultrasound velocity and different segments of the ophthalmic artery
      pulsatility index, the invasive intracranial pressure and comparing the measured values to
      calculate the the critical value of the ophthalmic artery segment intraorbital and
      intracranial velocity difference when intracranial pressure, thus fitting Based on
      projections of mathematical formulas intracranial pressure. This study will provide a
      non-invasive intracranial pressure monitor new approach.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      2014/08/28
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Cohort, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ophthalmic artery blood flow rate changes associated with intracranial pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;up to 6 months&quot;</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the change of the Ophthalmic artery peak sistolic velocity associated with intracranial pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;up to 6 months&quot;</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>the change of the Ophthalmic artery end diastolic velocity associated with intracranial pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;up to 6 months&quot;</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Cerebral Hemorrhage</condition>
  <condition>Increased Intracranial Pressure</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Traumatic brain injury patients has been in patients with invasive intracranial pressure
        monitoring
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. age 18-75 years of age (including 18 and 75 years), gender, ethnic limitation;

          2. have been carried out invasive intracranial pressure monitoring;

          3. the patient or his agent informed consent. -

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. the patient does not fit, measured by TCD can not be completed;

          2. TCD failed to detect the satisfaction of the ophthalmic artery flow signals were;

          3. patients with ocular trauma or a history of intraocular pressure -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wang X Ming, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>World Health Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NCU</name>
      <address>
        <city>ShangHai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200030</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ragauskas A, Matijosaitis V, Zakelis R, Petrikonis K, Rastenyte D, Piper I, Daubaris G. Clinical assessment of noninvasive intracranial pressure absolute value measurement method. Neurology. 2012 May 22;78(21):1684-91. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e3182574f50. Epub 2012 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22573638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 10, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 3, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shanghai Jiao Tong University Affiliated Sixth People's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Xueming Wang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief Physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TCD Traumatic brain injury increased intracranial pressure</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intracranial Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
