<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="625">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02030015</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Syner_G_Regimen</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02030015</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Synergistic Enteral Regimen for Treatment of the Gangliosidoses</brief_title>
  <acronym>Syner-G</acronym>
  <official_title>Synergistic Enteral Regimen for Treatment of the Gangliosidoses (Syner-G)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Data and Safety Monitoring Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesize that a combination therapy using miglustat and the ketogenic
      diet for infantile and juvenile patients with gangliosidoses will create a synergy that 1)
      improves overall survival for patients with infantile or juvenile gangliosidoses, and 2)
      improves neurodevelopmental clinical outcomes of therapy, compared to data reported in
      previous natural history studies. The ketogenic diet is indicated for management of seizures
      in patients with seizure disorders. The ketogenic diet has been used for seizure management
      for more than 100 years. In this study, the ketogenic diet will be used to minimize or
      prevent gastrointestinal side-effects of miglustat, and to improve central nervous system
      response to miglustat therapy. Patients with infantile and juvenile gangliosidoses do
      commonly suffer from seizure disorders, and use of the ketogenic diet in these patients may
      therefore also improve seizure management.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The infantile and juvenile forms of GM1 and GM2 gangliosidoses are neurodegenerative
      conditions that are lethal during childhood. There are no known effective therapies
      available for treatment of infantile and juvenile gangliosidoses. Studies of monotherapy
      with miglustat for treatment of these conditions have demonstrated safety, but have not
      demonstrated notable clinical improvement. To date, combination therapy for the infantile
      and juvenile gangliosidoses has not been explored. This study will evaluate a multi-targeted
      combination therapy for treatment of the gangliosidoses, using FDA approved therapies that
      have demonstrated safety in children. It is the aim of this study to learn if combination
      therapy using the &quot;Syner-G&quot; regimen (that is, synergistic enteral regimen for treatment of
      the gangliosidoses) will show significant increase in overall survival and clinical benefits
      in neurodevelopmental abilities in children with gangliosidosis diseases.

      This study is planned as a 5-year longitudinal treatment study. Subjects will be started on
      the treatment regimen when they are enrolled in the study. Data will be collected during
      yearly evaluations and at completion of study. Investigators may choose to stop therapy at
      any time, as clinically indicated for individual patients.

      The Ketogenic Diet is a special diet that contains higher amounts of fat and lower amounts
      of carbohydrate compared to an average diet. The purpose of this is to help the miglustat be
      more effective in the central nervous system, and to reduce food-miglustat interactions. It
      may also help in management of seizures. The goal is to have 4 parts of fat for every 1 part
      of protein/carbohydrate. Each research subject's caregiver(s) will work with ketogenic diet
      teams that will include a ketogenic dietitian, a neurologist trained in the ketogenic diet,
      and a pharmacist, to help their child to achieve this diet goal. Caregiver(s) will be
      working with a ketogenic diet team at the University of Minnesota, and also with their local
      ketogenic diet team. There will be close and frequent ongoing communication between the two
      ketogenic diet teams, and with the research subject's caregiver(s).

      Miglustat will be used to reduce the amount of ganglioside accumulation in the child's
      cells. Miglustat is not FDA approved for treatment of the gangliosidoses. It is FDA approved
      for a different inherited metabolic disease called Gaucher disease type I. The dose of
      miglustat will increase every 2 weeks until the child reaches a goal dose of 300 mg per day.
      It will take approximately 8 weeks to reach the full dose of miglustat. This dose titration
      process may take longer if the child needs more time to adjust to each dose level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The duration of survival of each research subject, measured in months and years</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of enrollment until 60 months thereafter, or the date of subject's death from any cause, whichever comes first, assessed up to 60 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The survival duration of patients with infantile and juvenile forms of gangliosidoses will be assessed, in order to judge the clinical impact of the Syner-G therapy regimen. This will be accomplished by recording the subject's age on the date of enrollment in this study, and the subject's age at the conclusion of this study, or on the date of their death, whichever comes first. The duration of each subject's survival, expressed in months and years, will be compared to available natural history data and the investigators' extensive clinical experience, in order to arrive at an expert assessment of the impact of the Syner-G therapy upon patient longevity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Change in Adaptive Behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Upon Enrollment, and thereafter at 12, 24, 36, 48 and 60 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales will be administered upon enrollment and annually thereafter for five years. The assessed functional domain is the research subject's adaptive behavior. The rate of change in the resulting adaptive behavior data (i.e. slope) will be calculated over the duration of follow-up, and will be compared to available natural history data. This measurement and analysis will be performed separately for each of the two gangliosidoses sub-types: infantile-onset and juvenile-onset.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Changes in Research Subjects' Seizure Frequency and Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Upon Enrollment, and thereafter at 12, 24, 36, 48 and 60 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in research subjects' seizure frequency and severity will be assessed by a qualified neurologist, using interviews of the research subjects' caregivers. This assessment will be performed upon enrollment and annually for five years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Changes in Research Subjects' Movement Disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>Upon Enrollment, and thereafter at 12, 24, 36, 48 and 60 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Changes in research subjects' movement disorders, if any movement disorders are present, will be assessed by a qualified neurologist, using interviews of the research subjects' caregivers. This assessment will be performed upon enrollment and annually for five years.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Change in Neurocognitive Functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Upon Enrollment, and thereafter at 12, 24, 36, 48 and 60 months post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development will be administered upon enrollment and annually thereafter for five years. The rate of change in the resulting neurocognitive functional domains data (i.e. slope) will be calculated over the duration of follow-up, and will be compared to available natural history data. This measurement and analysis will be performed separately for each of the two gangliosidoses sub-types: infantile-onset and juvenile-onset.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>GM1 Gangliosidoses</condition>
  <condition>GM2 Gangliosidoses</condition>
  <condition>Tay-Sachs Disease</condition>
  <condition>Sandhoff Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Syner-G Therapy Regimen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Syner-G therapy regimen includes switching the research subject to a full-time ketogenic diet, and daily treatment with orally-administered miglustat, for the duration of the 60-month study.
The miglustat oral dose will be gradually titrated over approximately 8 weeks to a goal-dose of 100 mg 3 times daily in the pediatric patients in this study. The specific details of the 8-week dose-titration schedule greatly exceed the maximum number of characters permitted in this field. Please contact the investigators for these specific details.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>miglustat</intervention_name>
    <description>The Syner-G therapy regimen includes treating with orally-administered miglustat for the duration of the 60-month study.
The miglustat dose will be gradually titrated over approximately 8 weeks to a goal-dose of 100 mg 3 times daily in the pediatric patients in this study. The specific details of the 8-week dose-titration schedule greatly exceed the maximum number of characters permitted in this field. Please contact the investigators for these specific details.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Syner-G Therapy Regimen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zavesca®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketogenic Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>The Syner-G therapy regimen includes switching the research subject to a full-time ketogenic diet for the 60-month duration of this study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Syner-G Therapy Regimen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects must have a documented infantile or juvenile gangliosidosis disease.

          2. Age: 17 years or less at time of enrollment

          3. Subjects and their caregivers must work closely with their University of Minnesota
             ketogenic diet team, and with their local ketogenic diet team, which must include a
             ketogenic dietician and a neurologist trained in the ketogenic diet.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. A desire to not participate

          2. Patients who are older than 17 years will not be enrolled in this study.

          3. Children with severe renal impairment will not be enrolled in this study.

          4. Post-pubertal females who are pregnant, or who are unwilling to use highly-effective
             methods to prevent pregnancy, will be excluded from this study.

          5. Breast-feeding females will be excluded from this study.

          6. Subjects who have an allergy to miglustat or any of the components within the drug
             product will be excluded from this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>204 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeanine R. Utz, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota Fairview Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jeanine R. Utz, PharmD</last_name>
    <phone>612-626-5131</phone>
    <email>utzx0002@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Evelyn S. Redtree, M.S.</last_name>
    <phone>612-625-0974</phone>
    <email>eredtree@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jeanine R. Utz, PharmD</last_name>
      <phone>612-626-5131</phone>
      <email>utzx0002@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Evelyn S. Redtree, M.S.</last_name>
      <phone>612-625-0974</phone>
      <email>eredtree@umn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeanine R. Utz, PharmD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chester B. Whitley, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.orpha.net/consor/cgi-bin/Disease_Search_Simple.php?lng=EN&amp;diseaseGroup=Gangliosidosis</url>
    <description>Orphanet links to detailed information about the gangliosidoses</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bley AE, Giannikopoulos OA, Hayden D, Kubilus K, Tifft CJ, Eichler FS. Natural history of infantile G(M2) gangliosidosis. Pediatrics. 2011 Nov;128(5):e1233-41. doi: 10.1542/peds.2011-0078. Epub 2011 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22025593</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nalini A, Christopher R. Cerebral glycolipidoses: clinical characteristics of 41 pediatric patients. J Child Neurol. 2004 Jun;19(6):447-52.</citation>
    <PMID>15446395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maegawa GH, Stockley T, Tropak M, Banwell B, Blaser S, Kok F, Giugliani R, Mahuran D, Clarke JT. The natural history of juvenile or subacute GM2 gangliosidosis: 21 new cases and literature review of 134 previously reported. Pediatrics. 2006 Nov;118(5):e1550-62. Epub 2006 Oct 2. Review. Erratum in: Pediatrics. 2007 Oct;120(4):936.</citation>
    <PMID>17015493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maegawa GH, van Giersbergen PL, Yang S, Banwell B, Morgan CP, Dingemanse J, Tifft CJ, Clarke JT. Pharmacokinetics, safety and tolerability of miglustat in the treatment of pediatric patients with GM2 gangliosidosis. Mol Genet Metab. 2009 Aug;97(4):284-91. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2009.04.013. Epub 2009 May 3.</citation>
    <PMID>19447653</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shapiro BE, Pastores GM, Gianutsos J, Luzy C, Kolodny EH. Miglustat in late-onset Tay-Sachs disease: a 12-month, randomized, controlled clinical study with 24 months of extended treatment. Genet Med. 2009 Jun;11(6):425-33. doi: 10.1097/GIM.0b013e3181a1b5c5.</citation>
    <PMID>19346952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Belmatoug N, Burlina A, Giraldo P, Hendriksz CJ, Kuter DJ, Mengel E, Pastores GM. Gastrointestinal disturbances and their management in miglustat-treated patients. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2011 Oct;34(5):991-1001. doi: 10.1007/s10545-011-9368-7. Epub 2011 Jul 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21779792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kossoff EH, Zupec-Kania BA, Amark PE, Ballaban-Gil KR, Christina Bergqvist AG, Blackford R, Buchhalter JR, Caraballo RH, Helen Cross J, Dahlin MG, Donner EJ, Klepper J, Jehle RS, Kim HD, Christiana Liu YM, Nation J, Nordli DR Jr, Pfeifer HH, Rho JM, Stafstrom CE, Thiele EA, Turner Z, Wirrell EC, Wheless JW, Veggiotti P, Vining EP; Charlie Foundation, Practice Committee of the Child Neurology Society; Practice Committee of the Child Neurology Society; International Ketogenic Diet Study Group. Optimal clinical management of children receiving the ketogenic diet: recommendations of the International Ketogenic Diet Study Group. Epilepsia. 2009 Feb;50(2):304-17. doi: 10.1111/j.1528-1167.2008.01765.x. Epub 2008 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>18823325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zaroff CM, Neudorfer O, Morrison C, Pastores GM, Rubin H, Kolodny EH. Neuropsychological assessment of patients with late onset GM2 gangliosidosis. Neurology. 2004 Jun 22;62(12):2283-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15210895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bembi B, Marchetti F, Guerci VI, Ciana G, Addobbati R, Grasso D, Barone R, Cariati R, Fernandez-Guillen L, Butters T, Pittis MG. Substrate reduction therapy in the infantile form of Tay-Sachs disease. Neurology. 2006 Jan 24;66(2):278-80.</citation>
    <PMID>16434676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 18, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 17, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>infantile Tay-Sachs disease</keyword>
  <keyword>juvenile Tay-Sachs disease</keyword>
  <keyword>infantile GM1 gangliosidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>juvenile GM1 gangliosidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>infantile GM2 gangliosidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>juvenile GM2 gangliosidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Sandhoff disease</keyword>
  <keyword>gangliosidoses</keyword>
  <keyword>miglustat</keyword>
  <keyword>ketogenic diet</keyword>
  <keyword>SYNER-G regimen</keyword>
  <keyword>Syner-G</keyword>
  <keyword>Zavesca</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Gangliosidoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gangliosidoses, GM2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gangliosidosis, GM1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sandhoff Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tay-Sachs Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Miglustat</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
