<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="972">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00809055</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08-0849</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NIH RO1HD057098-01</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HRPO 08-0849</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00809055</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) and Neurodevelopmental Outcomes in Preterm Infants Following Administration of High-Dose Caffeine</brief_title>
  <official_title>Magnetic Resonance Imaging and Neurodevelopmental Outcomes in Preterm Infants Following Administration of High-Dose Caffeine - A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Over the last 30 years the survival rates for babies born prematurely have improved greatly
      with research. As these babies grow up, we have found that many of the premature babies have
      learning and movement problems. The purpose of this research is to learn why premature
      infants are at risk for learning disabilities and movement problems later in childhood and
      whether this is changed by caffeine therapy. Caffeine is often used in premature babies to
      help them to breathe on their own. Nearly all babies born before 30 weeks gestation receive
      caffeine while they are in the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU). Scientists have shown
      that caffeine therapy given to premature babies reduces their disabilities.

      We will use brain monitoring, including electro-encephalogram (EEG) and magnetic resonance
      imaging (MRI) to understand how the brain of a premature baby develops and whether caffeine
      in high doses enhances protection of the developing brain. Just as we monitor the heart and
      lungs to improve our care of premature babies, we wish to monitor the brain so that we can
      understand how to improve our care for the brain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Apnea is defined as a cessation of breathing for twenty seconds or greater, or as a brief
      episode if associated with bradycardia, cyanosis, or pallor. Recurrent apnea of prematurity
      occurs in up to 85% of infants born under 1000g. Standard treatment of care for apnea of
      prematurity is the administration of methylxanthines, specifically caffeine citrate, as a
      respiratory stimulant. This class of pharmacotherapy is a nonselective inhibitor of
      adenosine receptors. Adenosine inhibits respiratory neural output both directly and through
      interactions with another inhibitor of respiratory control, GABA. Adenosine A1 receptors are
      also thought to play a role in hypoxia-induced brain injury, and features of perinatal white
      matter injury have been observed in rodents treated with A1AR agonists during early
      postnatal life. By inhibiting adenosine effects, caffeine may play a role in preventing
      white matter injury. Recently, caffeine therapy for apnea of prematurity has been shown to
      improve the rate of survival without neurodevelopmental disability at 18 to 21 months,
      reduce the incidence of cerebral palsy, and reduce the incidence of cognitive delay in
      infants with very low birth weight.

      In the last five years, multiple trials have studied the effects of using higher doses of
      caffeine citrate in the treatment of apnea of prematurity. Steer compared the efficacy of
      three dosing regimens of caffeine citrate (3, 15, and 30 mg/kg) and found that higher doses
      of caffeine correlated with less documented apnea and less time with oxygen saturations
      &lt;85%. The effectiveness of higher caffeine doses was confirmed when Scanlon showed that a
      loading dose of 50 mg/kg of caffeine citrate is more effective in reducing apneic episodes
      within eight hours than a caffeine citrate loading dose of 25 mg/kg. Studies evaluating the
      long-term neurologic effects of higher doses of methylxanthines, however, have resulted in
      conflicting conclusions. For patients at 12 months of corrected gestational age, Steer found
      a higher incidence of major disabilities in the low dose caffeine group compared with the
      high-dose group (18% to 7.5%). Conversely, Davis reported a higher incidence of cerebral
      palsy in 14 year old children with birth weight below 1501g who were treated with
      theophylline in the newborn period than prematurely born infants without methylxanthine
      treatment (13% to 1.6%).

      Recent advances in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) have allowed for new techniques in
      visualizing brain injury and development in preterm infants by non-invasive means. Diffusion
      tensor imaging (DTI) is a modality of MRI that measures the translational motion of water
      within tissue, or &quot;apparent diffusion.&quot; If the direction of diffusion is hindered more in
      one direction than another, the water motion is considered anisotropic. Water apparent
      diffusion in mature white matter is highly anisotropic; the directionally averaged water
      apparent diffusion coefficient (ADC) has been referenced at 1.0-2.0 x 10^-3 mm2/s for the
      infant brain, 0.8 x 10^-3 mm2/s for the adult brain. Normative values obtained by DTI have
      been shown to be a sensitive indicator for white and gray matter development and complexity.
      Both Dyet and Woodward have been able to correlate abnormal white matter signals on brain
      MRI in preterm infants with subsequent impairment in cognitive, motor, and neurosensory
      outcomes.

      As caffeine use in the CAPT study has been demonstrated in low doses commenced around 3 days
      of life to have a positive impact on neurodevelopmental outcomes at 18 to 21 months, it
      would be beneficial to understand the effects of a higher dose of caffeine on both short-
      and long-term outcomes with an emphasis on the prevention of brain injury (intraventricular
      hemorrhage and white matter injury) and the improvement of neurodevelopmental development.

      Thus, we propose a randomized controlled trial of high-dose versus standard low-dose
      caffeine therapy postulating that high doses of caffeine citrate will have beneficial
      effects on both short- and long-term neurologic outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Prevention</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of time requiring mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brain injury</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality rates</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of time requiring any respiratory support</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of time after birth until resolution of apnea of prematurity</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of chronic lung disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of time requiring inotropic support</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of time after birth until reaching full enteral feeds</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of necrotizing enterocolitis</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant neurobehavioral scoring by Dubowitz scale prior to discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of EEG seizure burden</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of retinopathy of prematurity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Advanced magnetic resonance imaging by diffusion analysis and cortical folding measures</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bayley Scales of Infant Development scores at 2 and 4 years of age</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of tachycardia and/or arrhythmias</measure>
    <time_frame>Time hospitalized</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Apnea of Prematurity</condition>
  <condition>Intraventricular Hemorrhage</condition>
  <condition>White Matter Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High dose caffeine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Loading dose 40mg/kg IV caffeine citrate, followed 12 hours later by 20mg/kg IV caffeine citrate, followed 12 hours later by 10mg/kg IV caffeine citrate, followed 12 hours later by 10mg/kg IV caffeine citrate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard dose caffeine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Loading dose 20mg/kg IV caffeine citrate, followed 12 hours later with D5W placebo, followed 12 hours later with 10mg/kg IV caffeine citrate, followed 12 hours later with D5W placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Caffeine citrate</intervention_name>
    <description>Caffeine to be administered as outlined to compare efficacy of different dosages.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High dose caffeine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard dose caffeine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Preterm infants from 24 to 30 weeks completed PMA admitted to the neonatal intensive
             care unit (NICU) at St. Louis Children's Hospital. The estimated post menstrual age
             will be provided by the obstetrical records and compared with a Dubowitz exam at
             admission. The provided PMA will be used unless the Dubowitz exam has a discrepancy
             of greater or equal to 2 weeks, where then the Dubowitz age will be used.

          -  Infants must be recruited within the first 24 hours of life.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants over 30 weeks gestation.

          -  Infants who are moribund with severe sepsis, in respiratory failure, or have severe
             brain injury present in the first 24 hours of life. This would be defined as
             physiologic instability requiring &gt;80% FiO2 for 6 hours and/or more than 2 inotropic
             drugs (excluding hydrocortisone), or in the attending or recruiting physicians'
             opinion the infant is likely to die within 24 hours or would not tolerate any
             handling for the protocol.

          -  Infants must not have received any doses of caffeine citrate prior to enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>24 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Weeks</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Terrie Inder, MBChB, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Louis Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 23, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 15, 2008</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Caffeine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Caffeine citrate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
