<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="697">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01289912</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-06-0247</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01289912</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of RAD001 and Neurocognition in Tuberous Sclerosis Complex (TSC)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TSC</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Double-Blind Phase 2 Trial Of RAD001 For Neurocognition In Individuals With Tuberous Sclerosis Complex</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mustafa Sahin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tuberous Sclerosis Alliance</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Autism Speaks</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Seizure Tracker LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Boston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Tuberous Sclerosis Complex (TSC) is a multi-system disease, usually presenting with
      seizures, mental retardation and autism, and exhibiting a high variability in clinical
      findings both among and within families. Investigators are doing research in order to
      identify possible neurocognitive benefits from treatment with RAD001 or placebo for a six
      month period. There may also be potential for improvements in seizure frequency, sleep and
      autistic behaviors. We hope this trial will lead to a better understanding of TSC and to new
      forms of treatment, to benefit children and adults with TSC in the future.

      Individuals diagnosed with TSC will be asked to participate in this study if they are
      between the ages of 6 and 21 years of age and have an IQ of greater than or equal to 60.
      Both males and females will be asked to participate. Additionally, to be eligible for study
      participation, individuals must have been on the same seizure medication(s), if applicable,
      for at least 6 months. Individuals must also be able to participate in neuropsychological
      testing and meet certain medical criteria. They will need to sign an informed consent. If
      enrolled in the study, participants will have a number of screening tests to help determine
      if they are eligible for participation in the clinical trial. If eligible for the treatment
      phase of the trial, they will be asked to take either the study drug or a placebo (pill with
      no medicine), which is determined by chance.

      The study involves about 9 visits, 3 of which can be done locally, over a six month period,
      as well as follow-up calls with our research nurse. Study visits will vary in length.
      Screening, three month and six month visits may last up to 8 hours, while all other visits
      will be less than 2 hours. The study visits include blood draws, laboratory tests and
      neuropsychological assessments. There is no fee to participate in this study. Some
      compensation may be available for travel costs of out-of-state participants based on fund
      availability. The study drug will be provided at no charge during the study.

      After all study data has been analyzed, families will be informed of the overall results.
      Treatment on this study may or may not improve a child's learning skills (neurocognition).
      Future patients may benefit from what is learned.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a signal-seeking Phase II randomized, placebo-controlled trial of RAD001 in children
      and young adults with TSC with neurocognition as the primary outcome and autism spectrum
      disorder as a secondary outcome.

      Specific Aims /Objectives Primary objective

        -  To evaluate the efficacy of RAD001 on neurocognition in patients with TSC compared to
           placebo as measured by well-validated, standardized, direct and indirect neurocognitive
           tools.

        -  To evaluate the safety of RAD001 compared with placebo in patients with TSC focusing on
           NCI CTCAE Grade 3 and 4 adverse events, serious adverse events, and Grade 3 and 4
           laboratory toxicities.

      Secondary objectives

        -  Comparison of absolute change from baseline in frequency of epileptiform events as
           recorded on seizure diaries between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo

        -  Comparison of sleep disturbances between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo, measured
           by the Pediatric Sleep Questionnaire (PSQ) and sleep logs

        -  Comparison of autism spectrum disorders features between patients taking RAD001 vs.
           placebo, measured by ADOS and SRS

        -  Comparison of academic skills between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo, measured by
           WRAT4

        -  Comparison of behavioral problems between patients taking RAD001 vs placebo, measured
           by behavioral rating scales (BRIEF, BASC, SDQ, CHQ and SRS)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the safety of RAD001 on neurocognition in patients with TSC compared with placebo in patients with TSC.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the safety of RAD001 compared with placebo in patients with TSC focusing on NCI CTCAE Grade 3 and 4 adverse events, serious adverse events, and Grade 3 and 4 laboratory toxicities.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the efficacy of RAD001 on neurocognition in patients with TSC compared with placebo in patients with TSC.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of RAD001 on neurocognition in patients with TSC compared to placebo as measured by well-validated, standardized, direct and indirect neurocognitive tools.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of absolute change from baseline in frequency of epileptiform events between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of absolute change from baseline in frequency of epileptiform events as recorded on seizure diaries between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of sleep disturbances between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of sleep disturbances between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo, measured by the Pediatric Sleep Questionnaire (PSQ) and sleep logs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of autism spectrum disorders features between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of autism spectrum disorders features between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo, measured by ADOS and SRS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of academic skills between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of academic skills between patients taking RAD001 vs. placebo, measured by WRAT4</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of behavioral problems between patients taking RAD001 vs placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Comparison of behavioral problems between patients taking RAD001 vs placebo, measured by behavioral rating scales (BRIEF, BASC, SDQ, CHQ and SRS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberous Sclerosis Complex</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RAD001</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>RAD001 is formulated as tablets of 5.0 mg strength, blister-packed under aluminum foil in units of 10 tablets and dosed on a regular basis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo will be provided as a matching tablet and will also be blister packed under aluminum foil in units of 10.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RAD001</intervention_name>
    <description>RAD001 is formulated as tablets of 5.0 mg strength, blister-packed under aluminum foil in units of 10 tablets and dosed on a regular basis. Matching placebo will be provided as a matching tablet and will also be blister packed under aluminum foil in units of 10. RAD001 or matching placebo tablets should be opened only at the time of administration as drug is both hygroscopic and light-sensitive.
Patients will be instructed to take 4.5 mg/m2 of RAD001 or matching placebo orally with a glass of water at regular intervals at the same time (delete: each day) in the morning after a light, nonfat breakfast.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RAD001</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Everolimus</other_name>
    <other_name>Afinitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          1. Male or female patients ages 6 to 21 years of age.

          2. IQ ≥60.

          3. Ability to participate in direct neuropsychological and developmental testing.

          4. English as primary language.

          5. Diagnosis of tuberous sclerosis complex confirmed by genetic testing and/or
             clinically definite diagnosis of tuberous sclerosis complex according to the modified
             Gomez criteria and an IQ&gt;60.

          6. Stable anti-epileptic drugs (no changes in medications except dose for &gt;6 months).

          7. Adequate renal function. The GFR would be greater than 50 ml/min.m2 as determined by
             the Schwartz Formula for children and MDRD for adults:

             http://www.nkdep.nih.gov/professionals/gfr_calculators/index.htm

          8. If female and of child bearing potential, documentation of negative pregnancy test
             prior to enrollment. Sexually active pre-menopausal female patients (and female
             partners of male patients) must use adequate contraceptive measures, excluding
             estrogen containing contraceptives, while on study. Abstinence will be considered an
             adequate contraceptive measure.

          9. INR ≤1.5 (Anticoagulation is allowed if target INR ≤ 1.5 on a stable dose of warfarin
             or on a stable dose of LMW heparin for &gt;2 weeks at time of randomization.)

         10. Adequate liver function as shown by:

               -  serum bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               -  ALT and AST ≤ 2.5x ULN (≤ 5x ULN in patients with liver metastases)

         11. Written informed consent according to local guidelines.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. Change of one or more antiepileptic medication in the past 6 months.

          2. Prior exposure to the systemic use of an mTOR inhibitor.

          3. Exposure to any investigational agent in the 30 days prior to randomization.

          4. Neurosurgery within 6 months.

          5. Known impaired lung function (e.g.FEV1 or DLCO &lt;70% of predicted), if not resolved or
             if resolved within past 24 months.

          6. Significant hematological or hepatic abnormality (i.e. transaminase levels &gt; 2.5 x
             ULN or serum bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN, hemoglobin &lt; 9 g/dL, platelets &lt; 80,000/ mm3,
             absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1,000/mm3).

          7. Serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 x ULN.

          8. Uncontrolled hyperlipidemia: Fasting serum cholesterol &gt; 300 mg/dL OR &gt; 7.75 mmol/L
             AND Fasting triglycerides &gt; 2.5 x ULN.

          9. Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus as defined by fasting serum glucose &gt; 1.5 x ULN.

         10. Patients with bleeding diathesis or on oral anti-vitamin K medication (except low
             dose warfarin).

         11. Patients with known history of HIV seropositivity.

         12. Pregnancy or breast feeding.

         13. Active infection at date of randomization.

         14. Prior history of organ transplant.

         15. Recent surgery (involving entry into a body cavity or requiring sutures) within the 4
             weeks prior to randomization.

         16. Inability to attend scheduled clinic visits.

         17. History of malignancy in the past two years, other than squamous or basal cell skin
             cancer.

         18. Patients should not receive immunization with attenuated live vaccines within one
             month of study entry or during study period. Close contact with those who have
             received attenuated live vaccines should be avoided during treatment with everolimus.
             Examples of live vaccines include intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral
             polio, BCG, yellow fever, varicella and TY21a typhoid vaccines.

         19. Liver disease such as cirrhosis or severe hepatic impairment (Child-Pugh class C).

             Note: A detailed assessment of Hepatitis B/C medical history and risk factors must be
             done at screening for all patients. HBV DNA and HCV RNA PCR testing are required at
             screening for all patients with a positive medical history based on risk factors
             and/or confirmation of prior HBV/HCV infection.

         20. Patients receiving chronic, systemic treatment with corticosteroids or another
             immunosuppressive agent. Topical or inhaled corticosteroids are allowed.

         21. Patients who have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or other
             conditions that could affect their participation in the study such as:

               -  symptomatic congestive heart failure of New York heart Association Class III or
                  IV

               -  unstable angina pectoris, symptomatic congestive heart failure, myocardial
                  infarction within 6 months of start of study drug, serious uncontrolled cardiac
                  arrhythmia or any other clinically significant cardiac disease

         22. Patients who have received an IQ score under 60 in the six months prior to the study
             screening visit will be deemed ineligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mustafa Sahin, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Boston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://tsclinic.org/index.php</url>
    <description>Boston Children's Hospital - Multi-Disciplinary Tuberous Sclerosis Program</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.tsalliance.org/</url>
    <description>Tuberous Sclerosis Alliance</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 27, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>February 2, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital, Boston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mustafa Sahin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tuberous Sclerosis Complex</keyword>
  <keyword>Autism</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurocognition</keyword>
  <keyword>RAD001</keyword>
  <keyword>Everolimus</keyword>
  <keyword>Afinitor</keyword>
  <keyword>TSC</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberous Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
