<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="911">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02178995</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MPH in epilepsy</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02178995</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Methylphenidate Treatment of Attention Deficits in Epilepsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Methylphenidate Treatment of Attentional and Cognitive Deficits in Epilepsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kimford Jay Meador</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Methylphenidate (MPH) has long been used to improve attention and cognitive difficulties
      associated with ADHD, including in children with ADHD and epilepsy (Torres et al., 2008).
      Methylphenidate (MPH) is also helpful in treating attention and other cognitive difficulties
      in a variety of other neurological and medical conditions (Kajs-Wyllie, 2002; Prommer,
      2012). We seek to evaluate the potential efficacy and safety of this medication in treating
      attention deficits, as well as other cognitive difficulties, experienced by adult patients
      with epilepsy.

      To our knowledge, there are currently very few studies which explicitly examine the impact
      of MPH on measureable attention deficits and other cognitive deficits in adult patients with
      epilepsy. We hope to quantify what impact, if any, methylphenidate has on attention, in
      addition to other specific measureable cognitive functions, in patients with cognitive
      complaints and epilepsy, and contribute to a growing body of evidence which supports the
      safety of methylphenidate's use for attention deficits in patients with epilepsy. As other
      effective treatments for attention and other cognitive difficulties in patients with
      epilepsy are not currently available, MPH could represent an important option in the
      treatment of such patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prospective participants with seizures will be identified primarily through the Stanford
      Neurology and Neuropsychiatry clinics and Stanford Medical Center, with the assistance of
      clinic staff and providers. Participants may also be identified and referred by their
      physicians in the community as well. Informational fliers will be distributed to these
      clinics and throughout Stanford Medical Center and Stanford campus in order to identify
      participants with epilepsy as well as healthy volunteers. Prospective participants may also
      contact study staff directly via contact information listed on the flier or provided to them
      by their providers. Those identified will be contacted, either in person or by telephone, by
      study staff.

      A telephone or in-person pre-screening will occur, expected to last approximately 20-30
      minutes, in order to determine eligibility for the study, interest in participating, and any
      questions related to the study. A brief summary of study procedures and goals will be
      reviewed during this pre-screening. Participants who meet inclusion/exclusion criteria may
      take part in an initial in-person visit at Stanford Medical Center, where informed consent
      will be obtained and signed (see attached informed consent form). Any additional history
      needed in order to confirm a participant's eligibility will be reviewed at this visit. If
      the individual chooses to proceed, the participant's blood pressure and heartrate will be
      measured, and if necessary (because a recent physical exam including cardiac auscultation is
      not available), a brief physical exam will be performed by a licensed physician. If vital
      signs and exam (if necessary) are normal, participants will be asked to complete
      neuropsychiatric questionnaires, self-report questionnaires, a quality-of-life
      questionnaire, and a seizure diary. The full 40-minute neurocognitive battery will be
      performed, and baseline scores obtained.

      Participants will be asked to complete the seizure diary once per week, either in-person at
      their visits or at home. Thereafter, the participant will be asked to attend at least three
      additional 2-hour sessions at Stanford Medical Center. The participant will be asked to
      avoid taking any non-routine sedating medications within 24 hours of his/her scheduled
      visit, and to refrain from eating, drinking caffeine, or smoking for 2 hours prior to
      his/her visit. When the participant arrives, they will be given either a placebo, 20mg of
      methylphenidate, or 40mg of methylphenidate (randomized and blinded by the research
      pharmacy), and asked to remain within the hospital for 1 hour prior to testing to allow the
      medication to enter their system. Both study staff and the participant will be blinded to
      whether they are receiving active medication or placebo. During this time, the participant
      will complete self-report questionnaires reporting any medication changes, medical events,
      or significant adverse events, and their seizure diary will be reviewed and kept by study
      staff. After this, the full neurocognitive battery will be completed. Following the
      completion of neurocognitive testing, the participant's next visit will be scheduled for
      approximately the same time of day in approximately one week, and payment will be provided.
      This procedure will be repeated for the next two visits. Participants will not receive any
      additional study drug during this period other than the single dose they receive in-person.

      At the participant's fourth visit, they will be asked to repeat the neuropsychiatric
      questionnaires from visit #1, as well as the usual self-report forms and seizure diary.
      Heartrate and blood pressure will be obtained again prior to the administration of the
      neurocognitive battery. At the end of the fourth visit, participants will be asked if they
      wish to take part in the four-week open-label phase of this study, designed to evaluate the
      ongoing efficacy and safety of methylphenidate for use in patients with epilepsy. Regardless
      of their answer, payment will be provided for their fourth visit.

      Those participants who are interested in participating in the open-label trial will be
      provided with a prescription for two weeks of methylphenidate 10mg PO BID, followed by two
      weeks of methylphenidate 20mg PO BID. Participants will be provided with copies of the
      seizure diary and asked to complete it weekly. Participants will be able to contact the
      protocol director by phone to report any significant side effects or adverse events during
      this trial. At the protocol director's discretion, in keeping with standard of care for this
      medication, the dosage of the medication may be lowered (minimum dose 5mg PO BID) in
      response to any side effects experienced by participants during this period.

      Participants in the open-label trial will be asked to return after four more weeks for a
      fifth and final visit. Participants will again be asked to refrain from eating, caffeine,
      and nicotine for 2 hours prior to their visit, and will take their prescribed
      methylphenidate upon arriving at Stanford Medical Center. Participants will wait 1 hour for
      the medication to enter their system, during which time they will complete neuropsychiatric
      and self-report questionnaires as before, their seizure diaries will be reviewed, and their
      heart rate and blood pressure will again be measured. The cognitive battery will be
      administered again. Afterwards, any participant questions will be answered and final
      financial compensation will be provided, and the participant's involvement has ended. Data
      will remain blinded until the completion of the study. Participants wishing to receive the
      active medication following the termination of the open-label phase of the study may do so
      at the discretion of their physicians.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Conners' continuous performance test (CPT)</measure>
    <time_frame>difference of 2 treatments (randomized to weeks 2, 3, or 4) from placebo (randomized to week 2, 3 or 4)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Scores on this test measure attentiveness/vigilance and response time. Primary measure will be confidence interval differences.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seizure frequency/severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (day 1) to methylphenidate treatments (single doses randomized to weeks 2, 3, or 4, and end of one month treatment at end month 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Seizure diaries will be monitored for changes in seizure frequency and/or severity associated with methylphenidate use during 2 single dose exposures and during 1 month open label.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symbol-digit matching test</measure>
    <time_frame>difference of 2 treatments (randomized to weeks 2, 3, or 4) from placebo (randomized to week 2, 3 or 4)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Symbol-digit matching test is a measure processing speed and working memory.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MCG paragraph memory test</measure>
    <time_frame>difference of 2 treatments (randomized to weeks 2, 3, or 4) from placebo (randomized to week 2, 3 or 4)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>MCG paragraph memory test is a measure verbal memory.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to end of methylphenidate open label treatment (end month 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Beck Depression Inventory is a questionnaire to assess mood.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Anxiety Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to end of methylphenidate open label treatment (end month 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Beck Anxiety Inventory is a questionnaire to assess anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QOLIE-89</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to end of methylphenidate open label treatment (end month 2)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>QOLIE-89 is a questionnaire to assess quality of life and subjective cognitive effects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Deficits</condition>
  <condition>Attention Deficits</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants with epilepsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive three single doses of blinded medication, either a placebo, 20mg of methylphenidate, or 40mg of methylphenidate, and will complete cognitive testing and neuropsychiatric questionnaires. This single-dose phase will be followed by an open-label 4-week treatment trial of methylphenidate.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthy controls will complete the same neurocognitive batteries and neuropsychiatric questionnaires as individuals with epilepsy, but will not be exposed to study medication.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylphenidate</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants with epilepsy will first receive blinded, single-dose capsules which contain either:
Placebo 20mg of methylphenidate or 40mg of methylphenidate.
At each visit, they will receive one capsule and then complete the neurocognitive batteries and neuropsychiatric questionnaires. There will be no medication administered between visits during this time. Following the final randomized visit, interested participants will be prescribed 10mg of methylphenidate twice daily, to be increased to 20mg of methylphenidate twice daily. After four weeks, their scores on the batteries and questionnaires will again be assessed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants with epilepsy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ritalin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. For participants with seizures:

               -  H/o seizures of any cause

               -  Subjective cognitive complaints

               -  Stable antiepileptic drug doses which are not expected to change during the
                  study

               -  Recent normal cardiac auscultation (may be done prior to enrollment by personal
                  physician or study staff)

          2. For healthy volunteers

               -  No history of seizures or other neurological disorders

               -  No history of cognitive complaints for any reason (including ADHD)

               -  Not on any medications which would interfere w/ cognitive testing

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. IQ

          2. History of an adverse reaction to methylphenidate

          3. Seizure frequency &gt; than 1 complex partial seizures (CPS) or absence seizure per
             month or &gt; than 3 generalized tonic-clonic seizures (GTCS) per year

          4. Age &gt;60 or &lt;18

          5. Family history of sudden cardiac death at age &lt;40

          6. Personal medical history of

               -  Arrhythmias,

               -  Structural cardiac disease,

               -  Other cardiac abnormality

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension (BP &gt;140/90 during study)

               -  Uncontrolled tachycardia (HR &gt;100 during study)

               -  Progressive neurological disorders (e.g., dementia) which may interfere w/
                  cognition for reasons other than seizures

               -  Glaucoma

               -  Other major medical illnesses which may interfere with cognition or medication
                  (e.g., severe liver or renal disease, active infections, etc)

               -  Intellectual disability/mental retardation

          7. Substance use history

               -  Met criteria for substance use disorder within the past year

               -  Any active illicit substance use

               -  Alcohol use meeting criteria for substance abuse

               -  Unwillingness to abstain from alcohol w/in 24 hours of testing

          8. Personal psychiatric history

               -  Any history of psychosis or mania

               -  History of suicide attempts within the last year

               -  Active suicidality

          9. Severe cognitive impairments (e.g. aphasia) which render a participant unable to
             consent

         10. Currently receiving medications which would be expected to interfere with the study
             tasks, if they cannot be held for study visits

         11. Pregnancy or active breastfeeding

         12. Women of childbearing potential who are sexually active and not willing or able to
             use a contraceptive strategy during the course of the study

         13. Any other factor which may interfere w/ a participant's ability to consent or to
             complete the required cognitive tasks, or may significantly interfere with their
             performance on the required tests
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jesse M Adams, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kimford Meador, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Barry, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kimford Meador, MD</last_name>
    <phone>650-275-6648</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2014</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 9, 2014</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 24, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kimford Jay Meador</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
