<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="533">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02516228</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EGI-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02516228</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcranial Electrical Neuromodulation for Suppressing Epileptiform Discharges</brief_title>
  <acronym>GTEN</acronym>
  <official_title>Geodesic Transcranial Electrical Neuromodulation(GTEN100) Device</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Electrical Geodesics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Harborview Injury Prevention and Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Huashan Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Electrical Geodesics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study examines the safety and feasibility of suppressing epileptic discharges through
      inducing long term depression of the epileptic focus with transcranial electrical
      neuromodulation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      One third of patients with epilepsy continue to have seizures despite receiving
      antiepileptic medication. The application of low frequency repetitive transcranial magnetic
      stimulation (rTMS) has shown promise for decreasing the frequency of epileptic seizures in
      drug refractory patients. The mechanism of action appears to be induction of long term
      depression (LTD) in the targeted cortex by the low frequency (0.5 Hz or 1 every 2 sec)
      pulses. Unfortunately, the electrical stimulation induced by available TMS coils is limited
      to the most superficial (gyral) regions of cortex, whereas epileptic foci may occur in
      sulci, and in deep as well as superficial cortex. The investigators have developed the
      ability to target currents to specific regions of cortex by aligning source and sink
      electrodes with flexible subsets of a 256 channel geodesic electrode array. A first step is
      accurate localization of the likely epileptic focus with 256 channel EEG. Detailed
      computational models of the electrical properties of head tissues allow optimization studies
      to select the best pattern of source-sink electrodes for that individual's head tissues and
      epileptic focus. The goal of the safety and feasibility trial in Phase I is to test whether
      one week (5 days) of GTEN treatment can achieve a similar depression of the target cortical
      region as low frequency rTMS, with the decrease in excitability measured by suppression of
      epileptic spikes. This safety and feasibility trial has received an Investigational Device
      Exemption from the FDA for treating 20 patients with focal neocortical epilepsy. Both Pulsed
      (emulating rTMS) and Sustained (emulating tDCS) current sequences will be evaluated. If
      either or both of these prove successful in suppressing spikes, a second feasibility study
      in Phase II will examine whether GTEN treatment (Pulsed or Sustained, whichever proves
      better) with 2 weeks (5 days per week) of treatment is successful with the primary endpoint
      of temporary suppression of seizures. The GTEN system implements a number of advanced
      technologies that provide improved targeting compared to conventional rTMS or tDCS,
      including electronics for both pulsed and sustained delivery of current with 256 electrodes;
      double fault safety circuits; computational modeling of the electromagnetic properties of
      the patient's head tissue for GTEN targeting with medical grade software; a lidocaine
      electrolyte that minimizes pain of the pulsed or sustained current with up to 200 µA per
      electrode (2 mA total); and online safety monitoring for adverse EEG changes with the 256
      dEEG array. Based on FDA feedback to date, success with these trials will allow us to
      progress to a pivotal clinical efficacy trial (with separate funding) to support a de novo
      510k approval for GTEN treatment for the temporary suppression of seizures in patients with
      drug-resistant epilepsy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Temporary suppression of epileptic activity, as assessed primarily by spikes seen in the EEG</measure>
    <time_frame>six months post treatment</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geodesic Transcranial Electrical Neuromodulation for Suppression of Eplieptiform Discharges</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>suppression of seizures as assessed by self-report using a seizure diary</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Partial Onset Seizures (Simple or Complex) With Extratemporal Focus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1. Sustained</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The sustained protocol is based on cortical surface cathodal tDCS, targeted to the epileptogenic zone. Intervention: Device: GeodesicTranscranial Electrical Neuromodulation (GTEN 100)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2. Pulsed</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the pulsed protocol, surface cathodal direct current, like in the sustained protocol, will be pulsed. Pulses will be delivered at .5 Hz, with each pulse lasting 100 ms. A total of 500 pulses will be delivered for each treatment block.
Intervention: Device: GeodesicTranscranial Electrical Neuromodulation (GTEN 100)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GeodesicTranscranial Electrical Neuromodulation (GTEN 100)</intervention_name>
    <description>In this feasibility study, patients will be randomly assigned to receive either continuous direct current stimulation or a slow-pulsed electrical current. Stimulation will be focused on the seizure generating cortex.
All patients enrolled in the study will have a one-month, pre-treatment baseline evaluation period. During this time, the patient (and/or family) will maintain the seizure diary that simply tracks the number of seizure the patient experiences each day.
During this baseline period, two three-hour EEG recordings (to be completed on 2 separate days) will be acquired. This baseline EEG data will be used to establish baseline inter-ictal spike rate as well as classification of the inter-ictal spikes used to localize seizure onset zone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1. Sustained</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2. Pulsed</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GTEN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 12 years and older.

          2. Partial onset seizures (simple or complex) with failure of adequate seizure control
             after prior use of at least 2 anti-seizure drugs at effective doses.

          3. Only one clearly identified and localizable extratemporal focus of epileptiform
             discharges, as defined the discharges (typically epileptiform spikes) and as
             identified by dEEG assessment through one or more routine clinical dEEG evaluations.

          4. Two or more partial seizures, with or without secondary generalization, in the last
             month, but less than 10 seizures per day.

          5. Anti-seizure drug regimen has remained unchanged for the month before study entry,
             and there is reasonable likelihood of stability for the duration of the study, with
             the exception of allowing short-term rescue medications, such as lorazepam.

          6. A history of epilepsy for at least 2 years.

          7. Ability to provide consent (for adult)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. If of childbearing potential, the patient must agree to use an effective method of
             birth control during the study and cease participation if pregnant.

          2. Pregnancy

          3. A history or condition of progressive brain disorders, serious systemic diseases,
             symptomatic cerebrovascular disease, cardiac disease, or alcohol/substance
             abuse.Special conditions, for example, non-malignant brain tumors and vascular
             malformations, can be considered for entry on a case-by-case basis.

          4. A history or condition of status epilepticus or psychogenic seizures (seizures not
             confirmed by EEG).

          5. Presence of a cardiac pacemaker, vagus nerve stimulator, or metal implants in the
             body (other than the teeth) including neurostimulators, cochlear implants, and
             implanted medication pumps (screened using the LCNI Safety Screening Questionaire).

          6. Previous surgery involving opening the skull.

          7. Allergy to or condition contraindicating lidocaine.

          8. Unable to express presence of pain or discomfort.

          9. Sensitivity to silver

        Although selection of patients according to the 5th inclusion criterion should minimize
        medication changes, if patients have their anti-seizure medications changed by their
        physician during the course of the study, they will not be excluded from the study.
        Rather, their physician will inform the researchers of the medication change and we may or
        may not exclude their data from final analysis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Don M Tucker, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>C.E.O/, Chief Scientist</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Don M Tucker, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>541-687-7962</phone>
    <phone_ext>411</phone_ext>
    <email>dtucker@egi.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Phan Luu, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>541-687-7962</phone>
    <phone_ext>403</phone_ext>
    <email>pluu@egi.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 26, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 23, 2015</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
