<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="534">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02100644</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200776</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02100644</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Valproate Dose Reduction and Its Clinical Evaluation by Introducing Lamotrigine in Japanese Women With Epilepsy - Single Arm, Multicenter, and Open-label Study -</brief_title>
  <official_title>Valproate Dose Reduction and Its Clinical Evaluation by Introducing Lamotrigine in Japanese Women With Epilepsy - Single Arm, Multicenter, and Open-label Study -</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Japan: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine whether the VPA (Valproate) dose can be reduced by
      additional administration of LTG (Lamotrigine) in Japanese pre-menopausal female epilepsy
      patients aged 15 years or older, whose seizures are well controlled by VPA monotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE In several studies that investigated the effects of in utero exposure to AEDs
      (antiepileptic drugs) on fetal malformations and intellectual development in children after
      birth, it has been reported that VPA causes neonatal malformations and decreases
      intelligence of children in a dose dependent manner, whereas such a risk is low in LTG
      (Hernandez-Díaz et al., 2012; Meador et al., 2013). It has also been reported that LTG as
      adjunctive therapy with VPA is effective in inhibiting seizures in patients with poorly
      controlled seizures, and adverse events under VPA monotherapy can be relieved by
      subsequently reducing VPA dose after LTG is combined (Sale et al., 2005; Jozwiak et al.,
      2000; Morris et al, 2004; Buchanan, 1996). Thus, by considering the benefits of replacing
      VPA by LTG in childbearing women, we will examine whether VPA dose can be reduced by
      introducing LTG in Japanese female epilepsy patients under VPA monotherapy (aged ≥ 15 years,
      pre-menopausal).

      STUDY DESIGN Single arm, multicenter, and open-label study TIME FRAME

        -  Screening(Retrospective review of medical records for 12 weeks)

        -  LTG escalation phase (8-18 weeks)

        -  VPA reduction phase (3-16 weeks)

        -  LTG &amp; VPA maintenance phase (12 weeks)

        -  Follow up (1-4 weeks) PRIMARY OBJECTIVE To examine whether the VPA dose can be reduced
           by additional administration of LTG (up to 200 mg/d if there are no safety concerns) in
           Japanese pre-menopausal female epilepsy patients aged 15 years or older, whose seizures
           are well controlled by VPA monotherapy (fixed maintenance dose of 400-1200 mg/d).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES

        -  To investigate the steady state concentration of LTG immediately before VPA dose
           reduction, at the time of VPA dose reduction, and during the LTG&amp;VPA maintenance phase.

        -  To investigate the safety and tolerability associated with additional administration of
           LTG followed by dose reduction of VPA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects and percent reduction of the VPA dose</measure>
    <time_frame>24-50 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Percentage of subjects who can reduce daily VPA dose during the LTG&amp;VPA maintenance phase and percent reduction of the VPA dose compared to baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of seizure day(s)</measure>
    <time_frame>24-50 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from screening in number of day(s) that epileptic seizures occur during the LTG&amp;VPA maintenance phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in QOLIE-31-P or QOLIE-AD-48</measure>
    <time_frame>24-50 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in QOLIE-31-P (subjects aged 18 years and older) or QOLIE-AD-48 (subjects aged 15-17 years) at the end of the LTG&amp;VPA maintenance phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects completing or discontinuing the study</measure>
    <time_frame>24-50 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>24-50 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline in body weight at the end of the LTG&amp;VPA maintenance phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate concentration of LTG</measure>
    <time_frame>24-50 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>To investigate the steady state concentration of LTG immediately before VPA dose reduction, at the time of VPA dose reduction, and during the LTG&amp;VPA maintenance phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type, severity, and incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>24-50 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number and percentage of subjects who experience the following adverse events will be summarized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lamotrigine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study objective is to examine whether the VPA dose can be reduced by additional administration of LTG in Japanese pre-menopausal female epilepsy patients, whose seizures are well controlled by VPA monotherapy. Then VPA is the standard product in this stuudy, not the investigational product.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lamotrigine tablets 25/100 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Lamotrigine (LTG) is administered according to the package insert: that is, 25 mg of LTG will be orally administered once every other day for the first 2 weeks and then once daily for the next 2 weeks. Thereafter, the dose will be gradually escalated by 25-50 mg every 1-2 week for once or twice daily administration. During the VPA reduction phase and LTG&amp;amp;VPA maintenance phase, as specified in the information of package insert, maintenance dose of LTG will be administered twice daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lamotrigine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. (Target disease) Epilepsy patients having the following seizure types as classified
             by the International Classification of Epileptic Seizures

               -  Partial seizures (with or without secondary generalization)

               -  Tonic-clonic seizures with or without myoclonus but without other generalized
                  seizure type(s)

          2. Subjects having a confident diagnosis of epilepsy that is uncomplicated by
             pseudoseizures such as psychogenic nonepileptic seizures

          3. Subjects whose seizures have been controlled for 12 weeks prior to start of the
             investigational product with a stable maintenance dose of VPA monotherapy (400-1200
             mg/d)

          4. (Age and gender)

        Japanese pre-menopausal women who are at least 15 years old at the time of consent, not
        lactating, and can agree to use any of the following types of contraception in a reliable
        fashion:

          1. Complete abstinence during the study as well as for a period after the study to
             account for elimination of the investigational product (a minimum of 2 weeks)

          2. Consistent and correct use of any of the following contraceptive methods

               -  Surgical sterilization of male partner (i.e., male partner is the sole sexual
                  partner for the female subject and is sterilized prior to the subject's entry
                  into the study)

               -  Intrauterine device with a failure rate of less than 1% per year

               -  Double barrier method (e.g., spermicide plus a condom or a diaphragm) Note:
                  Women who have had a hysterectomy or tubal ligation are considered to be of
                  non-childbearing potential. Since a pharmacokinetic interaction has been
                  observed between LTG and estrogen-based oral contraceptives, the use of hormonal
                  therapy such as for contraception or hormone replacement therapy is not allowed.

                  5.Outpatients 6.Subjects who can keep a seizure diary 7.Subjects who can
                  understand and sign the informed consent. If the subject is under 20 years old
                  at the time of consent, both the subject and subject's legally acceptable
                  representative have to sign the consent to participate in the study.

                  8.QTc &lt;480 msec for subjects with bundle branch block or QTc &lt;450 msec for other
                  subjects, in which QTc is measured by either single or triplicate-averaged ECG
                  9.Subjects who can comply with dosing of the investigational and standard
                  products and all study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with a history of hypersensitivity to LTG

          2. Subjects with a history of rash associated with other AED treatments.

          3. Subjects who have received another AED besides VPA during the 12 weeks prior to start
             of the investigational product

          4. Subjects with status epilepticus during the 6 months prior to start of the
             investigational product

          5. Subjects with a history of substance (including alcohol and drug) dependence or
             substance abuse as defined by the DSM-IV-TR within 12 months or 1 month,
             respectively, prior to start of the investigational product

          6. Subjects with a severe acute or chronic illness likely to impair drug absorption,
             distribution, metabolism, or excretion; or subjects with any unstable physical
             symptom likely to require hospitalization during the study

          7. Subjects with a severe psychiatric disorder that affects the procedures of the study
             or drug assessment

          8. Subjects with an acute or progressive neurological disorder or an organic disease

          9. Subjects with any clinically significant cardiac, renal, or hepatic medical
             condition. Any patient with these conditions will be excluded from the study even if
             these conditions are being controlled with a chronic therapy.

         10. Subjects with an unstable liver disease (as defined by the presence of ascites,
             encephalopathy, coagulopathy, hypoalbuminaemia, oesophageal or gastric varices, or
             persistent jaundice), cirrhosis, or known biliary abnormalities (with the exception
             of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones) Note: Chronic stable hepatitis B
             and C are acceptable if the subjects otherwise meet the inclusion criteria. However,
             the subjects with chronic stable hepatitis B will be excluded if significant
             immunosuppressive agents are being administered due to a risk of hepatitis B
             reactivation.

         11. Subjects who are pregnant or lactating, who may be pregnant, or who plan for
             pregnancy during the study

         12. Subjects who are suspected to have an urea cycle disorder as below:

               -  Subjects with a history of encephalopathy or coma of unknown cause

               -  Subjects with a family history of infant death of unknown cause or urea cycle
                  disorder

         13. Subjects taking inducers of LTG glucuronidation (i.e., rifampicinor
             lopinavir/ritonavir), atazanavir/ritonavir, risperidone, or oral contraceptives or
             hormone drugs containing estrogen

         14. Subjects taking carbapenem antibiotic (i.e., panipenem/betamipron, meropenem hydrate,
             imipenem hydrate/cilastatin sodium, biapenem, doripenem hydrate, or tebipenem
             pivoxil)

         15. Subjects who have participated in other clinical studies within 3 months prior to
             start of the investigational product

         16. Subjects who have had active suicidal plans/intent or suicidal thoughts in the past 3
             months prior to start of the investigational product; or subjects who have history of
             suicide attempts in the last 1 year prior to start of the investigational product or
             of multiple suicide attempts in their lifetime

         17. Subjects whom the investigator or subinvestigator considers ineligible for the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyogo</city>
        <zip>664-8540</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kagoshima</city>
        <zip>892-0844</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kyoto</city>
        <zip>606-8507</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Osaka</city>
        <zip>560-8565</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saitama</city>
        <zip>351-8551</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shizuoka</city>
        <zip>430-8558</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tokyo</city>
        <zip>185-0012</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Japan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 22, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 27, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anticonvulsants</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lamotrigine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
