<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="648">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00789113</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0308M51662</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IND72642</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00789113</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Determination of Absorption and Elimination of Lamotrigine-XR</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determination of Bioavailability and Clearance of Lamotrigine-XR by a Stable Isotope Technique</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People over 65 years of ag break down (metabolize) drugs differently than younger adults. It
      is not known why this happens or how elderly people absorb or break down these drug
      differently. These difference may show that elderly individuals need lower doses of
      medications to avoid possible toxicity. We are interested in studying how yor body absorbs
      and breaks down your lamotrigine medication. This research may indicate that doses of
      lamotrigine should be lowered as people get older.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If you agree to be in this study you will be admitted in to the General Clinical Research
      Center (GCRC) for approximately 24 hours on two different days (Part 1 and Part2). We will
      need you take a portion of your lamotrigine medication in a special form through a needle in
      your arm (intravenously). The special form of the drug is the same drug as you normally take
      except that it has a stable label (a NON-radioactive, naturally occurring atom) on the
      compound so that we can trace a small amount of the drug through your body. No commercial
      product of lamotrigine for intravenous use is available because of its poor solubility in
      water. The intravenous formulation used for this study has a chemical,
      hydroxypropyl-beta-cyclodextrin, that improves the solubility of lamotrigine in water. This
      formulation is similar to an intravenous formulation approved for another drug, Sporanox®
      (itraconazole) that is approved by the FDA. We have obtained approval form the FDA for this
      intravenous lamotrigine product to be used for research purposes and it has been shown to be
      safe in more than twenty younger individuals. We will collect fourteen (14) blood samples
      through a small tube placed into a vein in your arm and collect all of your urine over a
      period of 24 hours. One blood sample will then be drawn each day for 3 days for a total
      blood collection of seventeen (17 tubes (totaling approximately 170 mL or 11.5 tablespoons).
      The samples taken from you will be measured for blood chemistries and concentrations of
      lmaotrigine and its metabolites resulting from the medication that you take to control your
      disease (epilepsy or depression)

      For the second part of the study, you will be switched from your regular lamotrigine
      (Lamictal®) to once daily morning dosing of an extended-release formulation of Lamictal-XR®
      (at the same total daily dose). You will remain on the extended-release lamotrigine
      (Lamictal-XR) for two weeks, after which you will be re-admitted to the GCRC for 24 hours
      for Part 2 of the study. Study drug administration and blood and urine sampling will be
      identical to Part I. The extended-release formulation and your regular lamotrigine have been
      determined by the manufacturer in preliminary studies to be absorbed the same
      (bioequivalent0. You will not need to change your total daily dose and will only have to
      take your lamotrigine once daily with the extended-release product. Your blood levels of
      lamotrigine will be checked to insure that your are achieving the appropriate concentration
      with new extended-release product. For this study, you will be given a one-month supply free
      of charge of the extended-release formulation. After the study is completed, you would
      return to taking your regular lamotrigine dosing. If the FDA has approved the XR formulation
      at the end of the study, you and your doctor may decide to keep you on the extended-release
      form of the drug.

      With your consent, a genetics sample, consisting of three (3) additional blood tubes
      (totaling approximately six teaspoonfuls) will also be collected for a genetic analysis. The
      genetics sample will be identified with a subject number that corresponds to your other
      samples. We will use this sample to determine the genetic sequence of DNA that you have that
      is responsible for encoding proteins that are responsible for breaking down or transporting
      medications like lamotrigine so that they can be eliminated from your body. You can choose
      to participate in the main study without taking part in the genetics portion of the study.
      If you withdraw from the main study, the genetics sample will be discarded with the rest of
      the samples. if you choose to participate in the genetics portion of the study, we will
      store the genetics sample indefinitely, however, no testing other than for specific DNA
      sequences will be done unless we have contact you and received permission to do so.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Observational Model: Case-Crossover, Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <condition>Seizures</condition>
  <condition>Bipolar Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Bipolar Depression</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples to determine lamotrigine concentration. Urine samples to determine lamotrigine
      metabolite concentration. DNA from blood sample.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        15 elderly subjects over the age of 65 taking lamotrigine for control of epilepsy or
        bipolar disorder
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical Diagnosis of Epilepsy or Bipolar Depression

          -  able to have a venus catheter implanted for blood withdrawal and for intravenous
             infusion

          -  equal to or over the age of 65

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  not on any medication that will interact with lamotrigine e.g. carbamazepine,
             phenytoin, phenobarbital, valproic acid, St. John's wort, rifampin, tamoxifen
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rory P Remmel, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2010</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 7, 2008</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Rory P Remmel/Professor</name_title>
    <organization>University of Minnesota</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>lamotrigine</keyword>
  <keyword>epilepsy</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolism</keyword>
  <keyword>bipolar disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>bipolar depression</keyword>
  <keyword>glucuronidation</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lamotrigine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
