<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="654">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00298246</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060102</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-M-0102</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00298246</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Immunological Investigations of Subtypes of Autism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical and Immunological Investigations of Subtypes of Autism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn more about autism and its subtypes. Autism is a
      developmental disorder in which children have problems with communication and social skills
      and display restricted interests and repetitive behaviors.

      This study has several goals. One aim is to look at types of autism that are known, such as
      the regressive subtype, (where skills are lost). We will explore whether there is a unique
      change in immune functioning related to this subtype. Another aim is to serve as one of the
      sites that will pilot a larger natural history study, entitled Autism Phenome Project. The
      goal is to further understand autism by identifying other subtypes.

      We will look at several types of medical issues that may be related to autism, including
      immunologic problems. Children will be followed over the course of several years. We aim to
      capture medical problems that may be related to autism as they develop, and study outcomes
      in areas such as behavior and language, in order to explore known and new subtypes of
      autism.

      Normally developing children (aged 1) with autism (age 1, and developmental delays other
      than autism (age 1), may be eligible for this study.

      Depending on each child's study group and age, participants may undergo the following tests
      and procedures:

      Baseline Visit

        -  Medical and developmental history, physical examination, psychological, cognitive and
           medical tests to assess symptoms of autism or other developmental disorders,
           photographs of the child's face, collection of hair, urine and baby teeth samples. If
           available, hair samples from the baby's first haircut and from the biological mother's
           hair are also collected.

        -  Overnight electroencephalogram (EEG): A special cap with electrodes is placed on the
           child's head to measure brain waves (brain electrical activity) while the child sleeps
           in the hospital overnight. Healthy volunteers do not undergo this procedure.

        -  Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan: The child stays in the scanner, lying still for
           10 to 15 minutes at a time. Since it may be difficult for the child to lie still, the
           test may be scheduled for a time when the child is likely to be sleepy, or the child
           may be sedated.

        -  Lumbar puncture (for children in the autism). This test and the MRI may be done under
           sedation.

      Follow-Up Visits

      Follow-up visits are scheduled at different intervals, depending on study group, age and
      aspect of the study the child is enrolled in. The visits include a short interview session
      with the child's caregiver and assessment of the child's development and behavior. Some of
      the assessment measures used during the baseline examination are repeated, including
      symptoms ratings, behavioral tests and a blood test. For some children, the final visit will
      include repeats of the medical procedures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current investigation will focus on the interrelationship between regression in autism
      and immune dysfunction. We propose to conduct a longitudinal natural history of 140 children
      with autism: 50 children with strictly defined regression, 50 with no history of regression,
      and an additional 40 children initially recruited in a pilot study for the Autism Phenome
      Project. We will also evaluate and follow 75 typically developing children, and 50 children
      with Development Delay. Subjects will be 12-60 months of age at study entry in order to
      capture regression as close to its onset as possible. Systematic prospective evaluations
      will be utilized in order to provide validation to the phenomenon of regression in autism,
      determine diagnostic and functional outcomes, and evaluate behavioral, medical and
      immunologic functioning. These evaluations will include comprehensive medical history,
      behavioral assessment, physical and neurologic examination, sleep EEG, structural MRI, blood
      work for laboratory assays, and for some children, lumbar puncture. In an investigation of
      potential immunologic abnormalities and associated neuroinflammation, repeated assessments
      are necessary to determine whether both behavioral and/or immunologic parameters are due to
      state versus trait alterations: elements of these assessments will be conducted every 6 to
      12 months, depending on the child's age.

      Our objective is to determine if there is a unique alteration in immune function among
      autistic children with a regressive clinical course. Our primary hypothesis is that at least
      some children with regressive autism will have abnormalities in immune function. These
      abnormalities will not be found among autistic children without a regressive course nor will
      they be found among children without an autistic spectrum disorder. Our specific aims are:

      Specific Aim #1: To characterize and validate the regressive phenotype in children with
      autism.

      Working hypothesis: Children with the diagnosis of autism who had a regressive clinical
      course can be reliably distinguished from children with non-regressive autism, Rett's
      Disorder and healthy children. When compared to children with non-regressive autism, the
      history of children in the regressive group will consist of similar or higher skill levels
      prior to regression, and lower skill levels following regression.

      Specific Aim #2: To characterize the immune response in children with autism.

      Working Hypothesis 2a: Distinct immunologic responses and cytokine abnormalities will be
      evident in children in the regressive autism sample, but not in the non-regressive autism,
      Rett's Disorder, or typically developing samples.

      Working Hypothesis 2b: MRI scans will reveal regional neuroinflammation among children in
      the regressive autism sample, but not in the non-regressive autism, Rett's Disorder, or
      typically developing samples.

      Specific Aim #3: To identify neurobiologic markers for autism through the techniques of
      metabolomics, proteomics and genomics (e.g. gene expression profiles).

      Working hypothesis: These neurobiologic markers will reliably differentiate between
      regressive autism, non-regressive autism, Rett's Disorder, and typically developing
      children.

      In addition, although progress has been made in identifying children affected by autism,
      little attention has been paid to the different manifestations of autism (or autisms). As
      has been demonstrated in &quot;diabetes&quot; and &quot;cancer&quot;, it is expected that the differences
      between individuals with autism may be as informative as their behavioral similarities.
      Complementing this study that investigates one possible subtype (regression), we propose to
      pilot a phenomenologic investigation to identify other biological and behavioral subgroups
      of autistic individuals, in order to facilitate investigations of etiology, pathophysiology,
      treatment and prevention. This will be done as a collaborative project with the M.I.N.D.
      Institute in Sacramento, California (approval for the collaborative protocols and data
      sharing was prevousl given by both NIMH and the University of California-Davis IRBs). The
      phenomenoligic investigation will evaluate the same children specified in the other aims (if
      they sign the consent to share their data with the MIND Institute) as well as data from
      typically developing children and developmental delays that consent for this.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2006</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>6 to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Immune markers</measure>
    <time_frame>6 to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep/EEG findings</measure>
    <time_frame>6 to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuroimaging findings</measure>
    <time_frame>6 to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Other laboratory findings</measure>
    <time_frame>6 to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic abnormalities</measure>
    <time_frame>6 to 12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">557</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Seizures</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        The sample at study endpoint will contain 50 children diagnosed with idiopathic autism and
        regression (AUT-R), 50 children diagnosed with idiopathic autism (and no history of
        regression; AUT-NR), 75 typically developing children (TYP), matched on ethnicity, sex,
        chronological age and daycare enrollment. Matching for daycare setting (home versus
        setting with other children) will be attempted due to the potentially greater immunologic
        challenge experienced by children in daycare settings. In addition, as many as 40 children
        with autism (with or without a history of regression) will be included in the evaluations
        and 50 children with developmental delays (without autism) will be recruited as contrast
        subjects. The age range of all groups will be between 12 and 60 months at first visit. We
        will over-recruit for children in the 12-36 month age range, in order to maximize
        participants of the age when regression associated with autism diagnosis is most likely.

        Regression will be defined as:

        Language loss: Loss of at least 3 spontaneously meaningful words (excluding mama or dada)
        used for at least a month, and lost for at least a month.

        AND/OR

        Nonverbal communication/social loss: Loss of more than one nonverbal communicative
        behavior (e.g. gestures, joint attention, eye contact, imagination, pretend play, sharing,
        showing, watching children, orienting to name, social smiling, social games, spontaneous
        imitation of actions, response to social overtures).

        Autism groups (AUT-R &amp; AUT-NR): Children with a diagnosis of autism or referral from
        professional with concerns of a diagnosis of autism will be evaluated with the ADI-R and
        ADOS. Those meeting research criteria for autism will be included.

        Although there is overlap in the age period for regression specified in this protocol
        (regression between 15-30 months) and that described for childhood disintegrative disorder
        (CDD) (the DSM-IV criteria for CDD indicate apparently normal development for the first 2
        years after birth), the criteria for CDD also indicate a diagnosis can only be made if
        symptoms are not better accounted for by another pervasive developmental disorder such as
        autism. Symptoms of CDD that separate it from autism include loss of acquired skills in
        areas such as motor skills and bowel or bladder control, while the focus of the current
        study is on regression in core symptoms of autism (i.e. socio-communicative skills). Thus,
        the current protocol will include children with regression over 2 who meet criteria for
        autism, but not those who only meet criteria for CDD.

        Typically Developing control group (TYP): No diagnosis of developmental delay and no
        first-degree relatives with history of developmental problems.

        Developmental Delay group (DD): Developmental scores (Performance Quotient and Verbal
        Quotient) greater than 1.5 standard deviations below mean on Mullen Scales of Early
        Learning

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Diagnosis of cerebral palsy. For the typical controls only, a history of extremely
             low birthweight (due to prematurity or intrauterine growth failure).

          2. If behavioral management issues (e.g. self-injury, aggressiveness) are severe to the
             extent that the screening protocol was aborted.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>7 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan E Swedo, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2006-M-0102.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahlsén G, Rosengren L, Belfrage M, Palm A, Haglid K, Hamberger A, Gillberg C. Glial fibrillary acidic protein in the cerebrospinal fluid of children with autism and other neuropsychiatric disorders. Biol Psychiatry. 1993 May 15;33(10):734-43.</citation>
    <PMID>8353169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashwood P, Anthony A, Pellicer AA, Torrente F, Walker-Smith JA, Wakefield AJ. Intestinal lymphocyte populations in children with regressive autism: evidence for extensive mucosal immunopathology. J Clin Immunol. 2003 Nov;23(6):504-17.</citation>
    <PMID>15031638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashwood P, Van de Water J. Is autism an autoimmune disease? Autoimmun Rev. 2004 Nov;3(7-8):557-62. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15546805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 6, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>March 1, 2006</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neurodevelopmental Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurological Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Children- Onset</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Pervasive Developmental Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>PDD</keyword>
  <keyword>Autism</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
