<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="974">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01680653</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012PG-T1D001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01680653</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing State of the Art Remote Glucose Monitoring at Diabetes Camp</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pilot Study in Testing State of the Art Remote Glucose Monitoring at Diabetes Camp</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>DexCom, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Leona and Harry Helmsely Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of low blood sugar and hypoglycemic seizures at diabetes camp has been reduced
      thanks to overnight blood glucose level testing. The timing of the overnight blood test is
      often arbitrary and it is unclear when the highest frequency of nocturnal hypoglycemic
      events at camp are occurring. It is also unclear what the most appropriate treatment for
      nocturnal hypoglycemia is: simple carbohydrates, or mini-glucagon.

      In this study, we will use Continuous Glucose Monitors that will send subject data securely
      to a remote computer located in the medical cottage at camp throughout the night. Study
      staff will monitor the computer and will intervene on low blood sugar as it occurs in real
      time. On half of the nights, campers will receive mini-glucagon for low blood sugar, and on
      the rest, they will receive standard carbohydrate treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will include approximately 20 subjects with T1D per camp session. 10 will be
      linked to remote monitoring with the DIAs, and 10 will wear the Dexcom CGM with the same
      threshold alarm setting as those wearing the DiAs (70 mg/dl), but without remote monitoring.

      Study participants will be between the ages of 7-21 with type 1 diabetes. This would allow
      for a counselor in training or a young counselor with a history of recent nocturnal
      hypoglycemia to be included. It is these late adolescents and young adults who often have
      the most severe hypoglycemic events during a camp session. We will preferentially recruit
      campers into the study who: 1) have a history of nocturnal hypoglycemia requiring treatment
      within the last 2 months, 2) have hypoglycemia unawareness confirmed with the Clark
      screening test, 3) have an A1c of &lt;8% while requiring &gt;0.7 units/kg/day of insulin and
      diabetes duration of &gt; 1year.

      At the beginning of camp, a Dexcom G4 sensor will be inserted into each participating
      subject and after the initial calibration, they will be calibrated with blood glucose levels
      in the morning and before bed each day as well as when the Dexcom sensor requests a
      calibration. All insulin doses and treatment decisions at camp will be based on capillary
      blood glucose levels and they will not be based on sensor readings. Each night, 10 of the 20
      campers will be randomly assigned to remote monitoring. The randomization schedule will be
      computer generated prior to camp. A hypoglycemia threshold will be set for 70 mg/dl. The
      Dexcom communicating with the DiAs will not sound a local alarm, but an alarm will be
      generated at the remote monitoring. Medical personnel on call at the remote monitoring
      station will come to the camper's cabin and confirmatory capillary blood glucose (CBG)
      glucose will be obtained. If the camper is &lt;70 hypoglycemia, treatment will be given (we
      will not use predictive alarms or use the rate of change to determine treatment). Treatment
      will be randomized to mini-glucagon or standard oral treatment if campers are &lt;70 mg/dl in a
      1:1 ratio. All subjects less than 70 mg/dl will then be retested in 15 minutes with a CBG to
      confirm recovery from hypoglycemia.

      If a sensor should fail or be dislodged during camp, it will be replaced. If a sensor needs
      to be replaced more than 2 times, a subject may be dropped and a different subject enrolled.

      There will be a designed medical staff person who will be monitoring subjects remotely each
      night. A second staff person will be available to go to subjects cabins to provide treatment
      for hypoglycemia. If a second event should occur at the same time, a third staff person will
      be &quot;on call&quot; to attend the second camper.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Supportive Care</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of nocturnal hypoglycemia</measure>
    <time_frame>8 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>minutes of glucose readings &lt; 70 mg/dl</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Glucose readings &lt;50 mg/dl</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>minutes &lt; 50 mg/dl on Dexcom sensor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Need for repeat treatments of hypoglcyemia</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>After treatment for hypoglycemia,how many additional treatments were required.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-Glucagon and Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects glucose data are remotely monitored at night using the University of Virginia (UVA) Diabetes Assistant (DiAs) Android Platform. Study staff intervenes with a fingerstick blood glucose measurement when sensor value falls below 70mg/dL. If fingerstick value is less than 70 mg/dL, hypoglycemic treatment is administered as below.
Administer mini-glucagon as treatment for nocturnal hypoglycemia. Administer 0.01 cc per number of years in age via insulin syringe, subcutaneously. This amounts to 1 unit per age, for example: an 8 year old gets 8 &quot;units&quot; glucagon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbohydrates and Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects glucose data are remotely monitored at night using the University of Virginia (UVA) Diabetes Assistant (DiAs) Android Platform. Study staff intervenes with a fingerstick blood glucose measurement when sensor value falls below 70mg/dL. If fingerstick value is less than 70 mg/dL, hypoglycemic treatment is administered as below.
Administration of carbohydrate per camp protocol to treat nocturnal hypoglycemia. Expected treatment is 15-45g.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Carbohydrates No Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects wear a continuous glucose monitor for their own use, but they are not remotely monitored.
If hypoglycemia occurs and is acknowledged through standard camp protocol it will be treated with standard camp protocol administration of carbohydrates. Expected treatment is 15g-45g.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-Glucagon and No Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects wear a continuous glucose monitor for their own use, but they are not remotely monitored.
If hypoglycemia occurs and is acknowledged through standard camp protocol it will be treated with mini-glucagon.
Administer mini-glucagon as treatment for nocturnal hypoglycemia. Administer 0.01 cc per number of years in age via insulin syringe, subcutaneously. This amounts to 1 unit per age, for example: an 8 year old gets 8 &quot;units&quot; glucagon.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mini-glucagon</intervention_name>
    <description>Mini dose glucagon given for glucose &lt;70 mg/dl at a dose of 1unit/year of age</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-Glucagon and Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-Glucagon and No Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>glucagon</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Remote monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>Provides real-time continuous glucose monitoring</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mini-Glucagon and Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Carbohydrates and Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carbohydrates and remote monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>16 grams of carbohydrate with remote monitoring</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carbohydrates and Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carbohydrates No remote monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>Carbohydrates for hypoglycemia and no remote monitoring</description>
    <arm_group_label>Carbohydrates No Remote Monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of type 1 diabetes and using daily insulin therapy for at least
             one year

          -  Age 7-21 years

          -  Attendee of Camp De Los Ninos or Conrad Chinnock

          -  Come to camp with a consent already signed after having talked to study staff about
             the study, or at the onset of the camp meet with study staff and sign the consent
             before the first night at camp.

          -  Using multiple daily insulin injections (Lantus) or on an insulin pump (any brand)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cystic fibrosis

          -  Medications such as current use of oral steroids or other medications, which in the
             judgment of the investigator would be a contraindication to participation in the
             study.

          -  History of adhesive allergies which would interfere with sensor wear.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruce Buckingham, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 31, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 28, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bruce A. Buckingham</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Glucagon</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucagon-Like Peptide 1</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
