<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1315">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02001272</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-772</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02001272</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EWOC-1 Trial: Carboplatin +/- Paclitaxel in Vulnerable Elderly Patients With Stage III-IV Advanced Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>EWOC-1</acronym>
  <official_title>EWOC-1 Trial: Multicenter, Randomized Trial of Carboplatin +/- Paclitaxel in Vulnerable Elderly Patients With Stage III-IV Advanced Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospices Civils de Lyon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospices Civils de Lyon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The current standard of first-line chemotherapy in advanced ovarian cancer is the
      combination of carboplatin AUC 5mg/mL/min and paclitaxel 175 mg.m-². This combination is
      feasible in selected elderly patients such as those included in prospective trials. These
      trials, however, include a minority of the elderly population. In wider selection of
      patients &gt;70 years old, the standard carboplatin-paclitaxel regimen has been shown to induce
      an excess of toxicity and premature treatment stopping. For elderly patients thought to be
      vulnerable and at high risk of toxicity with the standard 3-weekly carboplatin-paclitaxel
      regimen, other options are used in routine practice. One option is to delete paclitaxel and
      treat elderly patients with carboplatin as a single agent. An alternative is to use the
      carboplatin-paclitaxel regimen in a weekly schedule for both drugs such as reported by the
      MITO (Multicentre Italian Trial in Ovarian Cancer).

      To date, there is no randomized trial which could give us some evidence of how to select
      patients who could benefit most of one or the other regimen described above. The 4th Ovarian
      Cancer Consensus Conference has indeed recognised the medical unmet need of adapted therapy
      for elderly patients with ovarian cancer and the necessity of additional research in this
      population.

      Recently, GINECO has described a Geriatric Vulnerability Score (GVS) in a population of
      elderly patients with advanced ovarian cancer included in a specific multicenter phase II
      trial. The best proportional hazard model fitting for overall survival identified the
      following geriatric covariates score as being poor survival risk factors: ADL score &lt;6, IADL
      score &lt;25, HADS score &gt;14, albuminemia &lt;35g/L and , lymphopenia &lt;1G/L. GVS is the sum of
      these risk factors for each patient. Using a cut off of 3, the GVS identified a group of
      patients at high risk of severe toxicity, early cessation of treatment, unplanned
      hospitalization and adverse outcomes.

      This international multicentre randomized phase II trial will compare the success rate of
      delivering 6 courses of chemotherapy with evidence of efficacy and without premature
      termination for progression, death or unacceptable toxicity of three different chemotherapy
      regimens in a selected population of elderly patients with a GVS ≥ 3:

        -  Arm A: Paclitaxel 175mg/m²/3 hours, I.V. and carboplatin AUC 5, I.V. every 3 weeks

        -  Arm B: Carboplatin monotherapy AUC 5 or 6 every 3 weeks

        -  Arm C: Weekly paclitaxel 60 mg/m²/1 hour and weekly carboplatin AUC 2 (d1, d8, d15
           every 4 weeks)

      The total number of patients to be enrolled is 240, ie 22 in each arm (total = 66) at the
      first step, then 58 more by arm (total=174) after interim analysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment success.Treatment success is defined as the ability to deliver 6 courses of chemotherapy without premature termination for progression, death or unacceptable toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 courses of chemotherapy i.e 4.5 to 6 months (depending on the arm)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Treatment success is defined as the ability to deliver 6 courses of chemotherapy without premature termination for progression, death or unacceptable toxicity. Unacceptable toxicity is defined as a major adverse event related to chemotherapy or treatment procedure leading either to early treatment stopping, to an unplanned hospital admission or to death or to a dose delay lasting more than 14 days or more than 2 dose reductions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Therapeutical strategy</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of treatment (6 courses ), i.e 4.5 to 6 months (depending on the arm)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Therapeutical strategy will be assessed by measuring the feasibility of performing an optimal surgery and feasibility of performing neoadjuvant chemotherapy and surgery and post operative chemotherapy until 6 courses in case of planned interval debulking surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time period from the date of randomization to the date of death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Progression-free survival is defined as the time period from the date of randomization to the date of disease progression or death whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of treatment (6 courses ), i.e 4.5 to 6 months (depending on the arm)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Quality of life is evaluated using the FACT-O questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of treatment (6 courses ), i.e 4.5 to 6 months (depending on the arm)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Adverse events are defined using the NCI-CTC AE scale version 4.3</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aging biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of treatment (6 courses ), i.e 4.5 to 6 months (depending on the arm)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Aging biomarkers are represented by the expression level of cathelin-related antimicrobial peptide or CRAMP, stathmin, EF-1α, and chitinase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A:Paclitaxel + Carboplatin every 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the arm A receive 6 courses the following regimen: Paclitaxel 175 mg/m²/3 hours, I.V. and carboplatin AUC 5, I.V. every 3 weeks (1 cycle = 21 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B:Carboplatin monotherapy every 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the arm B receive 6 courses the following regimen: Carboplatin monotherapy AUC 5 or 6 every 3 weeks (1 cycle = 21 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>C:Weekly Paclitaxel and Carboplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the arm C receive 6 courses the following regimen: weekly paclitaxel 60 mg/m²/1 hour and weekly carboplatin AUC 2 (d1, d8, d15 ; d1=d29) (1 cycle = 28 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel + Carboplatin every 3 weeks</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive a premedication of 130mg prednisolone the day before (22 pm) and the morning (7 am). A pretreatment using corticosteroids, antihistamines and H2 antagonists and setrons in accordance with local standards of care will be administered 30 minutes before Paclitaxel administration. At H0, Paclitaxel is administered at 175mg/m² in 3 hours then Carboplatin is administered at AUC 5mg/mL/min.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A:Paclitaxel + Carboplatin every 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin monotherapy every 3 weeks</intervention_name>
    <description>A pretreatment using setrons in accordance with local standards of care will be administered 30 minutes before Carboplatin at AUC 5 to 6mg/mL/min in 1 hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>B:Carboplatin monotherapy every 3 weeks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Weekly Paclitaxel and Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>A pretreatment using corticosteroids, antihistamines and H2 antagonists and setrons in accordance with local standards of care will be administered 30 minutes before Paclitaxel 60mg/m² in 1 hour followed by Carboplatin at AUC 2mg/mL/min in 1 hour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>C:Weekly Paclitaxel and Carboplatin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Woman &gt;70 year old

          -  Histologically or cytologically proven FIGO stage III to IV epithelial ovarian cancer
             or peritoneal primary or fallopian tube. A cytological proof is accepted if
             associated with a ratio of CA125/CEA &gt;25 and a radiological pelvic mass.

          -  GVS (Geriatric Vulnerability Score) &gt;3.

          -  Adequate bone marrow function including the following: Neutrophils ≥ 1.5 x 109/L ,
             platelets ≥100 x 109/L and hemoglobin ≥9 g/dL.

          -  Adequate glomerular filtration rate &gt;40 ml/min (estimates based on MDRD or Chatelut
             formula are sufficient)

          -  No icterus.

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 3 months.

          -  Written informed consent obtained.

          -  Covered by a Health System where applicable

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other malignancy within the last 5 years, except for adequately treated carcinoma in
             situ of the cervix or squamous carcinoma of the skin, or adequately controlled
             limited basal cell skin cancer.

          -  Prior history of chemotherapy.

          -  Prior history of radiotherapy which may affect patient tolerability to chemotherapy.

          -  Major perturbations of liver biology: Bilirubin &gt; 2 fold the upper normal limit
             (UNL), SGOT-SGPT &gt; 3 fold UNL.

          -  Patient unable to be regularly followed for any reason (geographic, familial, social,
             psychologic).

          -  Any mental or physical handicap at risk of interfering with the appropriate
             treatment.

          -  Known allergy to Cremophor ® EL -containing drugs.

          -  Any administrative or legal supervision where applicable
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claire FALANDRY, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Service d'oncogériatrie, Centre Hospitalier Lyon Sud, Hospices Civils de Lyon</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Claire FALANDRY, MD</last_name>
    <phone>4 78 86 15 80</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>claire.falandry@chu-lyon.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nathalie LE FUR</last_name>
    <phone>1 42 34 83 23</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>nlefur@arcagy.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service oncogériatrie, Centre Hospitalier Lyon Sud, Hospices Civils de Lyon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pierre-Bénite</city>
        <zip>69495</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Claire FALANDRY, MD</last_name>
      <phone>4 78 86 15 80</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>claire.falandry@chu-lyon.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claire FALANDRY, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.arcagy.org</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.gcig.igcs.org/</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.esgo.org/engot/Pages/AboutENGOT.aspx</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 13, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 22, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Vulnerable</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Chemotherapy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
