<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="352">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00150774</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N166</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00150774</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Levetiracetam as add-on Treatment of Myoclonic Jerks in Adolescents + Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-blind, Multicenter, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Levetiracetam (LEV) (Oral Tablets of 500 mg b.i.d.) at a Dose of 3000 mg/Day as Adjunctive Treatment in Adolescents (≥ 12 Years) and Adults (≤ 65 Years) Suffering From Idiopathic Generalized Epilepsy With Myoclonic Seizures.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UCB Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UCB Pharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Austria: Federal Ministry for Health and Women</authority>
    <authority>Australia: Department of Health and Ageing Therapeutic Goods Administration</authority>
    <authority>Belgium: Federal Agency for Medicines and Health Products, FAMHP</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>France: Afssaps - Agence française de sécurité sanitaire des produits de santé (Saint-Denis)</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</authority>
    <authority>Ireland: Irish Medicines Board</authority>
    <authority>Italy: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Mexico: National Institute of Public Health, Health Secretariat</authority>
    <authority>New Zealand: Food Safety Authority</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Ministry of Health and Consumption</authority>
    <authority>Switzerland: Swissmedic</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: The Central Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects (CCMO)</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A double-blind, placebo-controlled study to assess the efficacy of adjunctive treatment with
      LEV 3000mg/day in reducing myoclonic seizures in adolescents and adults suffering from
      idiopathic generalised epilepsy and to evaluate the safety of LEV in the same population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2004</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2004</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double-Blind, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Responder rate in myoclonic (type IIB) seizures days over 16 weeks</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of levetiracetam by means of AE, laboratory assessments, plasma concentration</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>116</enrollment>
  <condition>Generalized Convulsive Epilepsy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levetiracetam</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with a confirmed diagnosis consistent with idiopathic generalized epilepsy
             experiencing myoclonic seizures (IIB) that are classifiable according to the
             International Classification of Epileptic Seizures. To ensure an idiopathic
             generalized epilepsy population, only these subjects with the diagnosis of juvenile
             myoclonic epilepsy (JME), juvenile absence epilepsy (JAE) or epilepsy with
             generalized tonic- clonic seizures on awakening must be included.

          -  Presence of at least eight days with at least one myoclonic seizure (IIB) per day
             during the eight weeks of the Baseline period.

          -  Absence of brain lesion documented on a CT scan or MRI; if a CT scan or MRI has not
             been performed within the past five years before Visit 1, a CT scan (or MRI where
             legally required) should be performed during the Baseline period.

          -  Presence of EEG features consistent with idiopathic generalized epilepsy on an EEG
             recorded during the Baseline period or no more than one year before Visit 1.

          -  Male/female children ≥ 12 years of age or adult ≤ 65 years of age at Visit 1.

          -  Subject on a stable dose of one standard anti-epileptic treatment for at least four
             weeks before Visit 1.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous exposure to levetiracetam.

          -  History of partial seizures.

          -  History of convulsive or non-convulsive status epilepticus within 3 months prior to
             Visit 1.

          -  Subject taking vigabatrin or tiagabine, subject on felbamate with less than 18 months
             exposure, and subject under vagal nerve stimulation or ketogenic diet.

          -  Subject taking any drug (except the concomitant AEDs) with possible CNS effects.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>UCB Clinical Trial Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>UCB Pharma</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ucb.com/_up/ucb_com_patients/documents/N166_CSS_20060721.pdf</url>
    <description>Clinical Study Summary on UCB.com</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rosenfeld WE, Benbadis S, Edrich P, Tassinari CA, Hirsch E. Levetiracetam as add-on therapy for idiopathic generalized epilepsy syndromes with onset during adolescence: analysis of two randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies. Epilepsy Res. 2009 Jul;85(1):72-80. doi: 10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2009.02.016. Epub 2009 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>19327967</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Noachtar S, Andermann E, Meyvisch P, Andermann F, Gough WB, Schiemann-Delgado J; N166 Levetiracetam Study Group. Levetiracetam for the treatment of idiopathic generalized epilepsy with myoclonic seizures. Neurology. 2008 Feb 19;70(8):607-16. doi: 10.1212/01.wnl.0000297512.18364.40.</citation>
    <PMID>18285535</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2010</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>September 16, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>September 6, 2005</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Idiopathic Generalized Epilepsy, Myoclonic seizures</keyword>
  <keyword>Keppra - Levetiracetam</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy, Generalized</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Etiracetam</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Piracetam</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
