<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1060">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00025987</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>020025</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>02-N-0025</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00025987</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Temperature Response to a Head-Neck Cooling System</brief_title>
  <official_title>Thermal Responses In Normal Volunteers To Head-Neck Cooling</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the effectiveness of a specially designed head-neck cooling system
      for way lowering the body's central, or core, temperature and cooling the brain. Brain
      cooling has an effect on stopping seizure discharges in the brain as well as the seizures
      themselves. If this system works to cool the brain, a similar study may be tried in patients
      with epilepsy.

      Normal volunteers 21 years of age and older who have no medical or neurological condition
      and do not use any medications may be eligible for this study. Candidates will be screened
      with an interview. Women will have a pregnancy test. Those enrolled will be hospitalized
      twice for overnight stays, with the admissions 2 to 3 days apart.

      Participants will have a medical history, physical and neurological examinations,
      electroencephalogram (EEG) and electrocardiogram (EKG). Then, electrodes will be attached to
      their scalp, forearm and calf to measure temperatures in those locations. Intestinal (core)
      temperature will be measured with a temperature-sensing pill, which will be swallowed
      earlier), and a hand-held infrared thermometer will be used to measure temperatures from the
      ear canal, face, head, arms legs, and abdomen. Electrodes on the scalp will also measure
      changes in blood volume in the brain for a study of brain blood flow. Subjects will be
      seated in a comfortable chair and fitted with the cooling system, a portable unit with a
      circulating coolant. Cooling will last 30 minutes for the first session and 60 minutes for
      the second. Participants will be monitored for at least 30 minutes after each session to
      track temperature changes and have a post-cooling EEG recording.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this protocol is to study thermal responses in normal volunteers using a special
      cooling system designed to cool the head and neck. Temperature will be monitored at various
      locations including the scalp, face, mouth, ears (tympanic), arms, legs, and rectum.
      Previous studies indicate that cooling of the brain can be achieved with the head-neck
      cooling method. We hope to derive cooling parameters that will be used in a future study
      involving patients with epilepsy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 2003</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <enrollment>10</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Head and Neck Cooling System</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thermometer Pill</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        21 years and older

        No neurological or medical condition

        No use medication of any kind, including prescription, over-the-counter or herbal
        medicines.

        No history of any kind of gastrointestinal tract disorders

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Women who are pregnant (screened with urine pregnancy test)

        Those with progressive neurological disorders

        Those sensitive to coldness

        Those taking medication

        Those who smoke

        Those whose heart rate less than 50 or more than 100

        Those who are less than 80 pounds or excessively overweight

        Those who have a history of gastrointestinal disorders (i.e. diverticulitis and other
        inflammatory bowel diseases)

        Those who have difficulty swallowing or whose gag reflex is impaired
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amoateng-Adjepong Y, Del Mundo J, Manthous CA. Accuracy of an infrared tympanic thermometer. Chest. 1999 Apr;115(4):1002-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10208200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ao H, Moon JK, Tanimoto H, Sakanashi Y, Terasaki H. Jugular vein temperature reflects brain temperature during hypothermia. Resuscitation. 2000 Jul;45(2):111-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10950319</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baumgartner FJ, Janusz MT, Jamieson WR, Winkler T, Burr LH, Vestrup JA. Cardiopulmonary bypass for resuscitation of patients with accidental hypothermia and cardiac arrest. Can J Surg. 1992 Apr;35(2):184-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1562930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2003</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>March 3, 2008</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 2, 2001</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Brain</keyword>
  <keyword>Temperature</keyword>
  <keyword>Lower</keyword>
  <keyword>Tympanic</keyword>
  <keyword>Rectal</keyword>
  <keyword>Cooling of the Head and Neck</keyword>
  <keyword>Control</keyword>
  <keyword>Epilepsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
