<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="23">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02477839</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SP0967</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-000717-20</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02477839</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Lacosamide as Adjunctive Therapy in Subjects ≥1 Month to &lt;4 Years With Partial-onset Seizures</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Double-blind, Randomized, Placebo-controlled, Parallel-group Study to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Lacosamide as Adjunctive Therapy in Subjects With Epilepsy ≥1 Month to &lt;4 Years of Age With Partial-onset Seizures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UCB BIOSCIENCES, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pharmaceutical Research Associates</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UCB Pharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Argentina: Administracion Nacional de Medicamentos, Alimentos y Tecnologia Medica</authority>
    <authority>Australia: Department of Health and Ageing Therapeutic Goods Administration</authority>
    <authority>Brazil: National Health Surveillance Agency</authority>
    <authority>Bulgaria: Bulgarian Drug Agency</authority>
    <authority>Canada: Health Canada</authority>
    <authority>Chile: Instituto de Salud Pública de Chile</authority>
    <authority>Colombia: INVIMA Instituto Nacional de Vigilancia de Medicamentos y Alimentos</authority>
    <authority>Croatia: Ministry of Health and Social Care</authority>
    <authority>Georgia: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Greece: National Organization of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Israel: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Lithuania: State Medicine Control Agency - Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Moldova: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>Poland: Office for Registration of Medicinal Products, Medical Devices and Biocidal Products</authority>
    <authority>Romania: National Medicines Agency</authority>
    <authority>Czech Republic: State Institute for Drug Control</authority>
    <authority>France: Afssaps - Agence française de sécurité sanitaire des produits de santé (Saint-Denis)</authority>
    <authority>Serbia and Montenegro: Agency for Drugs and Medicinal Devices</authority>
    <authority>South Korea: Korea Food and Drug Administration (KFDA)</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>Taiwan : Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Thailand: Ministry of Public Health</authority>
    <authority>Ukraine: Ministry of Health</authority>
    <authority>United Kingdom: Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>Romania: National Agency for Medicines and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Hungary: National Institute for Quality and Organizational Development in Healthcare and Medicines</authority>
    <authority>Mexico: Federal Commission for Protection Against Health Risks</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this trial is to assess the effectiveness and the safety of Lacosamide
      administered as add-on therapy with 1 to 3 anti-seizure medications. This trial is for
      children aged 1 month to less than 4 years with epilepsy who currently have uncontrolled
      partial-onset seizures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The trial consists of a 7-day Baseline Period, a 20-day Titration Period, a 7-day
      Maintenance Period, and a 12-day Transition Period for subjects who complete the study and
      choose to enter the extension study. Subjects who will not enter the extension study will
      continue after the Maintenance Period with a 16-day Taper Period followed by a 30-day Safety
      Follow-Up Period. The Taper Period and Safety Follow-Up are also applicable for subjects not
      eligible for continuation and therefore ending the study earlier.

      If subjects meet the eligibility criteria for extension study, they will be randomized to
      receive either Lacosamide 8 mg/kg/day to 12 mg/kg/day, or placebo during the Maintenance
      Phase. The dose of Lacosamide will be titrated from 4mg/kg/day at study start to maximum of
      12 mg/kg/day at 3-day intervals of 1-2 mg/kg/day.

      All subjects who complete the 20-day Titration Period will enter the 7-day Maintenance
      Period. No dose adjustment is allowed during the Maintenance Phase. The Treatment Phase is
      defined as the combined Titration and Maintenance Phases.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Applicable for US only: The change in average daily frequency (ADF) of electrographic partial-onset seizures from Baseline to the End-of-Maintenance Period</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The change in ADF of electrographic partial-onset seizures as measured on the 72-hour End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG (video-electroencephalogram) compared to the 72-hour End-of-Baseline Period video-EEG</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Applicable for European Union (EU) and for US if dropout rate is &gt;10% : Proportion of responders : ≥ 50% reduction in partial onset seizure frequency from Baseline to the End-of-Maintenance Period</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The proportion of responders where a responder is a subject experiencing a 50% or greater reduction in their average daily frequency of electrographic partial-onset seizures recorded on the 72-hour End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG compared to the 72-hour End-of-Baseline Period video-EEG</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject withdrawals due to Adverse Events (AEs) during the study</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 to up to Day 93</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Subject withdrawals due to AEs during the duration of Study (including up to 30 days follow up after IMP(investigational medicinal product) discontinuation)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute change in average daily frequency (ADF) of electrographic partial-onset seizures from Baseline to End-of-Maintenance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The absolute change in ADF of electrographic partial-onset seizures as measured on the 72-hour End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG compared to the 72-hour End-of-Baseline Period video-EEG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in average daily frequency (ADF) of electrographic partial-onset seizures from Baseline to End-of Maintenance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The percent change in ADF of electrographic partial-onset seizures as measured on the 72-hour End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG compared to the 72-hour End-of-Baseline Period video-EEG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects who achieved &quot;seizure-free&quot; status at the End-of-Maintenance Period</measure>
    <time_frame>At Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance Period)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects who achieved &quot;seizure-free&quot; status (yes/no) for subjects who completed at least 48 hours of interpretable video-EEG recording during the End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects experiencing a ≥ 25% to &lt; 50% reduction in average daily frequency (ADF) of electrographic partial-onset seizures from Baseline to the End-of-Maintenance Period</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing a ≥ 25% to &lt; 50% reduction in ADF of electrographic partial-onset seizures from the End-Of-Baseline Period video-EEG to the End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects experiencing a 50% to 75% reduction in average daily frequency (ADF) of electrographic partial-onset seizures from Baseline to the End-of-Maintenance Period</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing 50% to 75% reduction in ADF of electrographic partial-onset seizures from the End-Of-Baseline Period video-EEG to the End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects experiencing no change in average daily frequency (ADF) of electrographic partial-onset seizures (between &lt;25% reduction and &lt;25% increase) from Baseline to the End-of-Maintenance Period</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing no change in ADF of electrographic partial-onset seizures (between &lt;25% reduction and &lt;25% increase) from the End-of-Baseline Period video-EEG to the End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects experiencing a &gt;75% reduction in average daily frequency (ADF) of electrographic partial-onset seizures from Baseline to the End-of Maintenance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing a &gt;75% reduction in ADF of electrographic partial-onset seizures from the end-of-Baseline Period video-EEG to the End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects experiencing an increase in average daily frequency (ADF) of electrographic partial-onset seizures of ≥25% from Baseline to the End-of-Maintenance Period</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Day 27 (End-of-Maintenance)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Proportion of subjects experiencing an increase in ADF of electrographic partial-onset seizures of ≥25% from the End-of-Baseline Period video-EEG to the End-of-Maintenance Period video-EEG</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">244</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy With Partial-onset Seizures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lacosamide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lacosamide syrup 8 mg/kg/day to 12 mg/kg/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matching placebo syrup</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lacosamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Active Substance: Lacosamide; Pharmaceutical Form: Syrup; Concentration: 10 mg/mL; Route of Administration: oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lacosamide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vimpat</other_name>
    <other_name>UCB Code: SPM 927</other_name>
    <other_name>Abreviated name: LCM</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Active Substance: Placebo; Pharmaceutical Form: Syrup; Concentration: N/A; Route of Administration: oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PBO</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is male or female from ≥1 month (ie, 4 weeks after full term [37 weeks
             gestational age]) to &lt;4 years of age.

          -  Subject has a diagnosis of epilepsy with partial-onset seizures. The results of ≥1
             prior EEG and ≥1 magnetic resonance imaging/computerized tomography scan should be
             consistent with this diagnosis.

          -  Subject weighs ≥4 kg to &lt;30 kg at Visit 1.

          -  Subject has uncontrolled partial-onset seizures after an adequate course of treatment
             (in the opinion of the investigator) with ≥2 AEDs (antiepileptic drugs) (concurrently
             or sequentially).

          -  Subject has experienced ≥2 partial-onset seizures with or without secondary
             generalization during each consecutive 7-day period during the 2 weeks prior to Visit
             1.

          -  Subject has ≥2 partial-onset seizures with or without secondary generalization during
             the 72-hour Baseline video-EEG.

          -  Subject is on a stable (concurrently or sequentially) dosage regimen of 1 to 3 AEDs.
             The dosage regimen of concomitant AED therapy must be kept constant for a period of
             ≥2 weeks prior to Visit 1. A stable daily dosage regimen of a concomitant
             benzodiazepine (BZD) will be considered as a concomitant AED.

          -  Vagus nerve stimulation (VNS) is allowed and will not be counted as a concomitant
             AED. The VNS device must have been implanted for ≥6 months prior to Visit 1; device
             settings must be kept stable for ≥2 weeks prior to Visit 1 and kept stable during the
             Baseline, Treatment, and Transition Periods. Use of the VNS device magnet is allowed.

          -  Subject is an acceptable candidate for venipuncture

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has experienced febrile seizures exclusively. The occurrence of febrile
             seizures in addition to partial-onset seizures is not exclusionary.

          -  Subject is on a ketogenic or other specialized diet for the treatment of epilepsy. If
             the subject was on a ketogenic or other specialized diet in the past, they must be
             off this diet for ≥2 months prior to Visit 1.

          -  Subject has an alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), or
             total bilirubin level ≥2 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), or creatinine
             clearance &lt;30 mL/minute.

          -  Subject has a clinically relevant ECG abnormality, in the opinion of the investigator
             (eg, second or third degree heart block at rest or a corrected QT interval [QTc] ≥450
             ms).

          -  Subject has a hemodynamically significant congenital heart disease.

          -  Subject has an arrhythmic heart condition requiring medical therapy.

          -  Subject has a known history of severe anaphylactic reaction secondary to medication
             intake or serious blood dyscrasias.

          -  Subject has nonepileptic events that could be confused with seizures. Subjects may be
             included if epileptic events can be clearly distinguished and the frequency meets the
             study inclusion criteria.

          -  Subject has a current diagnosis of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, epilepsia partialis
             continua, primary generalized epilepsy, or seizures that are not of partial-onset
             origin.

          -  Subject has a history of status epilepticus ≤2 months prior to Screening (Visit 1).

          -  Subject has been treated with ethosuximide.

          -  Subject is currently being treated with vigabatrin or has discontinued use &lt;12 months
             prior to Visit 1. Subjects who were previously treated with vigabatrin and have
             discontinued use &gt;12 months prior to Visit 1 are eligible.

          -  Subject has been treated with felbamate and has experienced any serious toxicity
             issues (defined as liver failure, aplastic anemia) with this treatment. Subjects
             treated with felbamate for &lt;12 months are excluded. Subjects treated with felbamate
             for ≥12 months prior to Visit 1 and who have not experienced serious toxicity issues
             are eligible.

          -  Subject has an acute or subacutely progressive central nervous system disease.
             Subject has epilepsy secondary to a progressing cerebral disease or any other
             progressively neurodegenerative disease (malignant brain tumor or Rasmussen
             Syndrome).

          -  Subject has a known sodium channelopathy, such as Brugada syndrome.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>47 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>UCB Clinical Trial Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>+1 877 822 9493 (UCB)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>UCB Clinical Trial Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>+1 877 822</phone>
    <phone_ext>9493</phone_ext>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 638</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 105</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 117</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 138</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Paul</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 115</name>
      <address>
        <city>Henderson</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 120</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lebanon</city>
        <state>New Hampshire</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 631</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poughkeepsie</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 630</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 114</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 152</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto Alegre</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 156</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 320</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ostrava</city>
        <country>Czech Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 342</name>
      <address>
        <city>Picardie</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 347</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rouen Cedex</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 361</name>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 362</name>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 363</name>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 364</name>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 360</name>
      <address>
        <city>Debrecen</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 366</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pecs</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 397</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 398</name>
      <address>
        <city>Messina</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 381</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 386</name>
      <address>
        <city>Verona</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 214</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cheongju</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 210</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 212</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 215</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 411</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaunas</city>
        <country>Lithuania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 425</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poznan</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 422</name>
      <address>
        <city>Szczecin</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 570</name>
      <address>
        <city>Timisoara</city>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 222</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 224</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sp0967 235</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Lithuania</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 4, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 13, 2015</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>epilepsy</keyword>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>partial-onset seizures</keyword>
  <keyword>Lacosamide (LCM)</keyword>
  <keyword>LCM</keyword>
  <keyword>pediatric</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Seizures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Lacosamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
