<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="845">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01270581</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-0603</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01270581</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High Flow Nasal Cannula Versus Bubble Nasal CPAP for the Treatment of Transient Tachypnea of the Newborn in Infants ≥ 35 Weeks Gestation</brief_title>
  <official_title>High Flow Nasal Cannula vs Bubble Nasal CPAP for the Treatment of Transient Tachypnea of the Newborn in Infants ≥ 35 Weeks Gestation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective is to determine whether High Flow Nasal Cannula (HFNC) is a superior
      respiratory modality for neonates ≥36 weeks with transient tachypnea of the newborn (TTN)
      when compared to the standard of care modality (NCPAP).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Transient Tachypnea of the Newborn, fetal lung fluid retention causing poor lung compliance
      and atelectasis, is a common entity in neonates ≥ 36 weeks in our unit. Currently our
      standard of care includes using the respiratory modality of bubble nasal continuous positive
      airway pressure (BNCPAP) to support these neonates during this illness. BNCPAP provides
      positive distending pressure to recruit alveoli and prevent atelectasis, however, it is
      associated with air leak (pneumothorax, pneumomediastinum), nasal irritation and necrosis,
      and intolerance. HFNC is another respiratory modality that uses high flow gas that also
      provides positive distending pressure and thus prevents atelectasis. This modality does not
      cause nasal irritation or necrosis and has a minimal risk of air leak. We postulate that
      HFNC is a superior modality to BNCPAP in treating neonates ≥ 36 weeks with TTN. This will be
      determined by comparing the duration of respiratory support (in hours) for newborns ≥ 36
      weeks gestation with a diagnosis to TTN randomized to receive either NCPAP or HFNC for
      respiratory care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>duration of respiratory support</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>esophageal pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>determination and comparison of esophageal pressure as an indirect measurement of positive distending pressure generated by NCPAP and HFNC</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time to first enteral feed</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>time to first oral feed</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>weight gain</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>frequency of desaturations</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>air leak syndrome</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>nasal irritation</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>local columella necrosis</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>need for endotracheal intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>need for mechanical ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>average of 7 days</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Transient Tachypnea of the Newborn</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Flow Nasal Cannula</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Unlike the nasal prongs for NCPAP (which fit tightly in the nares), the nasal cannula for HFNC have smaller, loose-fitting prong. With HFNC, positive airway pressure is achieved by high gas flow through the cannula into the external nares which provide resistance to expiration and facilitate inspiration. The distending pressure is determined by the size and structure of the nasal cannula, gas flow rate, and the neonate's airway anatomy 4,5,7. Newborns randomized to HFNC will be started on a flow rate of 4L/min and supplemental oxygen will be provided to maintain oxygen saturations between 88-93% (experimental group). Once initiated, the gas flow rate will be titrated as needed by the attending neonatologist to ameliorate signs of respiratory distress to a maximum flow rate of 6L/min. The nasal cannula size (0.2 cm or 0.3 mm outer diameter) will determined by the caliber of the subject's nares).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group- Bubble Nasal CPAP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>NCPAP provides continuous distending airway pressure during inspiration and expiration via nasal prongs; this has been shown to increase lung volume by increasing alveolar size, recruiting collapsed alveoli, and preventing atelectasis. Improved lung volumes decrease V/Q mismatch and improve the clinical course of neonates with RDS, and as such, early NCPAP use often avoids the need for intubation and mechanical ventilation. Newborns receiving bubble NCPAP will be placed on a PEEP 5cm H2O, and supplemental oxygen will be provided to maintain oxygen saturation between 88-93% (standard of care group) as is standard practice. The size of the nasal prongs used will be based on the subject's weight as per the manufacturer instructions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High Flow Nasal Cannula</intervention_name>
    <description>Humidified high flow nasal cannula (HFNC) has emerged as an alternative respiratory modality for late preterm newborns with respiratory distress. Like NCPAP, oxygen is delivered to the infant via nasal prongs and provides a continuous distending pressure. Unlike the nasal prongs for NCPAP (which fit tightly in the nares), the nasal cannula for HFNC have smaller, loose-fitting prong. With HFNC, positive airway pressure is achieved by high gas flow through the cannula into the external nares which provide resistance to expiration and facilitate inspiration. The distending pressure is determined by the size and structure of the nasal cannula, gas flow rate, and the neonate's airway anatomy 4,5,7.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Flow Nasal Cannula</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bubble Nasal CPAP</intervention_name>
    <description>NCPAP provides continuous distending airway pressure during inspiration and expiration via nasal prongs; this has been shown to increase lung volume by increasing alveolar size, recruiting collapsed alveoli, and preventing atelectasis. Improved lung volumes decrease V/Q mismatch and improve the clinical course of neonates with RDS, and as such, early NCPAP use often avoids the need for intubation and mechanical ventilation. Newborns receiving bubble NCPAP will be placed on a PEEP 5cm H2O, and supplemental oxygen will be provided to maintain oxygen saturation between 88-93% (standard of care group) as is standard practice. The size of the nasal prongs used will be based on the subject's weight as per the manufacturer instructions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group- Bubble Nasal CPAP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  gestational age ≥ 35 weeks

          -  diagnosis of TTN, defined as respiratory rate &gt;60, presence of subcostal and /or
             intercostal retractions, nasal flaring, grunting, oxygen saturations 70-93% on room
             air, and radiological evidence of perihilar streaking and patchy infiltrates

          -  admission to the NICU at Mount Sinai hospital within first 24 hours of life

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  gestational age &lt; 35 weeks

          -  history of thick meconium stained fluid and/or diagnosis of meconium aspiration
             syndrome

          -  diagnosis of major congenital pulmonary or cardiac anomalies

          -  initial CXR demonstrating air leak

          -  respiratory distress first occurring after 24 hours of life

          -  presumptive diagnosis of RDS as indicated by the need for FiO2 &gt; 40%, severe
             retractions and grunting with poor air entry, and diffuse alveolar consolidation on
             chest radiograph
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Hours</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea Weintraub, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Loren M DeLuca, DO</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-6186</phone>
      <email>loren.deluca@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Andrea Weintraub, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-6186</phone>
      <email>andrea.weintraub@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea Weintraub, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Loren M DeLuca, DO</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Green, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dani C, Pratesi S, Migliori C, Bertini G. High flow nasal cannula therapy as respiratory support in the preterm infant. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2009 Jul;44(7):629-34. doi: 10.1002/ppul.21051. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19499590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jasin LR, Kern S, Thompson S, Walter C, Rone JM, Yohannan MD. Subcutaneous scalp emphysema, pneumo-orbitis and pneumocephalus in a neonate on high humidity high flow nasal cannula. J Perinatol. 2008 Nov;28(11):779-81. doi: 10.1038/jp.2008.99.</citation>
    <PMID>18974751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lampland AL, Plumm B, Meyers PA, Worwa CT, Mammel MC. Observational study of humidified high-flow nasal cannula compared with nasal continuous positive airway pressure. J Pediatr. 2009 Feb;154(2):177-82. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2008.07.021. Epub 2008 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18760803</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shoemaker MT, Pierce MR, Yoder BA, DiGeronimo RJ. High flow nasal cannula versus nasal CPAP for neonatal respiratory disease: a retrospective study. J Perinatol. 2007 Feb;27(2):85-91.</citation>
    <PMID>17262040</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sreenan C, Lemke RP, Hudson-Mason A, Osiovich H. High-flow nasal cannulae in the management of apnea of prematurity: a comparison with conventional nasal continuous positive airway pressure. Pediatrics. 2001 May;107(5):1081-3.</citation>
    <PMID>11331690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Locke RG, Wolfson MR, Shaffer TH, Rubenstein SD, Greenspan JS. Inadvertent administration of positive end-distending pressure during nasal cannula flow. Pediatrics. 1993 Jan;91(1):135-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8416477</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2012</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 11, 2012</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>December 21, 2010</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>transient tachypnea of the newborn</keyword>
  <keyword>high flow nasal cannula</keyword>
  <keyword>bubble nasal</keyword>
  <keyword>continuous positive airway pressure</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Tachypnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Transient Tachypnea of the Newborn</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
