<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1177">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02272725</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>31907</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02272725</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-steroidal Anti-inflammatory Affect on Kidneys in Endurance Distances</brief_title>
  <acronym>NAKED</acronym>
  <official_title>Non-steroidal Anti-inflammatory Affect on Kidneys in Endurance Distances</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of this study is to evaluate the safety of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
      drugs (NSAIDs) and their impact on renal function and/or contribution to exercise-associated
      hyponatremia (EAH) during an ultramarathon foot race. There is currently much debate over
      whether NSAID ingestion during endurance events contributes to acute kidney injury.
      Endurance events often ignite a &quot;perfect storm&quot; of physiologic insults- heat stress,
      dehydration, and myopathy- which can all negatively impact kidney function. There is a
      concern that NSAIDs may further potentiate these negative effects as well as contribute to
      EAH through its anti-diuretic affect. To date, no powered, prospective study has ever
      examined the effects of NSAIDs on either of these two biochemical outcomes

      Ultramarathon endurance events, defined as any race longer than a marathon (26.2 miles), are
      increasing in popularity, with a 10% increase in annual participants, and more than 69,000
      finishers worldwide in 2013. Considerable literature has documented alterations in serum
      biochemical profiles of these endurance athletes, with consistent evidence of elevated serum
      creatinine (Cr) levels in healthy race finishers as well as those seeking medical care.
      While acute renal failure in ultramarathon runners is a rare occurrence, acute kidney injury
      is common, ranging from 34% in a single-stage ultramarathon to 55-80% in multi-stage
      ultramarathons. The evidence is equivocal regarding NSAID ingestion and AKI. One study
      showed that runners who ingested NSAIDs prior to marathons had greater post-race creatinine
      levels than matched controls as well as higher rates of hospitalization and acute renal
      failure. However, this contrasts with several other studies that showed a marked lack of
      difference in creatinine levels or development of acute kidney injury between NSAID users
      and non-users during ultramarathons. The only randomized trial to date on this subject found
      no difference in serum creatinine levels between the NSAID and placebo groups at
      ultramarathon race end, however conclusions were limited by a small unpowered sample size.

      Exercise associated hyponatremia (EAH), defined as a serum sodium concentration below
      135mEq/L, is recognized as a relatively common issue in endurance running events. The
      incidence of EAH varies depending upon the distance of the race, with reported values of
      3-28% for marathons, 23 - 38% for triathlons and 4-51% in single-stage ultramarathons. EAH
      is likely under-diagnosed as athletes are often asymptomatic. While EAH most often manifests
      as non-specific symptoms such as nausea, vomiting, dizziness, and fatigue, it can be a
      potentially fatal disease that can progress to encephalopathy, seizures, pulmonary edema,
      and death. There have been no large prospective studies examining the relationship between
      EAH and NSAID ingestion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be conducted during the fifth stage of a 6-stage ultramarathon foot race
      that covers a total of 250 kilometers. Data will be collected during four separate events
      over the course of the coming year. All races are run by the RacingThePlanet™ 4-desert race
      series with locations including: Jordan, Ecuador, China, and Chile. The evening after stage
      4, participants will be reminded to check in at the medical tent prior to stage 5 start, and
      at that time the participants will be weighed and given their study drug packet (ibuprofen
      or visually identical placebo). Approximately 80% of the finishers complete the 80-kilometer
      Stage 5 in less than 19 hours, so the majority of participants will ingest 1600mg of
      ibuprofen (400mg q 4 hours x 4 doses). The optimal adult dosing for analgesia is 400mg every
      4 hours, with a maximum daily dose of 3200mg ((1999). Product information: Motrin™,
      ibuprofen. Kalamazoo, MI, Pharmacia &amp; Upjohn Company.)

      Immediately after crossing the finish line of Stage 5, participants will be reweighed, then
      seated in the study tent where a fingertip blood sample will be obtained via lancet and
      capillary collection tube (Mock, Morrison, &amp; Yatscoff, 1995) then analyzed for Na, Cr and
      BUN (utilizing a Chem-8 cartridge) onsite immediately after collection using an iSTAT®
      point-of- care analyzer (Abbott; East Windsor, NJ). Any participant who did not complete any
      stage prior to stage 5 will be removed from the competition and the study. Both the
      point-of-care device and the digital scale will be calibrated for prior to taking
      measurements. At this point, the study is over and there is no further participant
      responsibilities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Investigator)</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute Kidney Injury</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed through the duration of a 50 mile ultramaraton, an expeced average of 18 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The incidence of acute kidney injury (by RIFLE criteria to qualify extent of injury) will be estimated from measured point-of-care blood test of the finish line of a 50 mile ultramarathon.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Exertion</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed through the duration of a 50 mile ultramaraton, an expeced average of 18 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>A BORG score of perceived exertion will be measured at the finish line of a 50 mile ultramarathon to measure what affect ibuprofen had on perceived exertion as analgesia may have made the endurance event perceived as less exertional.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise-Associated Hyponatremia</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed through the duration of a 50 mile ultramaraton, an expeced average of 18 hours</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The incidence of exercise-associated hyponatremia (defined as &lt; 135 mEq) will be estimated from measured point-of-care blood test of the finish line of a 50 mile ultramarathon.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Kidney Injury</condition>
  <condition>Exercise-associated Hyponatremia</condition>
  <condition>Perceived Exertion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>tasteless and inert tablets</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ibuprofen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each tablet containing 400mg of ibuprofen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibuprofen</intervention_name>
    <description>Ibuprofen</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ibuprofen</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>motrin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Tasteless and inert visually identical (to ibuprofen) pills</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sugar pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any participant in a RacingThePlanet sanctioned event who understands the consent
             form in English.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergic to any form of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory

          -  Taken a NSAID or steroid in prior 12 hours

          -  1 kidney

          -  Known to be pregnant or suspected to be pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Grant S Lipman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Grant S Lipman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>415-290-9286</phone>
    <email>grantlip@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kate Shea, MD</last_name>
    <phone>415-516-7896</phone>
    <email>anderson.kate@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94034</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Grant S Lipman, MD</last_name>
      <phone>415-290-9286</phone>
      <email>grantlip@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Grant S Lipman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 12, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 9, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Grant S Lipman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ultramarathon</keyword>
  <keyword>ibuprofen</keyword>
  <keyword>acute kidney injury</keyword>
  <keyword>exercise-associated hyponatremia</keyword>
  <keyword>exertion</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Kidney Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyponatremia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Inflammatory Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ibuprofen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
