<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="295">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02224560</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GWEP1414</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-002940-42</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02224560</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Cannabidiol (GWP42003-P; CBD) as Adjunctive Treatment for Seizures Associated With Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome in Children and Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Study to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Cannabidiol (GWP42003-P; CBD) as Adjunctive Treatment for Seizures Associated With Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome in Children and Adults.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GW Research Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GW Research Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate the potential antiepileptic effects of cannabidiol (GWP42003-P) in subjects
      with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a 1:1:1 randomized, double-blind, 14-week comparison of two Dose Levels of
      GWP42003-P versus placebo. The treatment period will consist of a two-week titration period
      followed by a 12-week maintenance period. The study will aim to determine the efficacy,
      safety and tolerability GWP42003-P compared with placebo. The High Dose Level will be as
      recommended by the Data Safety Monitoring Committee (DSMC) after assessment of safety and
      pharmacokinetic data from Part A of study GWEP1332. The Low Dose Level will be defined as
      50% of the High Dose Level. The first subject will not enroll into this study until the DSMC
      has reviewed the safety data from Part A of study GWEP1332.

      Following study completion, all subjects will be invited to continue to receive GWP42003-P
      in an open label extension (OLE) study (under a separate protocol).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percentage change from baseline in number of drop seizures (average per week) during the maintenance period.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the mean percentage change from baseline in number of drop seizures (average per week) during the maintenance period (Day 15 to the end of the evaluable period) in subjects taking GWP42003-P compared with placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percentage change from baseline in number of drop seizures (average per week) during the Weeks 1-4, 5-8 and 9-12 of the maintenance period.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects considered treatment responders, defined as those with a ≥25%, ≥50%, ≥75%, or 100% reduction in drop seizures from baseline. Summaries will be presented overall and four-weekly.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects experiencing a &gt;25% worsening, −25 to +25% no change, 25-50% improvement, 50-75% improvement or &gt;75% improvement in drop seizures from baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percentage change from baseline in number of non-drop seizures (average per week).</measure>
    <time_frame>2-14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean percentage change from baseline in the frequencies of sub-types of seizures (average per week).</measure>
    <time_frame>2-14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from baseline in Quality of Life.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline in the Caregiver Global Impression of Change (CGIC) score.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-14 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of adverse events as measure of subject safety.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -28 to Day 137</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of age-appropriate subjects with a treatment-emergent flag using the Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS or C-SSRS Children's depending on age) during the course of the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -28 to Day 137</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <condition>Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose Level GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GWP42003-P oral solution (100 mg/mL cannabidiol in sesame oil with anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener [sucralose] and strawberry flavoring).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose Level GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>GWP42003-P oral solution (100 mg/mL cannabidiol in sesame oil with anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener [sucralose] and strawberry flavoring).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo oral solution containing the excipients sesame oil and anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener (sucralose) and strawberry flavoring.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GWP42003-P</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose Level GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose Level GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cannabidiol</other_name>
    <other_name>CBD</other_name>
    <other_name>Epidiolex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo control</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject must be male or female aged between two and 55 years (inclusive).

          -  Subject must have a documented history of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. This includes
             written documentation of having met electroencephalogram (EEG) diagnostic criteria
             during the patient's history and evidence of at least one type of generalized
             seizure, including drop seizures (atonic, tonic, tonic-clonic or myoclonic) for at
             least six months.

          -  Subjects who have a history of slow (&lt;2.5 Hz) spike-and-wave pattern in an EEG prior
             to the enrollment into the baseline period.

          -  Subjects should be refractory; that is having documented failures on more than one
             antiepileptic drug (AED).

          -  Subject must be taking one or more AEDs at a dose which has been stable for at least
             four weeks prior to screening.

          -  All medications or interventions for epilepsy (including ketogenic diet and vagus
             nerve stimulation [VNS]) must have been stable for four weeks prior to screening and
             patient is willing to maintain a stable regimen throughout the study. The ketogenic
             diet and VNS treatments are not accounted as an AED.

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Etiology of subject's seizures is a progressive neurologic disease. Subjects with
             tuberous sclerosis will not be excluded from study participation, unless there is a
             progressive tumor.

          -  Subject has had an anoxic episode requiring resuscitation within six months of
             screening.

          -  Subject has clinically significant unstable medical conditions other than epilepsy.

          -  Subject has had clinically relevant symptoms or a clinically significant illness in
             the four weeks prior to screening or randomization, other than epilepsy.

          -  Subject is currently using or has in the past used recreational or medicinal
             cannabis, or synthetic cannabinoid based medications (including Sativex®) within the
             three months prior to study entry and is unwilling to abstain for the duration of the
             study.

          -  Subject has any known or suspected hypersensitivity to cannabinoids or any of the
             excipients of the Investigational Medicinal Product (IMP), such as sesame oil.

          -  Subject has been part of a clinical trial involving another IMP in the previous six
             months.

          -  Subject has significantly impaired hepatic function at screening (Visit 1) or
             randomization (Visit 2) (Alanine aminotransferase [ALT] &gt;5 x upper limit of normal
             [ULN] or total bilirubin [TBL] &gt;2 x ULN) OR the ALT or Aspartate aminotransferase
             (AST) &gt;3 x ULN and (TBL &gt;2 x ULN or international normalized ratio &gt;1.5). This
             criterion can only be confirmed once the laboratory results are available; subjects
             randomized into the study who are later found not to meet this criterion should be
             withdrawn from the study.

          -  Any history of suicidal behavior or any suicidal ideation of type four or five on the
             Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale in the last month or at screening.

          -  Subject is taking more than four concurrent AEDs.

          -  Subject has taken corticotropins in the six months prior to screening.

          -  Subject is currently taking long-term systemic steroids (excluding inhaled medication
             for asthma treatment) or any other daily medication known to exacerbate epilepsy. An
             exception will be made of prophylactic medication, for example, idiopathic nephrotic
             syndrome or asthma.

          -  Subject is taking felbamate, and they have been taking it for less than one year
             prior to screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>GW Research Medical Information</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0) 1223 266800</phone>
    <email>medicalinformation@gwpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GW Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>GW Research Medical Information</last_name>
      <email>medicalinformation@gwpharm.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 19, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 21, 2014</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cannabidiol</keyword>
  <keyword>CBD</keyword>
  <keyword>Epidiolex</keyword>
  <keyword>GWP42003-P</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
