<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="841">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00918047</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>804P107</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00918047</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics, Safety, and Tolerability of Oxcarbazepine Extended Release (OXC XR) as Adjunctive Therapy in Pediatric Subjects With Refractory Partial Epilepsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multiple Dose, Open-Label, Multi-Center Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics, Safety, and Tolerability of OXC XR as Adjunctive Therapy in Pediatric Subjects With Refractory Partial Epilepsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Supernus Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Supernus Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study to evaluate the pharmacokinetics, safety, and tolerability of OXC XR as adjunctive
      therapy in pediatric subjects with refractory partial epilepsy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Non-Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the steady-state pharmacokinetics (PK) of OXC XR and to assess the safety and tolerability of repeated oral dosing of OXC XR in pediatric subjects with partial seizures.</measure>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oxcarbazepine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Open Label Study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxcarbazepine</intervention_name>
    <description>Open Label study</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oxcarbazepine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NAP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Able to provide written informed assent (IAF), as appropriate, with written informed
             permission (and informed consent (ICF) where required by regional laws or
             regulations) from the parent or legally-authorized representative (LAR).

          2. Male or female aged 4 to 17 years, inclusive, with a current diagnosis of partial
             onset seizures with or without secondarily generalized seizures as confirmed by the
             1981 and 1989 International League Against Epilepsy Classifications).

          3. Currently receiving treatment with at least one and up to two AEDs, excluding
             oxcarbazepine and phenytoin. AED therapy must have been initiated more than one month
             prior to Visit 1 and doses must be stable for at least two weeks prior to Visit 1. A
             vagal nerve stimulator implanted for at least six months and with parameters
             unchanged for at least one month prior to Visit 1 is allowed and not considered to be
             an AED. Magnet use is allowed.

          4. No diagnosis of a progressive neurological disorder based on previous imaging.

          5. Weight within the 25 - 75 % weight-for-age percentiles based on the National Center
             for Health Statistics Growth Charts, and not less than 15.0kg.

          6. Able and willing to swallow whole tablets.

          7. Females of childbearing potential (FOCP) should either be sexually inactive
             (abstinent) for 14 days prior to the first dose, throughout the study and for four
             days following the last dose or, if sexually active, will be using one of the
             following acceptable birth control methods:

               1. Surgically sterile (bilateral tubal ligation, hysterectomy, bilateral
                  oophorectomy) six months minimum;

               2. Intrauterine device in place for at least three months;

               3. Barrier methods (condom, diaphragm) with spermicide for at least 14 days prior
                  to the first dose, throughout the study and for four days following the last
                  dose;

               4. Surgical sterilization of the partner (vasectomy for six months minimum);

               5. Hormonal contraceptives in addition to a barrier method (condom, diaphragm) with
                  spermicide for at least 14 days prior to the first dose, throughout the study
                  and for four days following the last dose.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. A documented history of status epilepticus in the past year.

          2. Seizures secondary to illicit drug or alcohol use, infection, neoplasia,
             demyelinating disease, degenerative neurological disease, or central nervous system
             disease deemed progressive, metabolic illness, or progressive degenerative disease.

          3. Diagnosis or an electroencephalogram consistent with a diagnosis of seizure disorders
             other than partial epilepsy.

          4. Meets criteria for history of major depressive or manic episode, according to
             Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition Text Revision.

          5. Any history of suicide intent and/or attempt.

          6. History or presence of clinically significant, chronic medical condition, especially
             those contraindicating antiseizure medication, (e.g., any neurological,
             gastrointestinal, endocrine, cardiovascular, pulmonary, hematological, immunologic,
             renal, hepatic or metabolic disease) that may affect the safety of the subject in the
             opinion of the Investigator.

          7. Use of oxcarbazepine or phenytoin within 10 days prior to first dose of SM.

          8. Use of felbamate with less than 18 months of continuous exposure prior to screening.

          9. Frequent need of rescue benzodiazepines (more than once in a 28 day period).

         10. Use of diuretics or other sodium-lowering medications within seven days prior to
             first dose of SM.

         11. History or presence of clinically significant laboratory, electrocardiogram (ECG), or
             vital sign abnormalities at screening that may affect the safety of the subject, in
             the opinion of the Investigator.

         12. Presence of potential hepatic function impairment as shown by, but not limited to,
             alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 3 times the
             upper limit of normal (ULN), or total bilirubin &gt;1.5 times ULN.

         13. Presence of suspected impairment of renal function defined by serum creatinine ≥1.5
             times ULN.

         14. History of substance abuse or dependence.

         15. Females who are pregnant or lactating.

         16. Previous known hypersensitivity to OXC or other related drugs, such as carbamazepine.

         17. Use of an investigational drug or device or participation in an investigational study
             within 30 days prior to the first dose of SM.

         18. Any reason which, in the opinion of the Investigator, would prevent the subject from
             participating in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 06</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 03</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loxahatchee</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Palm Beach</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 10</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 02</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockville</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 08</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lake Success</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 05</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 01</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingsport</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 07</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 10, 2013</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>June 9, 2009</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsies, Partial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Oxcarbazepine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
