<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1066">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00245037</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000447204</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016058</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>OHSU-HEM-05011-L</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>OHSU-210</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00245037</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Busulfan, Fludarabine, and Total-Body Irradiation in Treating Patients Who Are Undergoing a Donor Stem Cell Transplant for Hematologic Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>Bu Flu TBI</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Non-Myeloablative Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant for the Treatment of Patients With Hematologic Malignancies Using Busulfan, Fludarabine and Total Body Irradiation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Giving low doses of chemotherapy, such as fludarabine and busulfan, before a
      donor peripheral blood stem cell transplant helps stop the growth of cancer cells. It also
      stops the patient's immune system from rejecting the donor's stem cells. The donated stem
      cells may replace the patient's immune system and help destroy any remaining cancer cells
      (graft-versus-tumor effect). Giving an infusion of the donor's T cells (donor lymphocyte
      infusion) after the transplant may help increase this effect. Sometimes the transplanted
      cells from a donor can also make an immune response against the body's normal cells. Giving
      cyclosporine and mycophenolate mofetil after the transplant may stop this from happening.

      PURPOSE: This phase I/II trial is studying the side effects of giving busulfan and
      fludarabine together with total-body irradiation and to see how well they work in treating
      patients who are undergoing a donor stem cell transplant for hematologic cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  To assess safety and toxicity of the addition of busulfan added to an established
           fludarabine and low-dose total-body irradiation (TBI) conditioning regimen for
           non-myeloablative allogeneic transplantation in patients with hematologic malignancies.
           (Phase I)

        -  To assess the non-relapse mortality 1-year after conditioning with busulfan and
           fludarabine/TBI in patients with hematologic malignancies at moderate to high risk for
           graft rejection and/or relapse of underlying disease. (Phase II)

      Secondary

        -  To assess overall survival 1-year survival. (Phase II)

        -  To assess the incidence of graft rejection. (Phase II)

        -  To assess the incidence of grade II-IV acute graft-vs-host disease (GVHD) and chronic
           extensive GVHD. (Phase II)

        -  To assess rates of disease progression and/or relapse-related mortality. (Phase II)

        -  To determine non-hematologic grade III-IV organ specific toxicity. (Phase II)

      OUTLINE:

        -  Nonmyeloablative-conditioning regimen: Patients receive busulfan IV on day -5 and
           fludarabine IV over 30 minutes on days -4 to -2. Patients undergo total body
           irradiation on day 0.

        -  Allogeneic peripheral blood stem cell transplantation (PBSC): Patients undergo donor
           PBSC infusion on day 0.

        -  Graft-versus-host disease prophylaxis: Patients receive oral cyclosporine twice daily
           on days -3 to 56 followed by a taper to day 180. Patients with a related stem cell
           donor receive oral mycophenolate mofetil twice daily on days 0-28. Patients with an
           unrelated stem cell donor receive oral mycophenolate mofetil 3 times daily on days 0-28
           followed by a taper twice daily to day 56. Patients with evidence of relapse or
           persistent disease may also receive up to 3 donor lymphocyte infusions.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 225 patients will be accrued for this study; 25 patients
      accrued into the Phase I and 200 patients into Phase II.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Evaluations at 6 months, 12 months, 18 months and subsequent yearly follow-up's for a total of 5 years.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-relapse mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Chimerisms and post-engraftment are followed on days 28, 56, and 84 post transplant with an evaluation at 180 days (6 months), then 1 year, 18 months, 2, 3, 4, &amp; 5 years after.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">225</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Myeloproliferative Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma and Plasma Cell Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic/Myeloproliferative Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Precancerous Condition</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Busulfan 3.2 mg/kg IV on day -5 Fludarabine 30 mg/m2/day x 3 (total dose 90 mg/m2, day -4 to day -2 TBI 200 centigray (cGy) x 1, day 0</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic allogeneic lymphocytes</intervention_name>
    <description>A population of lymphocytes therapeutically administered to a recipient individual who is genetically distinct from a donor of the same species.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>busulfan</intervention_name>
    <description>Busulfan is an alkylating chemotherapeutic agent which has been used in many high dose and reduced intensity regimens prior to allogeneic or autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplants. It is active in a wide variety of malignancies and in high-doses it is myeloablative.
IV busulfan is available and diluted and administered per package insert guidelines.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cyclosporine</intervention_name>
    <description>Cyclosporine is a cyclic polypeptide immunosuppressive agent. It blocks the calcium-dependent calcineurin-mediated nuclear localization of nuclear factor of activated T cells (NFAT) following T-cell activation, thereby inhibiting transactivation of key T-cell response genes including Interleukin 2 (IL-2) and Interleukin 4 (IL-4).
- Starting on day -3, Cyclosporine (CSP) is given at a dose of 4.0 mg/kg p.o. b.i.d.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fludarabine phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Fludarabine's active metabolite 2-fluoro-ara-A is an antimetabolite that inhibits DNA primase, DNA polymerase alpha and ribonucleotide nuclease.
Dosing: Days -4, -3 and -2: Fludarabine 30 mg/m2/day IV. Total dose equals 90 mg/m2.
Monitoring: Fludarabine level is not monitored.
Dose Adjustments: There are no provisions for fludarabine dose adjustments.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mycophenolate mofetil</intervention_name>
    <description>Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) is the morpholinyl ethyl ester of mycophenolic acid (MPA) and reversibly inhibits inosine monophosphate dehydrogenase, particularly the type II isoform that is more prominent in activated lymphocytes. As a result of the inhibition of de novo purine synthesis, proliferation of B- and T-lymphocytes is blocked and antibody production is inhibited.
Related Donors: MMF will be given daily at 15mg/kg q 12 hrs until day +28, then stop without tapering. Doses will be rounded to the nearest 250 mg (capsules are 250 mg).
Unrelated Donors: MMF will be given daily at 15mg/kg q 8 hrs until day +28, then given daily at 15mg/kg q 12 hours until day +56, then stop without tapering. Doses will be rounded to the nearest 250 mg (capsules are 250 mg).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>peripheral blood stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Bone marrow transplantation (BMT) and peripheral blood stem cell transplantation (PBSCT) are procedures that restore stem cells that have been destroyed by high doses of chemotherapy and/or radiation therapy. There are three types of transplants:
In autologous transplants, patients receive their own stem cells.
In syngeneic transplants, patients receive stem cells from their identical twin.
In allogeneic transplants, patients receive stem cells from their brother, sister, or parent. A person who is not related to the patient (an unrelated donor) also may be used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total Body Irradiation (TBI)</intervention_name>
    <description>TBI is a form of radiotherapy used primarily as part of the preparative regimen for haematopoietic stem cell (or bone marrow) transplantation. As the name implies, TBI involves irradiation of the entire body, though in modern practice the lungs are often partially shielded to lower the risk of radiation-induced lung injury.
Toxicities: At the dosage used, side effects are not expected. Nevertheless, there may be fever, alopecia, parotitis, diarrhea, reversible skin pigmentation, mucositis and late effects including cataract formation, pulmonary damage, carcinogenesis, and sterilization.
Dosing: TBI will be given in one 200 cGy fraction from linear accelerator at a rate of 15-19 cGy/min.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF)</intervention_name>
    <description>Granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF or GCSF) is a colony-stimulating factor hormone. G-CSF is also known as colony-stimulating factor 3 (CSF 3).
It is a glycoprotein, growth factor and cytokine produced by a number of different tissues to stimulate the bone marrow to produce granulocytes and stem cells. G-CSF then stimulates the bone marrow to release them into the blood.
Toxicities: At the dosage used, the most common side effect will be medullary bone pain.
Dosing: 5 mcg/kg/day given per institutional standards (on approximately days 10-15 or not at all).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phenytoin</intervention_name>
    <description>This drug is used to prevent seizures while on chemotherapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>Methotrexate is used to treat severe psoriasis (a skin disease in which red, scaly patches form on some areas of the body) that cannot be controlled by other treatments.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Busulfan (Bu), Fludarabine (Flu), Total Body Iradiation (TBI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Diagnosis of a hematologic malignancy of 1 of the following high-risk types:

               -  Acute lymphoblastic leukemia

               -  Acute myeloid leukemia

               -  Chronic myelogenous leukemia

               -  Chronic lymphocytic leukemia

               -  Myelodysplastic syndromes

               -  Myeloproliferative disorder

               -  Multiple myeloma

               -  Plasma cell dyscrasias

               -  Non-Hodgkin lymphoma

               -  Hodgkin disease

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

        Performance status

          -  Karnofsky 50-100%

        Life expectancy

          -  Not specified

        Hematopoietic

          -  Not specified

        Hepatic

          -  No liver failure

          -  No cirrhosis with evidence of portal hypertension

          -  No alcoholic hepatitis

          -  No esophageal varices

          -  No chronic hepatitis

          -  No other liver disease

        Renal

          -  Not specified

        Cardiovascular

          -  Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) &gt; 35%

          -  No symptomatic coronary artery disease or cardiac failure requiring therapy

        Pulmonary

          -  Diffusing capacity of lung for carbon monoxide (DLCO) &gt; 30%

          -  Total lung capacity &gt; 30%

          -  Forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV_1) &gt; 30%

          -  No supplementary continuous oxygen

        Other

          -  HIV negative

          -  No active nonhematologic malignancy except localized skin cancer

          -  No overt organ dysfunction

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  Not specified
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Maziarz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>OHSU Knight Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Knight Cancer Institute at Oregon Health and Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239-3098</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.gov/clinicaltrials/OHSU-HEM-05011-L</url>
    <description>Clinical trial summary from the National Cancer Institute's PDQ® database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 24, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 25, 2005</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>recurrent adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult acute myeloid leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>de novo myelodysplastic syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>previously treated myelodysplastic syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>secondary myelodysplastic syndromes</keyword>
  <keyword>atypical chronic myeloid leukemia, breakpoint cluster region-Abelson (BCR-ABL) negative</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory chronic lymphocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III chronic lymphocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV chronic lymphocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>accelerated phase chronic myelogenous leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>blastic phase chronic myelogenous leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic phase chronic myelogenous leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>relapsing chronic myelogenous leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>primary systemic amyloidosis</keyword>
  <keyword>refractory multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>myelodysplastic/myeloproliferative neoplasm, unclassifiable</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic eosinophilic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>primary myelofibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic neutrophilic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>essential thrombocythemia</keyword>
  <keyword>polycythemia vera</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic myelomonocytic leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>acute undifferentiated leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>extramedullary plasmacytoma</keyword>
  <keyword>isolated plasmacytoma of bone</keyword>
  <keyword>monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance</keyword>
  <keyword>stage I multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>secondary acute myeloid leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with 11q23 (MLL) abnormalities</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with inv(16)(p13;q22)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with t(15;17)(q22;q12)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with t(16;16)(p13;q22)</keyword>
  <keyword>adult acute myeloid leukemia with t(8;21)(q22;q22)</keyword>
  <keyword>nodal marginal zone B-cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II adult Burkitt lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II adult diffuse large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II adult diffuse mixed cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II adult diffuse small cleaved cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II adult immunoblastic large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II adult lymphoblastic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II grade 1 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II grade 2 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II grade 3 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II mantle cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II marginal zone lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>noncontiguous stage II small lymphocytic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult Burkitt lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult Hodgkin lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult diffuse large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult diffuse mixed cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult diffuse small cleaved cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult immunoblastic large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent adult lymphoblastic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent cutaneous T-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent grade 1 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent grade 2 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent grade 3 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent mantle cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent marginal zone lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent small lymphocytic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>splenic marginal zone lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III adult Burkitt lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III adult Hodgkin lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III adult diffuse large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III adult diffuse mixed cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III adult diffuse small cleaved cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III adult immunoblastic large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III adult lymphoblastic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III grade 1 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III grade 2 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III grade 3 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III mantle cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III marginal zone lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III small lymphocytic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV adult Burkitt lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV adult Hodgkin lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV adult diffuse large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV adult diffuse mixed cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV adult diffuse small cleaved cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV adult immunoblastic large cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV adult lymphoblastic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV grade 1 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV grade 2 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV grade 3 follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV mantle cell lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV marginal zone lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV small lymphocytic lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>extranodal marginal zone B-cell lymphoma of mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic-Myeloproliferative Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myeloproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Plasmacytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precancerous Conditions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Busulfan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolate mofetil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
