<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="979">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01399047</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3908</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01399047</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cellcept for Treatment of Juvenile Neuronal Ceroid Lipofuscinosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>JUMP</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II, Randomized, Placebo Controlled Trial of the Safety and Tolerability of Mycophenolate in Children With Juvenile Neuronal Ceroid Lipofuscinosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Rochester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Batten Disease Support and Research Assocation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Rochester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this trial is to establish the safety and tolerability of
      short-term (8 weeks) administration of mycophenolate mofetil in ambulatory children with
      JNCL. The secondary objective is to gather preliminary evidence of the short-term (8 week)
      impact of mycophenolate mofetil on clinically relevant features of JNCL as measured by the
      Unified Batten Disease Rating Scale (UBDRS), including motor features, seizures, behavior,
      cognitive and functional measures.

      Funding source-FDA Office of Orphan Product Development (OOPD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Juvenile Neuronal Ceroid Lipofuscinosis (JNCL) is a fatal disorder. Currently treatment is
      symptomatic. Thus, there is a real need to intervene and slow the progression of this
      disease. Preliminary data on genetic knock-down of the ability to mount an immune response
      in cln3-knockout mice is supportive of a strategy for treating JNCL with an
      immuno-suppressive agent. Many drugs with the ability to suppress the immune system are
      steroidal and deemed unsuitable for long-term administration to children. Mycophenolate
      mofetil (CellCept) is used as an immunosuppressive agent in allogenic transplants in
      pediatric patients and is therefore approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for
      pediatric use.

      The study design is a double-blind, randomized, 22-week cross-over study of mycophenolate
      mofetil vs. placebo. After a 4-week washout period, subjects will undergo blinded crossover
      from active study drug to placebo or from placebo to active study drug.

      Subjects and caregivers will be evaluated in person in the University of Rochester Batten
      Center (URBC) at screening/baseline, and at weeks 8, 12, and 20. In addition, subjects will
      be evaluated by their local clinician who is a formalized member of the research team. Such
      contacts will occur at Weeks 2, 4, 14, 16, and any unscheduled or early termination visits.
      There will also be regular telephone contact between the URBC and the local clinician.

      We have selected the dosage currently FDA approved for use in children being treated for
      prophylaxis of renal transplant rejection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Crossover Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability as shown by number of subjects with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Establish the safety and tolerability of short-term (8 weeks) administration of mycophenolate mofetil in ambulatory children with JNCL</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary evidence of efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To gather preliminary evidence of the short-term (8 week) impact of mycophenolate mofetil on clinically relevant features of JNCL as measured by the UBDRS, including motor features, seizures, behavior, cognitive and functional measures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of clinical trials in rare disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>To pilot the feasibility of conducting controlled clinical trials of this rare neurological disorder base on collaboration between a national center of excellence in the disease (URBC), and children's local care-providers (pediatricians and/or local neurologists.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Juvenile Neuronal Ceroid Lipofuscinosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mycophenolate Mofetil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo liquid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycophenolate mofetil</intervention_name>
    <description>The liquid dosage will be individualized, contingent upon the subject's weight. Subjects will receive 50% of the target dose (300mg/m2/dose BID) during Week 0-Week 2, then increase to the full dose (600mg/m2/dose BID) in Week 3, continuing at this dose through Week 8. Additionally, due to the risk of gastrointestinal disturbance (hemorrhage, ulcer), children will also receive prophylactic Prilosec (Omeprazole) for the duration of the study, during both the mycophenolate and placebo arms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mycophenolate Mofetil</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cellcept</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liquid Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>The dosage will be individualized, contingent upon the subject's weight. Subjects will receive 50% of the target dose (300mg/m2/dose BID) during Week 0-Week 2, then increase to the full dose (600mg/m2/dose BID) in Week 3, continuing at this dose through Week 8. Additionally, due to the risk of gastrointestinal disturbance (hemorrhage, ulcer), children will also receive prophylactic Prilosec (omeprazole) for the duration of the study, during both the mycophenolate and placebo arms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo liquid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  JNCL as determined by a characteristic clinical presentation and confirmatory genetic
             evidence.

          -  Able to walk 10 feet without assistance beyond that required due to vision
             impairment.

          -  Subjects with local treating clinician (pediatrician or neurologist) willing to
             conduct the trial according to the protocol, good clinical practice, and applicable
             regulations.

          -  Subjects with a parent/legal guardian willing to accompany them to all study visits,
             oversee study drug compliance, and monitor and report to local treating
             clinician/investigator and the URBC investigative personnel any signs of adversity.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to tolerate oral administration of medications

          -  Concomitant medical condition, which, in the opinion of the local treating clinician,
             the parent(s)/guardian, or the URBC study investigator would place the child at
             greater than acceptable risk from: 1) travel by plane or car to the URBC on four
             occasions over the course of 22 weeks, 2) exposure to mycophenolate mofetil at
             protocol defined dosages for periods up to 8 weeks.

          -  Anticipated inability of the child (on the part of the investigator, parent/guardian,
             or URBC study personnel) to comply with the rigors of the protocol..

          -  Use of disallowed concomitant medications.

          -  Administration of immunosuppressive medications

          -  History of any prior exposure to mycophenolate mofetil

          -  History of hypersensitivity to mycophenolate mofetil, or any other component of the
             product

          -  History of frank gastrointestinal hemorrhage, ulceration, or melena

          -  White blood cell count &lt; 3000/μL, absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1500/μL,
             hemoglobin &lt; 10g/dL, or thrombocytopenia &lt;100,000/μL.

          -  Abnormal liver function (aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase
             (ALT) or bilirubin greater than 3 times the upper limit of normal)

          -  Pregnancy or vulnerability to engage in sexual intercourse based on report of the
             parent/guardian, judgment of the local treating clinician/investigator or judgment of
             the URBC study personnel.

          -  Positive Tuberculosis test

          -  Immunizations not up to date for age according to Centers for Disease Control
             guidelines
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Erika F Augustine, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Rochester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>August 14, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>July 5, 2011</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Rochester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Erika Augustine</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PI</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Batten Disease</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Neuronal Ceroid-Lipofuscinoses</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolate mofetil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
