<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="574">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02332655</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00029264</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02332655</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cannabidiol Expanded Access Study in Medically Refractory Sturge-Weber Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cannabidiol Expanded Access Study in Medically Refractory Sturge-Weber Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Anne Comi, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GW Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Faneca 66 Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hugo W. Moser Research Institute at Kennedy Krieger, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the tolerability and optimal dose of cannabidiol
      (CBD) as an simultaneous treatment in children and young adults with Sturge-Weber syndrome
      (SWS) and drug resistant epilepsy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We hope to gain an understanding of the utility of pure CBD used for the treatment of
      medically refractory epilepsy in SWS in this open-label, safety dose-finding, study. Recent
      evidence suggests that CBD has multiple, beneficial, effects in patients (such as those with
      SWS that undergo neurological deterioration) suffering from medically refractory seizures.
      We hypothesize that CBD will reduce seizure frequency in children and young adults with SWS
      and will therefore help stabilize and improve their neurologic status.This trial is part of
      an expanded access program, available through a partnership with GW Pharmaceutical, which
      has been sanctioned by the FDA to study the safety and efficacy of Epidiolex
      (cannabidiol/CBD) in participants with SWS and medically refractory seizures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in seizure frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in average seizure duration by seizure type</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the number of episodes of status epilepticus, defined as convulsive seizure lasting longer than 10 minutes</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the number of uses of rescue medication</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the number of ER visits/ hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Sturge-Weber Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cannabidiol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects will receive the experimental Epidiolex (cannabidiol) oral solution to be taken at home twice a day, and will be treated on an outpatient basis. The drug will be taken for 48 weeks unless the subject chooses to participate in the extension phase of the study, in which case the subject will continue to receive the drug for one additional year or until the drug is approved for clinical use for the treatment of epilepsy in patients with Sturge-Weber syndrome.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cannabidiol</intervention_name>
    <description>Initiation of treatment will begin with 2mg/kg/day. The dose will be increased by 3 mg/kg/day after seven days and then by 5 mg/kg/day every seven days up to a maximum dose of 25 mg/kg/day given.
The dose of concomitant antiepileptic drugs will remain unchanged during the first 12 weeks of CBD treatment (or until 8 weeks after steady state at final dose), unless symptoms of toxicity and/or significant changes in blood levels are observed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cannabidiol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Epidiolex</other_name>
    <other_name>CBD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documentation of a diagnosis of drug resistant epilepsy as evidenced by failure to
             control seizures despite appropriate trial of two or more anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs)
             at therapeutic doses. Drug resistant epilepsy for this study is defined as: At least
             6 reported quantifiable (no cluster or innumerable seizures) seizures (defined
             seizures with motor signs) with no continuous 21-day seizure-free period between
             Visit 1 (Screening Visit) and Visit 2 (Randomization visit), as per data captured in
             daily seizure diaries. These can be focal seizures, focal seizures with impaired
             consciousness, myoclonic seizures, generalized, and secondarily generalized seizures.

          -  Between 1-5 baseline anti-epileptic drugs at stable doses for a minimum of 4 weeks
             prior to enrollment. Vagus nerve stimulator (VNS), ketogenic diet and modified Atkins
             diet do not count toward this limit.

          -  VNS must be on stable settings for a minimum of 3 months prior to enrollment.

          -  If on ketogenic or Atkins diet, must be on stable ratio for a minimum of 3 months
             prior to enrollment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with seizures secondary to metabolic, toxic, infectious or psychogenic
             disorder or drug abuse or current seizures related to an acute medical illness.

          -  Presence of only non-motor partial seizures (without limb or facial movements, eye
             deviation or head turning)

          -  Patients who require rescue medication during the Baseline phase for more than 6
             days.

          -  Patients with any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions at randomization such
             as:

               1. liver disease such as cirrhosis, decompensated liver disease, and chronic
                  hepatitis [i.e. quantifiable hepatitis B virus (HBV)-DNA and/or positive HbsAg,
                  quantifiable hepatitis C virus (HCV)-RNA]

               2. Uncontrolled diabetes as defined by fasting serum glucose &gt; 1.5

               3. Active (acute or chronic) or uncontrolled severe infections.

               4. Patients with an active, bleeding diathesis.

          -  Patients who have had a major surgery or significant traumatic injury within 4 weeks
             of study entry. Patients who have not recovered from the side effects of any major
             surgery (defined as requiring general anesthesia), or patients that may require major
             surgery during the course of the study.

          -  Patients who change the dose of the AEDs during 4 weeks before screening or during
             the baseline period.

          -  Prior treatment with any investigational drug within the preceding 4 weeks prior to
             study entry.

          -  Patients with a history of non-compliance to medical regimens or who are considered
             potentially unreliable or will not be able to complete the entire study. Those in
             foster care, unable to keep follow-up appointments, maintain close contact with
             Principal Investigator, or complete all necessary studies to maintain safety.

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women, where pregnancy is defined as the state of a
             female after conception and until the termination of gestation, confirmed by a
             positive human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) laboratory test.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Month</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anne Comi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hugo W. Moser Research Institute at Kennedy Krieger, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Emma H Kaplan, BA</last_name>
    <phone>443-923-9569</phone>
    <email>kaplan@kennedykrieger.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kennedy Krieger Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emma H Kaplan, BA</last_name>
      <phone>443-923-9569</phone>
      <email>kaplan@kennedykrieger.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anne Comi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.kennedykrieger.org/patient-care/patient-care-centers/sturge-weber-center</url>
    <description>Hunter Nelson Sturge-Weber Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>January 5, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 5, 2015</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hugo W. Moser Research Institute at Kennedy Krieger, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anne Comi, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Director Sturge-Weber Center, Kennedy Krieger Institute,Associate Professor Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sturge-Weber syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>SWS</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug resistant epilepsy</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>Yes</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Stem Infarctions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sturge-Weber Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
