<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="1025">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01859013</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1304M31241</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01859013</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Topiramate in Adolescents With Severe Obesity</brief_title>
  <official_title>BMI Reduction With Meal Replacements + Topiramate in Adolescents With Severe Obesity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The prevalence of severe pediatric obesity is on the rise and youth with this condition are
      at elevated risk for developing chronic diseases such as cardiovascular disease (CVD) and
      type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). Topiramate, a medication approved by the Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA) for the treatment of seizures in adults and children, is associated
      with weight loss. Although not FDA approved for the treatment of obesity, studies in obese
      adults have demonstrated weight reduction of approximately 5% with 6-12 months of therapy.
      However, the weight loss effect of topiramate has never been evaluated among children and
      adolescents. Therefore, the goal of this pilot study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy
      of 24 weeks of topiramate therapy with a 4-week run-in of meal replacement therapy in
      adolescents with severe obesity. The primary hypothesis is that 4 weeks of meal replacement
      therapy followed by 24 weeks of topiramate will have a larger average percent decline in BMI
      between baseline and 28 weeks compared to meal replacement therapy followed by placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The prevalence of severe pediatric obesity is on the rise and youth with this condition are
      at elevated risk for developing chronic diseases such as cardiovascular disease (CVD) and
      type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). Lifestyle modification therapy alone is ineffective for
      most adolescents with severe obesity and few patients qualify for bariatric surgery. Many
      patients would likely benefit from pharmacotherapy but only one medication (orlistat) is
      approved for use in adolescents but notable side effects and limited efficacy impede its
      clinical use. Topiramate, a medication approved by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA)
      for the treatment of seizures in adults and children, is associated with weight loss.
      Although not FDA approved for the treatment of obesity, studies in obese adults have
      demonstrated weight reduction of approximately 5% with 6-12 months of therapy. However, the
      weight loss effect of topiramate has never been evaluated among children and adolescents.
      Therefore, the goal of this pilot study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of 24 weeks
      of topiramate therapy with a 4-week run-in of meal replacement therapy in adolescents with
      severe obesity.

      This will be a 28-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, pilot clinical trial
      of meal replacement therapy (4 weeks) followed by topiramate (24 weeks) vs. meal replacement
      therapy (4 weeks) followed by placebo (24 weeks) for BMI reduction and cardiometabolic risk
      factor improvement in 36 adolescents (ages 12-17 years old) with severe obesity. Monthly
      lifestyle modification/behavioral counseling will be delivered by trained study coordinators
      to patients in both groups. The lifestyle modification education materials will be given to
      patients and selected sections will be discussed at each monthly contact (five face-to-face
      sessions and three phone sessions).

      The primary object is to evaluate the effect of meal replacement therapy followed by
      topiramate vs. meal replacement therapy followed by placebo on percent change in BMI among
      adolescents with severe obesity. The primary hypothesis is that 4 weeks of meal replacement
      therapy followed by 24 weeks of topiramate will have a larger average percent decline in BMI
      between baseline and 28 weeks compared to meal replacement therapy followed by placebo.

      The secondary objective is to characterize the safety profile of topiramate for the
      treatment of adolescent obesity, evaluate the effects of meal replacement therapy followed
      by topiramate vs. meal replacement therapy followed by placebo on risk factors for CVD and
      T2DM, and evaluate response to topiramate treatment based on baseline eating behavior
      phenotype in adolescents with severe obesity. The secondary hypothesis is that 4 weeks of
      meal replacement therapy followed by 24 weeks of topiramate will significantly reduce
      average absolute BMI, absolute and percent body weight, percent total body and visceral fat,
      systolic blood pressure, fasting triglycerides and insulin, compared to meal replacement
      therapy followed by placebo, and that the presence of binge eating disorder characteristics
      at baseline will be associated with greater reduction in BMI with topiramate treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent Change from Baseline in Body Mass Index at 28-Weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 28-Weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Percent Change from Baseline in Body Mass Index at 28-Weeks</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity, Morbid</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Weight Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Topiramate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Four (4) weeks of meal replacement therapy, followed by 28-weeks of topiramate therapy. Topiramate will be initiated at a dose of 25 mg (taken orally once daily in the evening), escalated to 50 mg (taken orally once daily in the evening) after 1 week, and escalated to 75 mg (taken orally 25 mg in the morning and 50 mg in the evening) after 2 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Four (4) weeks of meal replacement therapy, followed by 28-weeks of placebo (sugar pill) therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Topiramate</intervention_name>
    <description>Topiramate will be initiated at a dose of 25 mg (taken orally once daily in the evening), escalated to 50 mg (taken orally once daily in the evening) after 1 week, and escalated to 75 mg (taken orally 25 mg in the morning and 50 mg in the evening) after 2 weeks. Patients who do not tolerate dose escalation will be reduced to the highest tolerated dose for the remainder of the trial.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Topiramate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Topamax</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will be taken orally once daily in the evening for the first two weeks, and orally twice daily (AM and PM) for the remainder of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar Pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI ≥1.2 times the 95th percentile (based on gender and age) or BMI ≥35 kg/m2

          -  12-18 years old

          -  Tanner stage IV or V by physical exam

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Tanner stage I, II, or III

          -  Type 1 or 2 diabetes mellitus

          -  Previous (within 6-months) or current use of weight loss medication (patients may
             undergo washout)

          -  Previous (within 6-months) or current use of drugs associated with weight gain (e.g.
             steroids/anti-psychotics)

          -  Previous bariatric surgery

          -  Recent initiation (within 3-months) of anti-hypertensive or lipid medication

          -  Previous (within 6-months) or current use of medication to treat insulin resistance
             or hyperglycemia (patients may undergo washout)

          -  Major psychiatric disorder

          -  Females: Pregnant, planning to become pregnant, or unwilling to use 2 or more
             acceptable methods of contraception when engaging in sexual activity throughout the
             study

          -  Tobacco use

          -  Liver/renal dysfunction

               -  ALT or AST &gt;2.5 times the upper limit of normal

               -  Bicarbonate &lt;18 mmol/L

               -  Creatinine &gt;1.2 mg/dL

          -  Glaucoma

          -  Obesity associated with genetic disorder (monogenetic obesity)

          -  Hyperthyroidism or uncontrolled hypothyroidism

          -  History of suicidal thought/attempts

          -  History of kidney stones

          -  History of cholelithiasis

          -  Current use of other carbonic anhydrase inhibitor
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aaron S Kelly, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cameron E Naughton, MPA</last_name>
    <phone>612-625-3623</phone>
    <email>naug0009@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ann E Sheldon, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>612-624-3137</phone>
    <email>shel0230@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cameron E Naughton, MPA</last_name>
      <phone>612-625-3623</phone>
      <email>naug0009@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ann E Sheldon, B.S.</last_name>
      <phone>612-624-3137</phone>
      <email>shel0230@umn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aaron S Kelly, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>May 26, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>May 9, 2013</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity, Morbid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Topiramate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
