<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="918">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on December 01, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02607891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GWEP1447 Blinded Phase</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-002939-18</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02607891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial to Investigate Possible Drug-drug Interactions Between Stiripentol or Valproate and Cannabidiol in Patients With Epilepsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Double-blind, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Pharmacokinetic Trial in 2 Parallel Groups to Investigate Possible Drug-drug Interactions Between Stiripentol or Valproate and GWP42003-P in Patients With Epilepsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GW Research Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GW Research Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>Spain: Agencia Española de Medicamentos y Productos Sanitarios</authority>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>Sweden: Medical Products Agency</authority>
    <authority>Netherlands: Medicines Evaluation Board (MEB)</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial consists of 2 parts: a double-blinded phase and an open-label extension phase.
      The blinded phase only will be described in this record. Participants will be randomized in
      a 4:1 ratio to receive GWP42003-P or matching placebo. The hypothesis is that levels of
      stiripentol (STP) or valproate (VPA) may be altered (increased or decreased) as a result of
      using GWP42003-P.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Pharmacokinetics Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax) of STP, VPA, cannabidiol (CBD), and CBD major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Cmax of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to the maximum plasma concentration (Tmax) of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Tmax of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the curve (AUC) from zero to the final time of positive detection (0-t) of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The AUC(0-t) of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC from zero to infinity with extrapolation of the terminal phase (0-∞) of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The AUC(0-∞) of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal half-life (t½) of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The t½ of STP, VPA, CBD, and CBD major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who experienced an adverse event.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 11 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of participants who experienced an adverse event during the trial is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a clinically significant change in 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG).</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of participants with a clinically significant change in ECG is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a clinically significant change in serum biochemistry.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of participants with a clinically significant change in serum biochemistry is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a clinically significant change in hematology.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of participants with a clinically significant change in hematology is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a clinically significant change in urinalysis.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of participants with a clinically significant change in urinalysis is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a clinically significant change in vital signs.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of participants with a clinically significant change in vital signs (systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, pulse rate) is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a clinically significant change in physical examination.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The number of participants with a clinically significant change in physical examination is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a treatment-emergent suicidality flag.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Suicidality was assessed using the Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS). The number of participants with a treatment-emergent flag is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Seizure frequency by subtype.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>The frequency of each subtype of seizure at baseline and end of treatment is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with a treatment-emergent finding indicative of drug abuse liability.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>Yes</safety_issue>
    <description>Abuse liability was assessed through monitoring of triggering adverse events of interest and study medication accountability discrepancies. Any findings were assigned to an appropriate classification by the investigator. The number of participants with a treatment-emergent finding indicative of drug abuse liability is presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax of delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) and its major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Cmax of THC and its major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax of THC and its major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The Tmax of THC and its major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-t) of THC and its major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The AUC(0-t) of THC and its major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-∞) of THC and its major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The AUC(0-∞) of THC and its major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>t½ of THC and its major metabolites.</measure>
    <time_frame>0, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose.</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The t½ of THC and its major metabolites are presented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STP + GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Administered orally, twice daily (morning and evening; immediately after the participant's STP dose), commencing with up-titration of 100 mg/mL GWP42003-P to a maintenance dose of 20 mg/kg/day over 11 days.
Participants remain on the maintenance dose for a further 14 days. Dosing is tapered (10% each day) for participants who do not enter the open-label-extension (OLE) phase or who withdraw early.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STP + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Administered orally, twice daily (morning and evening; immediately after the participant's STP dose), commencing with up-titration of placebo to an equivalent maintenance dose of 20 mg/kg/day over 11 days.
Participants remain on the maintenance dose for a further 14 days. Dosing is tapered (10% each day) for participants who do not enter the OLE phase or who withdraw early.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VPA + GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Administered orally, twice daily (morning and evening; immediately after the participant's VPA dose), commencing with up-titration of 100 mg/mL GWP42003-P to a maintenance dose of 20 mg/kg/day over 11 days.
Participants remain on the maintenance dose for a further 14 days. Dosing is tapered (10% each day) for participants who do not enter the OLE phase or who withdraw early.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VPA + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Administered orally, twice daily (morning and evening; immediately after the participant's VPA dose), commencing with up-titration of placebo to an equivalent maintenance dose of 20 mg/kg/day over 11 days.
Participants remain on the maintenance dose for a further 14 days. Dosing is tapered (10% each day) for participants who do not enter the OLE phase or who withdraw early.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GWP42003-P</intervention_name>
    <description>Clear, pale yellow, oily solution containing cannabidiol dissolved in the excipients sesame oil and anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener (sucralose) and strawberry flavoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>STP + GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VPA + GWP42003-P</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cannabidiol</other_name>
    <other_name>CBD</other_name>
    <other_name>Epidiolex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Clear, pale yellow, oily solution containing the excipients sesame oil and anhydrous ethanol with added sweetener (sucralose) and strawberry flavoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>STP + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VPA + Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant must be taking STP (for the STP arm) or VPA (for the VPA arm) and no more
             than 2 other antiepileptic drugs (AEDs) during the blinded period of the trial.

               -  In the VPA arm only, the participant must not be receiving STP (VPA allowed in
                  STP arm).

          -  AED doses, including STP or VPA, must be stable for 4 weeks prior to screening and
             regimen must remain stable throughout the duration of the blinded period of the
             trial.

          -  Participant must have a documented magnetic resonance imaging/computerized tomography
             of the brain that ruled out a progressive neurologic condition.

          -  Participant must have experienced at least 1 countable uncontrolled seizure of any
             type (i.e., tonic-clonic, tonic, clonic, atonic, partial onset or focal: focal
             seizures with retained consciousness and a motor component, focal seizures with
             impaired consciousness, focal seizures evolving to bilateral secondary
             generalization) within 2 months prior to randomization.

          -  Intervention with vagus nerve stimulation and/or ketogenic diet must be stable for 4
             weeks prior to baseline and the participant must be willing to maintain a stable
             regimen during the blinded period of the trial.

          -  Participant must abstain from alcohol during the blinded period of the trial.

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant has clinically significant unstable medical conditions other than
             epilepsy.

          -  Participant has a history of symptoms related to a drop in blood pressure due to
             postural changes (e.g., dizziness, light-headedness, blurred vision, palpitations,
             weakness, syncope).

          -  Participant has any history of suicidal behavior or any suicidal ideation of type 4
             or 5 on the C-SSRS in the last month or at screening.

          -  Participant has had clinically relevant symptoms or a clinically significant illness
             in the 4 weeks prior to screening or enrollment, other than epilepsy.

          -  Participant is currently using felbamate and has been taking it for less than 12
             months prior to screening.

          -  Participant has consumed alcohol during the 7 days prior to enrollment and is
             unwilling to abstain during the blinded phase of the trail.

          -  Participant is currently using or has in the past used recreational or medicinal
             cannabis, or synthetic cannabinoid-based medications (including Sativex®) within the
             3 months prior to trial entry.

          -  Participant has any known or suspected history of any drug abuse or addiction.

          -  Participant is unwilling to abstain from recreational or medicinal cannabis, or
             synthetic cannabinoid based medications (including Sativex) for the duration for the
             study.

          -  Participant has consumed grapefruit or grapefruit juice 7 days prior to enrollment
             and is unwilling to abstain from drinking grapefruit juice within 7 days of
             pharmacokinetic visits.

          -  Participant has any known or suspected hypersensitivity to cannabinoids or any of the
             excipients of the Investigational Medicinal Product (IMP), e.g., sesame oil.

          -  Participant has received an IMP within the 12 weeks prior to the screening visit.

          -  Participant has significantly impaired hepatic function at the screening or
             randomization visit, defined as any of the following:

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt; 5 × upper
                  limit of normal (ULN).

               -  ALT or AST &gt; 3 × ULN and total bilirubin (TBL) &gt; 2 × ULN or international
                  normalized ratio (INR) &gt; 1.5.

               -  ALT or AST &gt; 3 × ULN with the presence of fatigue, nausea, vomiting, right upper
                  quadrant pain or tenderness, fever, rash, and/or eosinophilia (&gt; 5%).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>GW Research Medical Information</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0) 1223 266 800</phone>
    <email>medinfo@gwpharm.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 16, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>November 16, 2015</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cannabidiol</keyword>
  <keyword>GWP42003-P</keyword>
  <keyword>Epidiolex</keyword>
  <keyword>Stiripentol</keyword>
  <keyword>Valproate</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>No</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Stiripentol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
