<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="491">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01728077</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N01372</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-000827-42</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01728077</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Long-term Safety, and Efficacy of Brivaracetam (BRV) Used as Adjunctive Treatment in Subjects With Epilepsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Multicenter, Follow-up Study to Evaluate the Long-term Safety and Efficacy of Brivaracetam Used as Adjunctive Treatment in Subjects Aged 16 Years or Older With Epilepsy Phase 3b</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UCB Pharma SA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UCB Pharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>France: Agence Nationale de Sécurité du Médicament et des produits de santé</authority>
    <authority>Germany: Federal Institute for Drugs and Medical Devices</authority>
    <authority>Spain: Spanish Agency of Medicines</authority>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      N01372 study is to evaluate the long-term safety, tolerability, maintenance of efficacy of
      Brivaracetam (BRV); as well as the effect of BRV on subjects' health-related quality of life
      and to explore the direct medical resource use for BRV (for subjects entering N01372 from a
      study where pharmacoeconomic data was collected). BRV will be used at doses up to maximum of
      200 mg/day, as adjunctive treatment in subjects aged 16 years or older with Epilepsy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Flexible dosing up to 200 mg/day, twice daily (10, 25 and 50 mg oral film-coated tablets).
      The study will continue until either regulatory approval of BRV has been granted by any
      Health Authority in an indication of adjunctive treatment of Epilepsy, or until the Sponsor
      decides to close the study, or until the BRV development is stopped by the Sponsor.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety/Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of Treatment Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs) during Evaluation Period</measure>
    <time_frame>From Entry Visit (Month 0) to the Last Evaluation Period Visit or Early Discontinuation Visit (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Withdrawal due to an Adverse Event (AE) during the Evaluation Period</measure>
    <time_frame>From Entry Visit (Month 0) to the Last Evaluation Period Visit or Early Discontinuation Visit (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of a Serious Adverse Event (SAE) during the Evaluation Period</measure>
    <time_frame>From Entry Visit (Month 0) to the Last Evaluation Period Visit or Early Discontinuation Visit (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of Partial-Onset Seizure (POS) Type I per 28 days during the Evaluation Period for subjects with focal-onset Epilepsy</measure>
    <time_frame>From Entry Visit (Month 0) to the Last Evaluation Period Visit or Early Discontinuation Visit (up to 46 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The POS frequency is standardized to a 28-day duration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of reduction in Partial-Onset-Seizure (POS) Type I frequency per 28 days from Baseline of the previous study to the Evaluation Period for subjects with focal-onset Epilepsy entering N01372 from a study where Baseline seizure data was collected</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline of the previous study to the Last Evaluation Period Visit or Early Discontinuation Visit (up to 49 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The POS frequency is standardized to a 28-day duration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>50 % responder rate in Partial-Onset-Seizure (POS) Type I frequency from Baseline of the previous study to the Evaluation Period for subjects with focal-onset Epilepsy entering N01372 from a study where Baseline seizure data was collected</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline of the previous study to the Last Evaluation Period Visit or Early Discontinuation Visit (up to 49 months)</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>The POS frequency is standardized to a 28-day duration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">650</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brivaracetam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>At Entry Visit (EV), subjects will start on the individualized Brivaracetam (BRV) dose that they had reached at the completion of the previous study. Dose adjustments of the Investigational Medicinal Product (IMP) are allowed at any time based on the clinical judgment of the investigator. The BRV dose can be increased or decreased in increments of 50 mg/day based on the individual subject's seizure control and/or tolerability; however, the BRV dose should not exceed 200 mg/day during the study and must always be administered as a symmetrical morning and evening dose. Upon completion or early discontinuation from this study, there will be a Down-Titration Period in steps of 50 mg/day on a weekly basis until 20 mg/day for 1 week is reached, followed by a Post-Treatment Period (between 2 and 4 weeks) during which the subject will not receive study drug. No down-Titration Period will be applicable if subjects are continued on BRV after they complete this study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brivaracetam</intervention_name>
    <description>Flexible dosing, can up and down-titrate as needed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Brivaracetam</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>UCB34714</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is male or female and 16 years or older. Subjects under 18 years of age may
             be included only where legally permitted and ethically accepted

          -  Subjects having completed the Treatment Period of an applicable previous BRV study,
             and have access to the present study

          -  Subject for whom the investigator believes a reasonable benefit from the long-term
             administration of BRV may be expected

          -  Female subjects without childbearing potential (postmenopausal for at least 2 years,
             bilateral oophorectomy or tubal ligation, complete hysterectomy) are eligible. Female
             subjects with childbearing potential are eligible if they use a medically accepted
             contraceptive method

          -  Subjects must be able to take the oral film-coated tablets of BRV

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has developed hypersensitivity to any components of the Investigational
             Medicinal Product (IMP) or comparative drugs as stated in the protocol during the
             course of the prior study

          -  Severe medical, neurological, or psychiatric disorders, or laboratory values that may
             have an impact on the safety of the subject

          -  Poor compliance with the visit schedule or medication intake in the previous BRV
             study

          -  Planned participation in any other clinical study of another investigational drug or
             device during this study

          -  Pregnant or lactating woman

          -  Any medical condition which, in the investigator's opinion, warrants exclusion

          -  Subject has a lifetime history of suicide attempt (including an actual attempt,
             interrupted attempt, or aborted attempt), or has suicidal ideation in the past 6
             months as indicated by a positive response (&quot;Yes&quot;) to either question 4 or question 5
             of the Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) at the last visit of the
             previous study or at the Entry Visit of this study if not completed at the last visit
             of the previous study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>UCB Clinical Trial Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>+1 877 822 9493 (UCB)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>103</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>108</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>109</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>106</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akron</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>110</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>102</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>201</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>303</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bernau</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>300</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kehl-Kork</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>502</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>October 8, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>October 26, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brivaracetam</keyword>
  <keyword>Long-term Follow-up</keyword>
  <keyword>Epilepsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Partial Onset Seizures</keyword>
  <keyword>Adjunctive treatment</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
