<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="375">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02535091</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>YKP3089C021</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02535091</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Pharmacokinetic Study of YKP3089 as Adjunctive Therapy in Subjects With Partial Onset Seizures</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Multicenter, Safety and Pharmacokinetic Study of YKP3089 as Adjunctive Therapy in Subjects With Partial Onset Seizures</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SK Life Science</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SK Life Science</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Food and Drug Administration</authority>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, open label study to assess the safety and pharmacokinetics of YKP3089
      as adjunctive therapy in subjects with partial onset seizures. Initially, subjects taking
      phenytoin or phenobarbital will be enrolled followed by additional subjects taking
      anti-epileptic drugs other than phenytoin and phenobarbital to further investigate long-term
      safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Endpoint Classification: Safety Study, Intervention Model: Single Group Assignment, Masking: Open Label, Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the pharmacokinetics of YKP3089 and concomitant Antiepileptic Drugs (AEDs)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Change from baseline of trough plasma concentrations of YKP3089 and concomitant AEDs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>All observed or volunteered AEs and SAEs regardless of suspected causal relationship to the investigational product to be reported</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Laboratory Test Abnormalities (Hematology)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Hematology data will be analyzed by central laboratories.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Laboratory Test Abnormalities (Chemistry)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Chemistry data will be analyzed by central laboratories</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Laboratory Test Abnormalities (Urinalysis)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Urinalysis data will be analyzed by central laboratories</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Vital Sign Results of Potential Clinical Importance</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Vital signs include sitting blood pressure, respiration rate, heart rate and temperature. Potential clinical importance to be determined according to investigator clinical judgement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">490</enrollment>
  <condition>Partial Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>YKP3089 Adjunctive Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>YKP3089</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>YKP3089 Adjunctive Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of partial epilepsy according to the International League Against
             Epilepsy's Classification of Epileptic Seizures.

          -  Have uncontrolled partial seizures and require additional Antiepileptic Drug (AED)
             therapy despite having been treated with at least one Antiepileptic Drug (AED) within
             approximately the last 2 years.

          -  Currently on stable antiepileptic treatment regimen.

          -  Computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan performed within
             the past 10 years that ruled out a progressive cause of epilepsy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of serious systemic disease, including hepatic insufficiency, renal
             insufficiency, a malignant neoplasm, any disorder in which prognosis for survival is
             less than 3 months, or any disorder which in the judgment of the investigator will
             place the subject at excessive risk by participation in a controlled trial.

          -  Subjects taking phenytoin must not be taking phenobarbital or primidone; subjects
             taking phenobarbital must not be taking phenytoin or primidone.

          -  Subjects taking concomitant Antiepileptic Drugs (AEDs) other than phenytoin or
             phenobarbital, must not be taking phenytoin or phenobarbital or primidone.

          -  Subjects with clinical evidence of phenytoin or phenobarbital toxicity.

          -  A history of nonepileptic or psychogenic seizures.

          -  Presence of only nonmotor simple partial seizures or primary generalized epilepsies.

          -  Presence or previous history of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome.

          -  Scheduled epilepsy surgery within 8 months after Visit 1.

          -  Subjects implanted with or planning to have implantation of deep brain stimulator.

          -  Any clinically significant laboratory abnormality that in the opinion of the
             investigator would exclude the subject from the study.

          -  Evidence of significant active hepatic disease.

          -  An active Central Nervous System (CNS) infection, demyelinating disease, degenerative
             neurologic disease, or any Central Nervous System (CNS) disease deemed to be
             progressive during the course of the study that may confound the interpretation of
             the study results.

          -  Any clinically significant psychiatric illness, psychological, or behavioral problems
             that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with the subject's ability
             to participate in the study.

          -  Presence of psychotic disorders and/or unstable recurrent affective disorders evident
             by use of antipsychotics; presence or recent history (within 6 months) of major
             depressive episode.

          -  History of alcoholism, drug abuse, or drug addiction within the past 2 years.

          -  Current use of felbamate with less than 18 months of continuous exposure.

          -  Current or recent (within the past year) use of vigabatrin or ezogabine.

          -  History of status epilepticus within 3 months of Visit 1.

          -  History of any serious drug-induced hypersensitivity reaction (including but not
             limited to Stevens Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis, drug reaction with
             eosinophilia and systemic symptoms) or any drug-related rash requiring
             hospitalization.

          -  History of AED-associated rash that involved conjunctiva or mucosae or more than one
             maculopapular rash that required discontinuation.

          -  Screening laboratory investigation demonstrates abnormal renal function.

          -  Absolute neutrophil count less than 1500/μL.

          -  Clinical or Electrocardiogram (ECG) evidence of serious cardiac disease, including
             ischemic heart disease, uncontrolled heart failure, and major arrhythmias, or
             relevant replicated changes in QT intervals.

          -  Platelet counts lower than 80,000/μL in subjects treated with Valproic Acid (VPA).

          -  A &quot;yes&quot; answer to Question 1 or 2 of the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale
             (C-SSRS) (Baseline/Screening version) Ideation Section in the past 6 months or a
             &quot;yes&quot; answer to any of the Suicidal Behavior Questions in the past 2 years.

          -  More than 1 lifetime suicide attempt.

          -  Participation in any other trials involving an investigational product or device
             within 30 days of screening.

          -  Current use of any of the following medications: clopidogrel, fluvoxamine,
             amitriptyline, clomipramine, bupropion, methadone, ifosfamide, cyclophosphamide,
             efavirenz, fosphenytoin, ethotoin, mephenytoin, or natural progesterone (within 1
             month of Visit 1).

          -  History of positive antibody/antigen test for hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or HIV.

          -  Presence of congenital short QT syndrome.

          -  A history of previous exposure to YKP3089.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>O Senanan, MS</last_name>
    <phone>201-421-3885</phone>
    <email>oranuch@sk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>P Ilankumaran, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>201-421-3810</phone>
    <email>pilan@sk.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Trials, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dusty Holderfield</last_name>
      <phone>501-227-5061</phone>
      <phone_ext>123</phone_ext>
      <email>dholderfield@clinicaltrialsinc.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Victor Biton, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mid-Atlantic Epilepsy and Sleep Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Arkady Barber, RN</last_name>
      <email>barbera@epilesydc.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pavel Klein, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Austin Epilepsy Care Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78758</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheryle Yarborough</last_name>
      <phone>512-339-8831</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>November 24, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 21, 2015</firstreceived_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsies, Partial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
