<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="857">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on November 27, 2015</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01663545</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120182</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-N-0182</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01663545</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brain P-gp and Inflammation in People With Epilepsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Positron Emission Tomography Measurement of Neuroinflammation and P-glycoprotein in Localization-Related Epilepsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Federal Government</authority>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  The brain is protected by a barrier that keeps toxins in the blood from reaching the
           brain. However, this barrier can also keep useful medications from reaching the brain.
           P-glycoprotein (P-gp) is a brain protein that is part of the blood-brain barrier. The
           level of P-gp is higher in people with epilepsy than in people without epilepsy. These
           different levels of P-gp may explain why some people have seizures that do not respond
           well to medications. Researchers want to see if P-gp can affect the response to
           epilepsy medications.

        -  Epilepsy may also be associated with brain inflammation. Researchers also want to look
           at the part of the brain affected by epilepsy to see if inflammation is present.

      Objectives:

        -  To see if P-gp can affect the response to epilepsy medications.

        -  To see if inflammation is present in the part of the brain affected by epilepsy.

      Eligibility:

        -  &lt; TAB&gt; Individuals between 18 and 60 years of age who have temporal lobe epilepsy. We
           plan to study some patients whose seizures are well controlled by drugs, and some whose
           seizures are not controlled.

        -  &lt; TAB&gt;

        -  Healthy volunteers between 18 and 60 years of age.

      Design:

        -  This study requires four or five visits to the NIH Clinical Center over the course of a
           year. The visits will be outpatient visits and will last from 2 to 5 hours.

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected.

        -  All participants will have two positron emission tomography (PET) scans. The scans will
           take place during different visits. Different drugs will be used in each scan. One drug
           will be used to temporarily block the effect of P-gp in the brain. The other drug will
           show areas of inflammation in the brain.

        -  Participants with epilepsy will have a third PET scan. This scan will also look at P-gp
           activity in the brain. However, it will not use the drug that blocks the effect of
           P-gp.

        -  All participants will also have one magnetic resonance imaging scan. This scan will
           help show brain function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives

      1) To investigate the relationship between permeability-glycoprotein (P-gp) function,
      neuroinflammation, and drug-resistance in participants with temporal lobe epilepsy (TLE). 2)
      To attempt to detect an increased level of inflammation in epileptic foci. 3) To assess
      theeffect of genetic polymorphisms of P-gp on brain uptake of [11C]dLop and of genetic
      polymorphisms of TSPO on brain uptake of [11C]PBR28.

      Study population

      25 participants with drug-resistant focal epilepsy; 25 participants with drug responsive
      focal epilepsy; and 25 healthy volunteers.

      Design

      Screening of enrolled participants will include a medical history, physical exam,
      electrocardiogram (ECG), and blood and urine laboratory testing. Blood samples will also be
      used for genetic polymorphism study. Healthy volunteers will receive two brain positron
      emission tomography (PET) scans with [11C]dLop and [11C]PBR28. Epilepsy participants will
      receive three PET scans (2 with [11C]dLop and 1 with [11C]PBR28). Everyone will receive a
      brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). Because [11C]dLop uptake is influenced by blood
      flow, a [15O]H2O scan will also be performed to determine flow to the brain before each
      [11C]dLop scan. The [11C]dLop scan will be performed during infusion of intravenous
      tariquidar at up to 2 mg/kg, to partially block brain P-gp and ensure that some [11C]dLop
      enters the brain.

      Outcome measures

      The primary outcome measure will be the amount of differential [11C]dLop and [11C]PBR28
      uptake between the epileptic focus and the homologous contralateral region. [11C]dLop brain
      uptake will be measured in terms of standardized uptake values (SUV). SUV reflects the
      measured brain radioactivity after tracer injection, corrected for patient weight and
      injected activity. [11C]PBR28 distribution volume (VT) will be measured using an arterial
      input function. We want to quantify the tracer VT in regions of the brain distant from the
      epileptic focus, which may be affected by the disease. For this kind of quantification, the
      SUV is unsuitable, because it provides only a crude estimate of brain uptake, without taking
      into account the rate of delivery from the blood.

      After P-gp blocking with tariquidar, we expect, in participants with drug-resistant
      epilepsy, that the amount of [11C]dLop uptake on the side of the epileptic focus will be
      lower than in the contralateral side. This difference will be significantly greater than the
      side-to side difference found in healthy participants. We expect an intermediate difference
      in the population of drug-responsive epilepsy participants. [11C]dLop uptake will be
      corrected for cerebral blood flow using [15O]H2 O PET.

      We also hypothesize that TLE will be associated with brain inflammation and, therefore, that
      [11C]PBR28 uptake in the affected side of the brain will be higher than in the contralateral
      side. We will explore whether the degree of inflammation correlates with drug resistance and
      [11C]dLop uptake.

      Finally, we will perform genetic testing to study the effect of polymorphisms of P-gp on
      brain uptake of [11C]dLop and with inhibition by tariquidar. The primary polymorphism
      (C3435T) of interest is the one that has been associated with drug resistance in epilepsy.
      We will also study the polymorphism of the translocator protein (TSPO), because TSPO
      polymorphism has an influence on [11C]PBR28 binding. This polymorphism is due to the
      non-conservative amino-acid substitution at position 147 from alanine to threonine
      (Ala147Thr) in the fifth transmembrane domain of the TSPO protein. If new genetic findings
      are published in the literature about epilepsy and its relationship with inflammation and
      efflux transporters, we may perform other types of genetic testing on the blood samples we
      have collected. Prospective approval from the IRB will be obtained for any genetic testing
      that has clinical implications for participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <study_design>Time Perspective: Prospective</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A secondary goal is to determine if inhibiting P-gp with tariquidar results in increased concentrations of anti-epileptic medications into the CSF, as a surrogate marker for increased penetration of these medications into the central nervous sys...</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsies, Partial</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        For patients

          -  Age 18-60.

          -  Able to give written informed consent.

          -  Drug resistant participants will be defined as having clinically documented partial
             seizures with consistent EEG evidence as defined by the 1981 International
             Classification of Epileptic Seizures, refractory to standard antiepileptic treatment
             for at least one year prior to enrolling in this study and with an average of at
             least one seizure per week. This criterion will be established by preliminary
             screening in the NINDS Clinical Epilepsy Section outpatient clinic under protocol
             01-N-0139, and if necessary, inpatient video-EEG monitoring. Seizure focus
             localization will be determined by standard clinical, neurophysiologic, and imaging
             studies.

          -  Drug-responsive participants will be defined as having clinically documented partial
             seizures with consistent EEG evidence as defined by the 1981 International
             Classification of Epileptic Seizures, responsive to standard antiepileptic treatment
             for at least three months prior to enrolling in this study. This criterion will be
             established by preliminary screening in the NINDS Clinical Epilepsy Section
             outpatient clinic under protocol 01-N-0139, and if necessary, inpatient video-EEG
             monitoring. Seizure focus localization will be determined by standard clinical,
             neurophysiologic, and imaging studies.

          -  Negative toxicology testing at the time of screening.

          -  No prior diagnosis of drug or alcohol abuse or dependence.

        For healthy volunteers

          -  Age 18-60.

          -  Able to give written informed consent.

          -  No prior diagnosis of drug or alcohol abuse or dependence.rom the blood.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        For patients

          -  Previous radiation exposure (X-rays, PET scans etc.) that, together with study
             procedures, would exceed NIH RSC research limits.

          -  Claustrophobia to a degree that the subject would feel uncomfortable in the MRI
             machine.

          -  History of brain disease other than epilepsy.

          -  Cannot lie on their back for at least two hours.

          -  Use of medications that may interfere with P-gp function in the 16 days before
             Tariquidar administration, except clinically needed antiepileptic drugs. For
             reference we have included a list of medications that may interfere with P-gp
             function. Drugs should be avoided for a period of 16 days before Tariquidar to one
             week after.

          -  Known cause for seizures, other than mesial temporal sclerosis, such as tumor or
             infection.

          -  Serious medical illness, other than epilepsy.

          -  Clinically significant laboratory abnormalities.

          -  Positive test for HIV.

          -  Brain abnormality such as a brain tumor, stroke, brain damage from head trauma or
             blood vessel abnormalities, on an MRI scan.

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding.

          -  Able to get pregnant but does not use birth control.

          -  Risk for MRI scan, such as a pacemaker or other implanted electrical devices, brain
             stimulators, some types of dental implants, aneurysm clips (metal clips on the wall
             of a large artery), metallic prostheses (including metal pins and rods, heart valves,
             and cochlear implants), permanent eyeliner, implanted delivery pump, or shrapnel
             fragments. Welders and metal workers are also at risk for injury because of possible
             small metal fragments in the eye of which they may be unaware.

          -  PBR28 non-binders.

          -  For drug-responsive subjects: occurrence of a seizure within the last three months.

        For healthy volunteers

          -  Any current Axis I diagnosis.

          -  Clinically significant laboratory abnormalities.

          -  Positive test for HIV.

          -  Unable to have a MRI Scan.

          -  History of neurologic illness or injury with the potential to affect study data
             interpretation.

          -  History of seizures, other than in childhood and related to fever.

          -  Recent exposure to radiation (i.e., PET from other research) which when combined with
             this study would be above the allowable limits.

          -  Inability to lie flat on camera bed for at least two hours.

          -  Use of medications that interfere with P-gp function in the two weeks before
             Tariquidar administration. For reference we have included a list of medications that
             may interfere with P-gp function. Drugs should be avoided for a period of two weeks
             before Tariquidar to one week after.

          -  PBR28 non-binders

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding.

          -  Able to get pregnant but does not use birth control.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William H Theodore, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patricia M Reeves-Tyer, R. EEG T.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-1923</phone>
    <email>tyerp@ninds.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>William H Theodore, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-1505</phone>
    <email>theodorw@ninds.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Patient Recruitment and Public Liaison Office (PRPL)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@mail.cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2012-N-0182.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aronica E, Gorter JA, Redeker S, van Vliet EA, Ramkema M, Scheffer GL, Scheper RJ, van der Valk P, Leenstra S, Baayen JC, Spliet WG, Troost D. Localization of breast cancer resistance protein (BCRP) in microvessel endothelium of human control and epileptic brain. Epilepsia. 2005 Jun;46(6):849-57.</citation>
    <PMID>15946326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aronica E, Boer K, van Vliet EA, Redeker S, Baayen JC, Spliet WG, van Rijen PC, Troost D, da Silva FH, Wadman WJ, Gorter JA. Complement activation in experimental and human temporal lobe epilepsy. Neurobiol Dis. 2007 Jun;26(3):497-511. Epub 2007 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>17412602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boer K, Troost D, Spliet WG, van Rijen PC, Gorter JA, Aronica E. Cellular distribution of vascular endothelial growth factor A (VEGFA) and B (VEGFB) and VEGF receptors 1 and 2 in focal cortical dysplasia type IIB. Acta Neuropathol. 2008 Jun;115(6):683-96. doi: 10.1007/s00401-008-0354-6. Epub 2008 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18317782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>February 26, 2015</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>August 8, 2012</firstreceived_date>
  <keyword>Epilepsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Epileptic Focus</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>P-Glycoprotein</keyword>
  <keyword>PET Imaging</keyword>
  <is_fda_regulated>No</is_fda_regulated>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsies, Partial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                -->
</clinical_study>
